<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Most royal majesty,
	I crave no more than hath your highness offer'd,
	Nor will you tender less.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	I know no answer.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Pardon me, royal sir;
	Election makes not up on such conditions.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Royal Lear,
	Give but that portion which yourself propos'd,
	And here I take Cordelia by the hand,
	Duchess of Burgundy.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	I am sorry, then, you have so lost a father
	That you must lose a husband.
