<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	Dear sir, forbear.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	How now, my noble friend! since I came hither,—
	Which I can call but now,—I have heard strange news.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	Nor I, assure thee, Regan.
	Edmund, I hear that you have shown your father
	A child-like office.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	Is he pursu'd?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	If he be taken he shall never more
	Be fear'd of doing harm; make your own purpose,
	How in my strength you please. For you, Edmund,
	Whose virtue and obedience doth this instant
	So much commend itself, you shall be ours:
	Natures of such deep trust we shall much need;
	You we first seize on.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	You know not why we came to visit you,—
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Keep peace, upon your lives:
	He dies that strikes again. What is the matter?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	What is your difference? speak.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Thou art a strange fellow; a tailor make a man?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Speak yet, how grew your quarrel?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Peace, sirrah!
	You beastly knave, know you no reverence?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Why art thou angry?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	What! art thou mad, old fellow?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	Why dost thou call him knave? What is his fault?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	No more, perchance, does mine, nor his, nor hers.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	This is some fellow,
	Who, having been prais'd for bluntness, doth affect
	A saucy roughness, and constrains the garb
	Quite from his nature: he cannot flatter, he,
	An honest mind and plain, he must speak truth:
	An they will take it, so; if not, he's plain.
	These kind of knaves I know, which in this plainness
	Harbour more craft and more corrupter ends
	Than twenty silly-ducking observants,
	That stretch their duties nicely.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	What mean'st by this?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	What was the offence you gave him?
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Fetch forth the stocks!
	You stubborn ancient knave, you reverend braggart,
	We'll teach you.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Fetch forth the stocks! As I have life and honour,
	There shall he sit till noon.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	This is a fellow of the self-same colour
	Our sister speaks of. Come, bring away the stocks.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	I'll answer that.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	Hail to your Grace!
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	Fie, air, fie!
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	What trumpet's that?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 4><43%>
	What means your Grace?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 4><43%>
	I set him there, sir: but his own disorders
	Deserv'd much less advancement.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	Let us withdraw; 'twill be a storm.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	Follow'd the old man forth. He is return'd.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	Whither is he going?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	'Tis best to give him way; he leads himself.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	Shut up your doors, my lord; 'tis a wild night:
	My Regan counsels well: come out o' the storm.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 5><57%>
	I will have my revenge ere I depart his house.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 5><57%>
	I now perceive it was not altogether your brother's evil disposition made him seek his death; but a provoking merit, set a-work by a reproveable badness in himself.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 5><57%>
	Go with me to the duchess.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 5><58%>
	True, or false, it hath made thee Earl of Gloucester. Seek out where thy father is, that he may be ready for our apprehension.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 5><58%>
	I will lay trust upon thee; and thou shalt find a dearer father in my love.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 7><61%>
	Post speedily to my lord your husband; show him this letter: the army of France is landed. Seek out the traitor Gloucester.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 7><62%>
	Leave him to my displeasure. Edmund, keep you our sister company: the revenges we are bound to take upon your traitorous father are not fit for your beholding. Advise the duke, where you are going, to a most festinate preparation: we are bound to the like. Our posts shall be swift and intelligent betwixt us. Farewell, dear sister: farewell, my Lord of Gloucester.
	How now? Where's the king?
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 7><62%>
	Get horses for your mistress.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 7><62%>
	Edmund, farewell.
	Go seek the traitor Gloucester,
	Pinion him like a thief, bring him before us.
	Though well we may not pass upon his life
	Without the form of justice, yet our power
	Shall do a courtesy to our wrath, which men
	May blame but not control. Who's there? The traitor?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 7><62%>
	Bind fast his corky arms.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 7><62%>
	Bind him, I say.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	To this chair bind him. Villain, thou shalt find—
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	Come, sir, what letters had you late from France?
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	And what confederacy have you with the traitors
	Late footed in the kingdom?
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	Cunning.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	Where hast thou sent the king?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	Wherefore to Dover? Let him answer that.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 3><SCENE 7><64%>
	See 't shalt thou never. Fellows, hold the chair.
	Upon these eyes of thine I'll set my foot.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 3><SCENE 7><64%>
	If you see vengeance.—
<SPEECH 52><ACT 3><SCENE 7><64%>
	My villain!
<SPEECH 53><ACT 3><SCENE 7><64%>
	Lest it see more, prevent it. Out, vile jelly!
	Where is thy lustre now?
<SPEECH 54><ACT 3><SCENE 7><65%>
	I have receiv'd a hurt. Follow me, lady.
	Turn out that eyeless villain; throw this slave
	Upon the dunghill. Regan, I bleed apace:
	Untimely comes this hurt. Give me your arm.
