<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Sir, I love you more than words can wield the matter;
	Dearer than eye-sight, space, and liberty;
	Beyond what can be valu'd, rich or rare;
	No less than life, with grace, health, beauty, honour;
	As much as child e'er lov'd, or father found;
	A love that makes breath poor and speech unable;
	Beyond all manner of so much I love you.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	Let your study
	Be to content your lord, who hath receiv'd you
	At fortune's alms; you have obedience scanted,
	And well are worth the want that you have wanted.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	Sister, it is not little I have to say of what most nearly appertains to us both. I think our father will hence to-night.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	You see how full of changes his age is; the observation we have made of it hath not been little: he always loved our sister most; and with what poor judgment he hath now cast her off appears too grossly.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	The best and soundest of his time hath been but rash; then, must we look to receive from his age, not alone the imperfections of long-engraffed condition, but, therewithal the unruly waywardness that infirm and choleric years bring with them.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	There is further compliment of leave-taking between France and him. Pray you, let us hit together: if our father carry authority with such dispositions as he bears, this last surrender of his will but offend us.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	We must do something, and i' the heat.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 3><15%>
	Did my father strike my gentleman for chiding of his fool?
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 3><15%>
	By day and night he wrongs me; every hour
	He flashes into one gross crime or other,
	That sets us all at odds: I'll not endure it:
	His knights grow riotous, and himself upbraids us
	On every trifle. When he returns from hunting
	I will not speak with him; say I am sick:
	If you come slack of former services,
	You shall do well; the fault of it I'll answer.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 3><15%>
	Put on what weary negligence you please,
	You and your fellows; I'd have it come to question:
	If he distaste it, let him to my sister,
	Whose mind and mine, I know, in that are one,
	Not to be over-rul'd. Idle old man,
	That still would manage those authorities
	That he hath given away! Now, by my life,
	Old fools are babes again, and must be us'd
	With cheeks as flatteries, when they are seen abus'd.
	Remember what I have said.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 3><16%>
	And let his knights have colder looks among you;
	What grown of it, no matter; advise your fellows so:
	I would breed from hence occasions, and I shall,
	That I may speak: I'll write straight to my sister
	To hold my very source. Prepare for dinner.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 4><21%>
	Not only, sir, this your all-licens'd fool,
	But other of your insolent retinue
	Do hourly carp and quarrel, breaking forth
	In rank and not-to-be-endured riots. Sir,
	I had thought, by making this well known unto you,
	To have found a safe redress; but now grow fearful,
	By what yourself too late have spoke and done.
	That you protect this course, and put it on
	By your allowance; which if you should, the fault
	Would not 'scape censure, nor the redresses sleep,
	Which, in the tender of a wholesome weal,
	Might in their working do you that offence,
	Which else were shame, that then necessity
	Will call discreet proceeding.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 4><22%>
	I would you would make use of your good wisdom,
	Whereof I know you are fraught; and put away
	These dispositions which of late transform you
	From what you rightly are.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 4><22%>
	This admiration, sir, is much o' the favour
	Of other your new pranks. I do beseech you
	To understand my purposes aright:
	As you are old and reverend, should be wise.
	Here do you keep a hundred knights and squires;
	Men so disorder'd, so debosh'd, and bold,
	That this our court, infected with their manners,
	Shows like a riotous inn: epicurism and lust
	Make it more like a tavern or a brothel
	Than a grac'd palace. The shame itself doth speak
	For instant remedy; be then desir'd
	By her that else will take the thing she begs,
	A little to disquantity your train;
	And the remainder, that shall still depend,
	To be such men as may besort your age,
	Which know themselves and you.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 4><23%>
	You strike my people, and your disorder'd rabble
	Make servants of their betters.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 4><24%>
	Never afflict yourself to know the cause;
	But let his disposition have that scope
	That dotage gives it.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 4><25%>
	Do you mark that?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 4><25%>
	Pray you, content. What, Oswald, ho!
	</STAGE DIR> You, sir, more knave than fool, after your master.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 4><25%>
	This man hath had good counsel. A hundred knights!
	'Tis politic and safe to let him keep
	At point a hundred knights; yes, that on every dream,
	Each buzz, each fancy, each complaint, dislike,
	He may enguard his dotage with their powers,
	And hold our lives in mercy. Oswald, I say!
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 4><25%>
	Safer than trust too far.
	Let me still take away the harms I fear,
	Not fear still to be taken: I know his heart.
	What he hath utter'd I have writ my sister;
	If she sustain him and his hundred knights,
	When I have show'd the unfitness,—
	How now, Oswald!
	What! have you writ that letter to my sister?
<SPEECH 21><ACT 1><SCENE 4><25%>
	Take you some company, and away to horse:
	Inform her full of my particular fear;
	And thereto add such reasons of your own
	As may compact it more. Get you gone,
	And hasten your return. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> No, no, my lord,
	This milky gentleness and course of yours
	Though I condemn not, yet, under pardon,
	You are much more attask'd for want of wisdom
	Than prais'd for harmful mildness.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 1><SCENE 4><26%>
	Nay, then—
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 4><43%>
	Why not by the hand, sir? How have I offended?
	All's not offence that indiscretion finds
	And dotage terms so.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 4><43%>
	At your choice, sir.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 4><44%>
	Why might not you, my lord, receive attendance
	From those that she calls servants, or from mine?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 4><45%>
	Hear me, my lord.
	What need you five-and-twenty, ten, or five,
	To follow in a house, where twice so many
	Have a command to tend you?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	'Tis his own blame; hath put himself from rest,
	And must needs taste his folly.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	So am I purpos'd.
	Where is my Lord of Gloucester?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	My lord, entreat him by no means to stay.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 7><62%>
	Pluck out his eyes.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 7><62%>
	Farewell, sweet lord, and sister.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	Welcome, my lord; I marvel our mild husband
	Not met us on the way. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Now, where's your master?
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	</STAGE DIR> Then, shall you go no further.
	It is the cowish terror of his spirit
	That dares not undertake; he'll not feel wrongs
	Which tie him to an answer. Our wishes on the way
	May prove effects. Back, Edmund, to my brother;
	Hasten his musters and conduct his powers:
	I must change arms at home, and give the distaff
	Into my husband's hands. This trusty servant
	Shall pass between us; ere long you are like to hear,
	If you dare venture in your own behalf,
	A mistress's command. Wear this; spare speech;
	Decline your head: this kiss, if it durst speak,
	Would stretch thy spirits up into the air.
	Conceive, and fare thee well.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 2><69%>
	My most dear Gloucester!
	O! the difference of man and man!
	To thee a woman's services are due:
	My fool usurps my bed.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 2><69%>
	I have been worth the whistle.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 2><69%>
	No more; the text is foolish.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 2><69%>
	Milk-liver'd man!
	That bear'st a cheek for blows, a head for wrongs;
	Who hast not in thy brows an eye discerning
	Thine honour from thy suffering; that not know'st
	Fools do those villains pity who are punish'd
	Ere they have done their mischief. Where's thy drum?
	France spreads his banners in our noiseless land,
	With plumed helm thy slayer begins threats,
	Whilst thou, a moral fool, sitt'st still, and criest
	'Alack! why does he so?'
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	O vain fool!
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	Marry, your manhood.—Mew!
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	</STAGE DIR> One way I like this well;
	But being widow, and my Gloucester with her,
	May all the building in my fancy pluck
	Upon my hateful life: another way,
	This news is not so tart. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> I'll read and answer.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	</STAGE DIR> I had rather lose the battle than that sister
	Should loosen him and me.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Combine together 'gainst the enemy;
	For these domestic and particular broils
	Are not the question here.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	No.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	</STAGE DIR> O, ho! I know the riddle. <span class="stage>[Aloud.] I will go.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	Not so hot;
	In his own grace he doth exalt himself
	More than in your addition.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	That were the most, if he should husband you.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	Holla, holla!
	That eye that told you so look'd but a-squint.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	Mean you to enjoy him?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	An interlude!
<SPEECH 50><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	</STAGE DIR> If not, I'll ne'er trust medicine.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	This is practice, Gloucester:
	By the law of arms thou wast not bound to answer
	An unknown opposite; thou art not vanquish'd,
	But cozen'd and beguil'd.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 5><SCENE 3><95%>
	Say, if I do, the laws are mine, not thine:
	Who can arraign me for 't?
