<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	I am made of that self metal as my sister,
	And prize me at her worth. In my true heart
	I find she names my very deed of love;
	Only she comes too short: that I profess
	Myself an enemy to all other joys
	Which the most precious square of sense possesses
	And find I am alone felicitate
	In your dear highness' love.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	Prescribe not us our duties.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	That's most certain, and with you; next month with us.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	'Tis the infirmity of his age; yet he hath ever but slenderly known himself.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	Such unconstant starts are we like to have from him as this of Kent's banishment.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	We shall further think on't.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	If it be true, all vengeance comes too short
	Which can pursue the offender. How dost, my lord?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	What! did my father's godson seek your life?
	He whom my father nam'd? your Edgar?
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	Was he not companion with the riotous knights
	That tend upon my father?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	No marvel then though he were ill affected;
	'Tis they have put him on the old man's death,
	To have the expense and waste of his revenues.
	I have this present evening from my sister
	Been well-inform'd of them, and with such cautions
	That if they come to sojourn at my house,
	I'll not be there.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	Thus out of season, threading dark-ey'd night:
	Occasions, noble Gloucester, of some prize,
	Wherein we must have use of your advice.
	Our father he hath writ, so hath our sister,
	Of differences, which I best thought it fit
	To answer from our home; the several messengers
	From hence attend dispatch. Our good old friend,
	Lay comforts to your bosom, and bestow
	Your needful counsel to our businesses,
	Which craves the instant use.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	The messengers from our sister and the king.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Till noon! Till night, my lord; and all night too.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Sir, being his knave, I will.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	My sister may receive it much more worse
	To have her gentleman abus'd, assaulted,
	For following her affairs. Put in his legs.
	Come, my good lord, away.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	I am glad to see your highness.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	I pray you, sir, take patience. I have hope
	You less know how to value her desert
	Than she to scant her duty.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	I cannot think my sister in the least
	Would fail her obligation: if, sir, perchance
	She have restrain'd the riots of your followers,
	'Tis on such ground, and to such wholesome end,
	As clears her from all blame.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 4><41%>
	O, sir! you are old;
	Nature in you stands on the very verge
	Of her confine: you should be rul'd and led
	By some discretion that discerns your state
	Better than you yourself. Therefore I pray you
	That to our sister you do make return;
	Say, you have wrong'd her, sir.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	Good sir, no more; these are unsightly tricks:
	Return you to my sister.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	O the blest gods! So will you wish on me,
	When the rash mood is on.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	Good sir, to the purpose.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 4><42%>
	I know't, my sister's; this approves her letter,
	That she would soon be here. Is your lady come?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 4><43%>
	I pray you, father, being weak, seem so.
	If, till the expiration of your month,
	You will return and sojourn with my sister,
	Dismissing half your train, come then to me:
	I am now from home, and out of that provision
	Which shall be needful for your entertainment.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 4><44%>
	Not altogether so:
	I look'd not for you yet, nor am provided
	For your fit welcome. Give ear, sir, to my sister;
	For those that mingle reason with your passion
	Must be content to think you old, and so—
	But she knows what she does.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 4><44%>
	I dare avouch it, sir: what! fifty followers?
	Is it not well? What should you need of more?
	Yea, or so many, sith that both charge and danger
	Speak 'gainst so great a number? How, in one house,
	Should many people, under two commands,
	Hold amity? 'Tis hard; almost impossible.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 4><44%>
	Why not, my lord? If then they chanc'd to slack you
	We could control them. If you will come to me,—
	For now I spy a danger,—I entreat you
	To bring but five-and-twenty; to no more
	Will I give place or notice.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 4><44%>
	And in good time you gave it
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 4><45%>
	And speak't again, my lord; no more with me.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 4><45%>
	What need one?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	This house is little: the old man and his people
	Cannot be well bestow'd.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	For his particular, I'll receive him gladly,
	But not one follower.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 4><46%>
	O! sir, to wilful men,
	The injuries that they themselves procure
	Must be their schoolmasters. Shut up your doors;
	He is attended with a desperate train,
	And what they may incense him to, being apt
	To have his ear abus'd, wisdom bids fear.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 7><62%>
	Hang him instantly.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 7><62%>
	Ingrateful fox! 'tis he.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	Hard, hard. O filthy traitor!
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	So white, and such a traitor!
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	Be simple-answer'd, for we know the truth.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	To whose hands have you sent the lunatic king?
	Speak.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	And false.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	Wherefore to Dover? Wast thou not charg'd at peril—
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 7><63%>
	Wherefore to Dover?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 7><64%>
	One side will mock another; the other too.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 7><64%>
	How now, you dog!
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 7><64%>
	Give me thy sword. A peasant stand up thus!
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 7><64%>
	Out, treacherous villain!
	Thou call'st on him that hates thee; it was he
	That made the overture of thy treasons to us,
	Who is too good to pity thee.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 7><65%>
	Go thrust him out at gates, and let him smell
	His way to Dover. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> How is 't, my lord? How look you?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	But are my brother's powers set forth?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Himself in person there?
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Lord Edmund spake not with your lord at home?
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	What might import my sister's letter to him?
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Faith, he is posted hence on serious matter.
	It was great ignorance, Gloucester's eyes being out,
	To let him live; where he arrives he moves
	All hearts against us. Edmund, I think, is gone,
	In pity of his misery, to dispatch
	His nighted life; moreover, to descry
	The strength o' the enemy.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Our troops set forth to-morrow; stay with us,
	The ways are dangerous.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Why should she write to Edmund? Might not you
	Transport her purposes by word? Belike,
	Something—I know not what. I'll love thee much,
	Let me unseal the letter.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	I know your lady does not love her husband;
	I am sure of that: and at her late being here
	She gave strange ceilliades and most speaking looks
	To noble Edmund. I know you are of her bosom.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	I speak in understanding; you are, I know't:
	Therefore I do advise you, take this note:
	My lord is dead; Edmund and I have talk'd,
	And more convenient is he for my hand
	Than for your lady's. You may gather more.
	If you do find him, pray you, give him this,
	And when your mistress hears thus much from you,
	I pray desire her call her wisdom to her:
	So, fare you well.
	If you do chance to hear of that blind traitor,
	Preferment falls on him that cuts him off.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 5><75%>
	Fare thee well.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Our sister's man is certainly miscarried.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Now, sweet lord,
	You know the goodness I intend upon you:
	Tell me, but truly, but then speak the truth,
	Do you not love my sister?
<SPEECH 60><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	But have you never found my brother's way
	To the forefended place?
<SPEECH 61><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	I am doubtful that you have been conjunct
	And bosom'd with her, as far as we call hers.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	I never shall endure her: dear my lord,
	Be not familiar with her.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Why is this reason'd?
<SPEECH 64><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Sister, you'll go with us?
<SPEECH 65><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	'Tis most convenient; pray you, go with us.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	That's as we list to grace him:
	Methinks our pleasure might have been demanded,
	Ere you had spoke so far. He led our powers,
	Bore the commission of my place and person;
	The which immediacy may well stand up,
	And call itself your brother.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	In my rights,
	By me invested, he compeers the best.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	Jesters do oft prove prophets.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	Lady, I am not well; else I should answer
	From a full-flowing stomach. General,
	Take thou my soldiers, prisoners, patrimony;
	Dispose of them, of me; the walls are thine;
	Witness the world, that I create thee here
	My lord and master.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	</STAGE DIR> Let the drum strike, and prove my title thine.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	Sick! O sick!
<SPEECH 72><ACT 5><SCENE 3><93%>
	My sickness grows upon me.
