<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	So is Lysander.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	I would my father look'd but with my eyes.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	I do entreat your Grace to pardon me.
	I know not by what power I am made bold,
	Nor how it may concern my modesty
	In such a presence here to plead my thoughts;
	But I beseech your Grace, that I may know
	The worst that may befall me in this case,
	If I refuse to wed Demetrius.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	So will I grow, so live, so die, my lord,
	Ere I will yield my virgin patent up
	Unto his lordship, whose unwished yoke
	My soul consents not to give sovereignty.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Belike for want of rain, which I could well
	Beteem them from the tempest of mine eyes.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	O cross! too high to be enthrall'd to low.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	O spite! too old to be engag'd to young.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	O hell! to choose love by another's eye.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	If then true lovers have been ever cross'd,
	It stands as an edict in destiny:
	Then let us teach our trial patience,
	Because it is a customary cross,
	As due to love as thoughts and dreams and sighs,
	Wishes and tears, poor fancy's followers.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	My good Lysander!
	I swear to thee by Cupid's strongest bow,
	By his best arrow with the golden head,
	By the simplicity of Venus' doves,
	By that which knitteth souls and prospers loves,
	And by that fire which burn'd the Carthage queen,
	When the false Troyan under sail was seen,
	By all the vows that ever men have broke,—
	In number more than ever women spoke,—
	In that same place thou hast appointed me,
	To-morrow truly will I meet with thee.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	God speed fair Helena! Whither away?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	I frown upon him, yet he loves me still.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	I give him curses, yet he gives me love.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	The more I hate, the more he follows me.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 1><10%>
	His folly, Helena, is no fault of mine.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 1><10%>
	Take comfort: he no more shall see my face;
	Lysander and myself will fly this place.
	Before the time I did Lysander see,
	Seem'd Athens as a paradise to me:
	O! then, what graces in my love do dwell,
	That he hath turn'd a heaven unto a hell.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 1><10%>
	And in the wood, where often you and I
	Upon faint primrose-beds were wont to lie,
	Emptying our bosoms of their counsel sweet,
	There my Lysander and myself shall meet;
	And thence from Athens turn away our eyes,
	To seek new friends and stranger companies.
	Farewell, sweet playfellow: pray thou for us;
	And good luck grant thee thy Demetrius!
	Keep word, Lysander: we must starve our sight
	From lovers' food till morrow deep midnight.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Be it so, Lysander: find you out a bed,
	For I upon this bank will rest my head.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Nay, good Lysander; for my sake, my dear,
	Lie further off yet, do not lie so near.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Lysander riddles very prettily:
	Now much beshrew my manners and my pride,
	If Hermia meant to say Lysander lied.
	But, gentle friend, for love and courtesy
	Lie further off; in human modesty,
	Such separation as may well be said
	Becomes a virtuous bachelor and a maid,
	So far be distant; and, good night, sweet friend.
	Thy love ne'er alter till thy sweet life end!
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	With half that wish the wisher's eyes be press'd!
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	</STAGE DIR> Help me, Lysander, help me! do thy best
	To pluck this crawling serpent from my breast.
	Ay me, for pity! what a dream was here!
	Lysander, look how I do quake with fear:
	Methought a serpent eat my heart away,
	And you sat smiling at his cruel prey.
	Lysander! what! remov'd?—Lysander! lord!
	What! out of hearing? gone? no sound, no word?
	Alack! where are you? speak, an if you hear;
	Speak, of all loves! I swound almost with fear.
	No! then I well perceive you are not nigh:
	Either death or you I'll find immediately.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	Now I but chide; but I should use thee worse,
	For thou, I fear, hast given me cause to curse.
	If thou hast slain Lysander in his sleep,
	Being o'er shoes in blood, plunge in knee deep,
	And kill me too.
	The sun was not so true unto the day
	As he to me. Would he have stol'n away
	From sleeping Hermia? I'll believe as soon
	This whole earth may be bor'd, and that the moon
	May through the centre creep, and so displease
	Her brother's noontide with the Antipodes.
	It cannot be but thou hast murder'd him;
	So should a murderer look, so dead, so grim.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	What's this to my Lysander? where is he?
	Ah! good Demetrius, wilt thou give him me?
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	Out, dog! out, cur! thou driv'st me past the bounds
	Of maiden's patience. Hast thou slain him then?
	Henceforth be never number'd among men!
	O! once tell true, tell true, e'en for my sake;
	Durst thou have look'd upon him being awake,
	And hast thou kill'd him sleeping? O brave touch!
	Could not a worm, an adder, do so much?
	An adder did it; for with doubler tongue
	Than thine, thou serpent, never adder stung.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	I pray thee, tell me then that he is well.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	A privilege never to see me more.
	And from thy hated presence part I so;
	See me no more, whe'r he be dead or no.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	Dark night, that from the eye his function takes,
	The ear more quick of apprehension makes;
	Wherein it doth impair the seeing sense,
	It pays the hearing double recompense.
	Thou art not by mine eye, Lysander, found;
	Mine ear, I thank it, brought me to thy sound.
	But why unkindly didst thou leave me so?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	What love could press Lysander from my side?
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	You speak not as you think: it cannot be.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 2><56%>
	I am amazed at your passionate words.
	I scorn you not: it seems that you scorn me.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	I understand not what you mean by this.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	Sweet, do not scorn her so.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Lysander, whereto tends all this?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Why are you grown so rude? what change is this,
	Sweet love,—
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Do you not jest?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	What! can you do me greater harm than hate?
	Hate me! wherefore? O me! what news, my love?
	Am not I Hermia? Are not you Lysander?
	I am as fair now as I was erewhile.
	Since night you lov'd me; yet, since night you left me:
	Why, then you left me,—O, the gods forbid!—
	In earnest, shall I say?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 2><59%>
	O me! you juggler! you canker-blossom!
	You thief of love! what! have you come by night
	And stol'n my love's heart from him?
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 2><59%>
	Puppet! why, so: ay, that way goes the game.
	Now I perceive that she hath made compare
	Between our statures: she hath urg'd her height;
	And with her personage, her tall personage,
	Her height, forsooth, she hath prevail'd with him.
	And are you grown so high in his esteem,
	Because I am so dwarfish and so low?
	How low am I, thou painted maypole? speak;
	How low am I? I am not yet so low
	But that my nails can reach unto thine eyes.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 2><60%>
	Lower! hark, again.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 2><61%>
	Why, get you gone. Who is't that hinders you?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 2><61%>
	What! with Lysander?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 2><61%>
	'Little' again! nothing but 'low' and 'little!'
	Why will you suffer her to flout me thus?
	Let me come to her.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 2><62%>
	You, mistress, all this coil is 'long of you:
	Nay, go not back.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 2><62%>
	I am amaz'd, and know not what to say.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 2><67%>
	Never so weary, never so in woe,
	Bedabbled with the dew and torn with briers,
	I can no further crawl, no further go;
	My legs can keep no pace with my desires.
	Here will I rest me till the break of day.
	Heavens shield Lysander, if they mean a fray!
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 1><77%>
	Methinks I see these things with parted eye,
	When everything seems double.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 1><77%>
	Yea; and my father.
