<SPEECH 1><ACT 5><SCENE 1><91%>
	You, ladies, you, whose gentle hearts do fear
	The smallest monstrous mouse that creeps on floor,
	May now perchance both quake and tremble here,
	When lion rough in wildest rage doth roar.
	Then know that I, one Snug the joiner, am
	A lion-fell, nor else no lion's dam:
	For, if I should as lion come in strife
	Into this place, 'twere pity on my life.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	</STAGE DIR> Oh—.
