<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	Give the word, ho! and stand.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	He is at hand; and Pindarus is come
	To do you salutation from his master.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	With courtesy and with respect enough;
	But not with such familiar instances,
	Nor with such free and friendly conference,
	As he hath us'd of old.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 2><71%>
	They mean this night in Sardis to be quarter'd;
	The greater part, the horse in general,
	Are come with Cassius.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	</STAGE DIR> You shall not come to them.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	My lord?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 5><SCENE 4><95%>
	O young and noble Cato, art thou down?
	Why, now thou diest as bravely as Titinius,
	And mayst be honour'd being Cato's son.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 5><SCENE 4><96%>
	Only I yield to die:
	There is so much that thou wilt kill me straight.
	Kill Brutus, and be honour'd in his death.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 5><SCENE 4><96%>
	Safe, Antony; Brutus is safe enough:
	I dare assure thee that no enemy
	Shall ever take alive the noble Brutus:
	The gods defend him from so great a shame!
	When you do find him, or alive or dead,
	He will be found like Brutus, like himself.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	So Brutus should be found. I thank thee, Brutus,
	That thou hast prov'd Lucilius' saying true.
