<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	My lord!
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	I will, my lord.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 2><37%>
	They would not have you to stir forth to-day.
	Plucking the entrails of an offering forth,
	They could not find a heart within the beast.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Thus, Brutus, did my master bid me kneel;
	Thus did Mark Antony bid me fall down;
	And, being prostrate, thus he bade me say:
	Brutus is noble, wise, valiant, and honest;
	Cæsar was mighty, bold, royal, and loving:
	Say I love Brutus, and I honour him;
	Say I fear'd Cæsar, honour'd him, and lov'd him.
	If Brutus will vouchsafe that Antony
	May safely come to him, and be resolv'd
	How Cæsar hath deserv'd to lie in death,
	Mark Antony shall not love Cæsar dead
	So well as Brutus living; but will follow
	The fortunes and affairs of noble Brutus
	Thorough the hazards of this untrod state
	With all true faith. So says my master Antony.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	I'll fetch him presently.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE 1><54%>
	I do, Mark Antony.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE 1><54%>
	He did receive his letters, and is coming;
	And bid me say to you by word of mouth—
	O Cæsar!—
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 1><55%>
	He lies to-night within seven leagues of Rome.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 2><66%>
	Sir, Octavius is already come to Rome.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 2><66%>
	He and Lepidus are at Cæsar's house.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 2><66%>
	I heard him say Brutus and Cassius
	Are rid like madmen through the gates of Rome.
