<SPEECH 1><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	Give me your hand first: fare you well, my lord.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	Free from the bondage you are in, Messala;
	The conquerors can but make a fire of him;
	For Brutus only overcame himself,
	And no man else hath honour by his death.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	Ay, if Messala will prefer me to you.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	I held the sword, and he did run on it.
