<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><3%>
	I had thought, sir, to have held my peace until
	You had drawn oaths from him not to stay.
	You, sir,
	Charge him too coldly: tell him, you are sure
	All in Bohemia's well: this satisfaction
	The by-gone day proclaim'd: say this to him,
	He's beat from his best ward.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><3%>
	To tell he longs to see his son were strong:
	But let him say so then, and let him go;
	But let him swear so, and he shall not stay,
	We'll thwack him hence with distaffs.
	</STAGE DIR> Yet of your royal presence I'll adventure
	The borrow of a week. When at Bohemia
	You take my lord, I'll give him my commission
	To let him there a month behind the gest
	Prefix'd for's parting: yet, good deed, Leontes,
	I love thee not a jar o' the clock behind
	What lady she her lord. You'll stay?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><3%>
	Nay, but you will?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><3%>
	Verily!
	You put me off with limber vows; but I,
	Though you would seek to unsphere the stars with oaths,
	Should yet say, 'Sir, no going.' Verily,
	You shall not go: a lady's 'verily' 's
	As potent as a lord's. Will you go yet?
	Force me to keep you as a prisoner,
	Not like a guest; so you shall pay your fees
	When you depart, and save your thanks. How say you?
	My prisoner, or my guest? by your dread 'verily,'
	One of them you shall be.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Not your gaoler then,
	But your kind hostess. Come, I'll question you
	Of my lord's tricks and yours when you were boys:
	You were pretty lordings then.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	Was not my lord the verier wag o' the two?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><4%>
	By this we gather
	You have tripp'd since.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	Grace to boot!
	Of this make no conclusion, lest you say
	Your queen and I are devils; yet, go on:
	The offences we have made you do we'll answer;
	If you first sinn'd with us, and that with us
	You did continue fault, and that you slipp'd not
	With any but with us.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	He'll stay, my lord.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	Never?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	What! have I twice said well? when was't before?
	I prithee tell me; cram's with praise, and make's
	As fat as tame things: one good deed, dying tongueless,
	Slaughters a thousand waiting upon that.
	Our praises are our wages: you may ride's
	With one soft kiss a thousand furlongs ere
	With spur we heat an acre. But to the goal:
	My last good deed was to entreat his stay:
	What was my first? it has an elder sister,
	Or I mistake you: O! would her name were Grace.
	But once before I spoke to the purpose: when?
	Nay, let me have't; I long.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 2><5%>
	'Tis grace indeed.
	Why, lo you now, I have spoke to the purpose twice:
	The one for ever earn'd a royal husband,
	The other for some while a friend.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	He something seems unsettled.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	You look
	As if you held a brow of much distraction:
	Are you mov'd, my lord?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	If you would seek us,
	We are yours i' the garden: shall's attend you there?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Take the boy to you: he so troubles me, 'Tis past enduring.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	What wisdom stirs amongst you? Come sir, now
	I am for you again: pray you, sit by us,
	And tell's a tale.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	As merry as you will.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	Let's have that, good sir.
	Come on, sit down: come on, and do your best
	To fright me with your sprites; you're powerful at it.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	Nay, come, sit down; then on.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	Come on then,
	And give't me in mine ear.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 1><19%>
	What is this? sport?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 1><19%>
	But I'd say he had not,
	And I'll be sworn you would believe my saying,
	Howe'er you lean to the nayward.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	Should a villain say so,
	The most replenish'd villain in the world,
	He were as much more villain: you, my lord,
	Do but mistake.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	No, by my life,
	Privy to none of this. How will this grieve you
	When you shall come to clearer knowledge that
	You thus have publish'd me! Gentle my lord,
	You scarce can right me throughly then to say
	You did mistake.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 1><21%>
	There's some ill planet reigns:
	I must be patient till the heavens look
	With an aspect more favourable. Good my lords,
	I am not prone to weeping, as our sex
	Commonly are; the want of which vain dew
	Perchance shall dry your pities; but I have
	That honourable grief lodg'd here which burns
	Worse than tears drown. Beseech you all, my lords,
	With thoughts so qualified as your charities
	Shall best instruct you, measure me; and so
	The king's will be perform'd!
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 1><21%>
	Who is't that goes with me? Beseech your highness,
	My women may be with me; for you see
	My plight requires it. Do not weep, good fools;
	There is no cause: when you shall know your mistress
	Has deserv'd prison, then abound in tears
	As I come out: this action I now go on
	Is for my better grace. Adieu, my lord:
	I never wish'd to see you sorry; now
	I trust I shall. My women, come; you have leave.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 2><35%>
	Since what I am to say must be but that
	Which contradicts my accusation, and
	The testimony on my part no other
	But what comes from myself, it shall scarce boot me
	To say 'Not guilty:' mine integrity
	Being counted falsehood, shall, as I express it,
	Be so receiv'd. But thus: if powers divine
	Behold our human actions, as they do,
	I doubt not then but innocence shall make
	False accusation blush, and tyranny
	Tremble at patience. You, my lord, best know,—
	Who least will seem to do so,—my past life
	Hath been as continent, as chaste, as true,
	As I am now unhappy; which is more
	Than history can pattern, though devis'd
	And play'd to take spectators. For behold me,
	A fellow of the royal bed, which owe
	A moiety of the throne, a great king's daughter,
	The mother to a hopeful prince, here standing
	To prate and talk for life and honour 'fore
	Who please to come and hear. For life, I prize it.
	As I weigh grief, which I would spare: for honour,
	'Tis a derivative from me to mine,
	And only that I stand for. I appeal
	To your own conscience, sir, before Polixenes
	Came to your court, how I was in your grace,
	How merited to be so; since he came,
	With what encounter so uncurrent I
	Have strain'd, to appear thus: if one jot beyond
	The bound of honour, or in act or will
	That way inclining, harden'd be the hearts
	Of all that hear me, and my near'st of kin
	Cry fie upon my grave!
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 2><36%>
	That's true enough;
	Though 'tis a saying, sir, not due to me.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 2><36%>
	More than mistress of
	Which comes to me in name of fault, I must not
	At all acknowledge. For Polixenes,—
	With whom I am accus'd,—I do confess
	I lov'd him as in honour he requir'd,
	With such a kind of love as might become
	A lady like me; with a love even such,
	So and no other, as yourself commanded:
	Which not to have done I think had been in me
	Both disobedience and ingratitude
	To you and toward your friend, whose love had spoke,
	Even since it could speak, from an infant, freely
	That it was yours. Now, for conspiracy,
	I know not how it tastes, though it be dish'd
	For me to try how: all I know of it
	Is that Camillo was an honest man;
	And why he left your court, the gods themselves,
	Wotting no more than I, are ignorant.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 2><36%>
	Sir,
	You speak a language that I understand not:
	My life stands in the level of your dreams,
	Which I'll lay down.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 2><37%>
	Sir, spare your threats:
	The bug which you would fright me with I seek.
	To me can life be no commodity:
	The crown and comfort of my life, your favour,
	I do give lost; for I do feel it gone,
	But know not how it went. My second joy,
	And first-fruits of my body, from his presence
	I am barr'd, like one infectious. My third comfort,
	Starr'd most unluckily, is from my breast,
	The innocent milk in its most innocent mouth,
	Hal'd out to murder: myself on every post
	Proclaim'd a strumpet: with immodest hatred
	The child-bed privilege denied, which 'longs
	To women of all fashion: lastly, hurried
	Here to this place, i'the open air, before
	I have got strength of limit. Now, my liege,
	Tell me what blessings I have here alive,
	That I should fear to die? Therefore proceed.
	But yet hear this; mistake me not; no life,
	I prize it not a straw:—but for mine honour,
	Which I would free, if I shall be condemn'd
	Upon surmises, all proofs sleeping else
	But what your jealousies awake, I tell you
	'Tis rigour and not law. Your honours all,
	I do refer me to the oracle:
	Apollo be my judge!
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 2><38%>
	The Emperor of Russia was my father:
	O! that he were alive, and here beholding
	His daughter's trial; that he did but see
	The flatness of my misery; yet with eyes
	Of pity, not revenge!
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 2><38%>
	Praised!
<SPEECH 35><ACT 5><SCENE 3><99%>
	You gods, look down,
	And from your sacred vials pour your graces
	Upon my daughter's head! Tell me, mine own,
	Where hast thou been preserv'd? where liv'd? how found
	Thy father's court? for thou shalt hear that I,
	Knowing by Paulina that the oracle
	Gave hope thou wast in being, have preserv'd
	Myself to see the issue.
