<SPEECH 1><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Most noble sir,
	That which I shall report will bear no credit,
	Were not the proof so nigh. Please you, great sir,
	Bohemia greets you from himself by me;
	Desires you to attach his son, who has—
	His dignity and duty both cast off—
	Fled from his father, from his hopes, and with
	A shepherd's daughter.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Here in your city; I now came from him:
	I speak amazedly, and it becomes
	My marvel and my message. To your court
	Whiles he was hastening,—in the chase it seems
	Of this fair couple,—meets he on the way
	The father of this seeming lady and
	Her brother, having both their country quitted
	With this young prince.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Lay't so to his charge:
	He's with the king your father.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Camillo, sir: I spake with him, who now
	Has these poor men in question. Never saw I
	Wretches so quake: they kneel, they kiss the earth,
	Forswear themselves as often as they speak:
	Bohemia stops his ears, and threatens them
	With divers deaths in death.
