<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	The dinner is on the table; my father desires your worships' company.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	Will't please your worship to come in, sir?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	The dinner attends you, sir.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	I may not go in without your worship: they will not sit till you come.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	I pray you, sir, walk in.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><10%>
	I think there are, sir; I heard them talked of.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><10%>
	Ay, indeed, sir.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 1><10%>
	Not I, sir; pray you, keep on.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 1><10%>
	I pray you, sir.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 4><58%>
	Alas! how then?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 4><58%>
	May be he tells you true.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	Gentle Master Fenton,
	Yet seek my father's love; still seek it, sir:
	If opportunity and humblest suit
	Cannot attain it, why, then,—hark you hither.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 4><59%>
	I come to him. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> This is my father's choice.
	O, what a world of vile ill-favour'd faults
	Looks handsome in three hundred pounds a year!
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 4><60%>
	Good Master Shallow, let him woo for himself.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 4><60%>
	Now, Master Slender.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 4><60%>
	What is your will?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 4><60%>
	I mean, Master Slender, what would you with me?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 4><61%>
	Good mother, do not marry me to yond fool.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 4><61%>
	Alas! I had rather be set quick i' the earth,
	And bowl'd to death with turnips.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 5><SCENE 5><92%>
	Fairies, black, grey, green, and white,
	You moonshine revellers, and shades of night,
	You orphan heirs of fixed destiny,
	Attend your office and your quality.
	Crier Hobgoblin, make the fairy oyes.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 5><SCENE 5><93%>
	About, about!
	Search Windsor castle, elves, within and out:
	Strew good luck, ouphs, on every sacred room,
	That it may stand till the perpetual doom,
	In state as wholesome as in state 'tis fit,
	Worthy the owner, and the owner it.
	The several chairs of order look you scour
	With juice of balm and every precious flower:
	Each fair instalment, coat, and several crest,
	With loyal blazon, ever more be blest!
	And nightly, meadow-fairies, look you sing,
	Like to the Garter's compass, in a ring:
	The expressure that it bears, green let it be,
	More fertile-fresh than all the field to see;
	And, Honi soit qui mal y pense write
	In emerald tufts, flowers purple, blue, and white;
	Like sapphire, pearl, and rich embroidery,
	Buckled below fair knighthood's bending knee:
	Fairies use flowers for their charactery.
	Away! disperse! But, till 'tis one o'clock,
	Our dance of custom round about the oak
	Of Herne the hunter, let us not forget.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 5><SCENE 5><94%>
	With trial-fire touch me his finger-end:
	If he be chaste, the flame will back descend
	And turn him to no pain; but if he start,
	It is the flesh of a corrupted heart.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 5><SCENE 5><94%>
	Corrupt, corrupt, and tainted in desire!
	About him, fairies, sing a scornful rime;
	And, as you trip, still pinch him to your time.
	Fie on sinful fantasy!
	Fie on lust and luxury!
	Lust is but a bloody fire,
	Kindled with unchaste desire,
	Fed in heart, whose flames aspire,
	As thoughts do blow them higher and higher.
	Pinch him, fairies, mutually;
	Pinch him for his villany;
	Pinch him, and burn him, and turn him about,
	Till candles and star-light and moonshine be out.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	Pardon, good father! good my mother, pardon!
