<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 4><19%>
	</STAGE DIR> Who's within there? ho!
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 4><19%>
	How now, good woman! how dost thou?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 4><19%>
	What news? how does pretty Mistress Anne?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 4><19%>
	Shall I do any good, thinkest thou? Shall I not lose my suit?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 4><20%>
	Yes, marry have I; what of that?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 4><20%>
	Well, I shall see her to-day. Hold, there's money for thee; let me have thy voice in my behalf: if thou seest her before me, commend me.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 4><20%>
	Well, farewell; I am in great haste now.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 4><58%>
	I see I cannot get thy father's love;
	Therefore no more turn me to him, sweet Nan.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 4><58%>
	Why, thou must be thyself.
	He doth object, I am too great of birth,
	And that my state being gall'd with my expense,
	I seek to heal it only by his wealth.
	Besides these, other bars he lays before me,
	My riots past, my wild societies;
	And tells me 'tis a thing impossible
	I should love thee but as a property.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 4><58%>
	No, heaven so speed me in my time to come!
	Albeit I will confess thy father's wealth
	Was the first motive that I woo'd thee, Anne:
	Yet, wooing thee, I found thee of more value
	Than stamps in gold or sums in sealed bags;
	And 'tis the very riches of thyself
	That now I aim at.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 4><60%>
	Nay, Master Page, be not impatient.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 4><61%>
	Sir, will you hear me?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 4><61%>
	Good Mistress Page, for that I love your daughter
	In such a righteous fashion as I do,
	Perforce, against all checks, rebukes and manners,
	I must advance the colours of my love
	And not retire: let me have your good will.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 4><61%>
	Farewell, gentle mistress. Farewell, Nan.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 4><62%>
	I thank thee: and I pray thee, once to-night
	Give my sweet Nan this ring. There's for thy pains.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 6><86%>
	Yet hear me speak. Assist me in my purpose,
	And, as I am a gentleman, I'll give thee
	A hundred pound in gold more than your loss.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 6><86%>
	From time to time I have acquainted you
	With the dear love I bear to fair Anne Page;
	Who, mutually hath answer'd my affection,
	So far forth as herself might be her chooser,
	Even to my wish. I have a letter from her
	Of such contents as you will wonder at;
	The mirth whereof so larded with my matter,
	That neither singly can be manifested,
	Without the show of both; wherein fat Falstaff
	Hath a great scare: the image of the jest
	I'll show you here at large <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Hark, good mine host:
	To-night at Herne's oak, just 'twixt twelve and one,
	Must my sweet Nan present the Fairy Queen;
	The purpose why, is here: in which disguise,
	While other jests are something rank on foot,
	Her father hath commanded her to slip
	Away with Slender, and with him at Eton
	Immediately to marry: she hath consented:
	Now, sir,
	Her mother, even strong against that match
	And firm for Doctor Caius, hath appointed
	That he shall likewise shuffle her away,
	While other sports are tasking of their minds;
	And at the deanery, where a priest attends,
	Straight marry her: to this her mother's plot
	She, seemingly obedient, likewise hath
	Made promise to the doctor. Now, thus it rests:
	Her father means she shall be all in white,
	And in that habit, when Slender sees his time
	To take her by the hand and bid her go,
	She shall go with him: her mother hath intended,
	The better to denote her to the doctor,—
	For they must all be mask'd and vizarded—
	That quaint in green she shall be loose enrob'd,
	With ribands pendent, flaring 'bout her head;
	And when the doctor spies his vantage ripe,
	To pinch her by the hand; and on that token
	The maid hath given consent to go with him.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 6><87%>
	Both, my good host, to go along with me:
	And here it rests, that you'll procure the vicar
	To stay for me at church 'twixt twelve and one,
	And, in the lawful name of marrying,
	To give our hearts united ceremony.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 6><87%>
	So shall I evermore be bound to thee;
	Besides, I'll make a present recompense.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	You do amaze her: hear the truth of it.
	You would have married her most shamefully,
	Where there was no proportion held in love.
	The truth is, she and I, long since contracted,
	Are now so sure that nothing can dissolve us.
	The offence is holy that she hath committed,
	And this deceit loses the name of craft,
	Of disobedience, or unduteous title,
	Since therein she doth evitate and shun
	A thousand irreligious cursed hours,
	Which forced marriage would have brought upon her.
