<SPEECH 1><ACT 3><SCENE 7><48%>
	You have an excellent armour; but let my horse have his due.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 3><SCENE 7><48%>
	Will it never be morning?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 3><SCENE 7><48%>
	You are as well provided of both as any prince in the world.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 3><SCENE 7><49%>
	He's of the colour of the nutmeg.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE 7><49%>
	No more, cousin.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE 7><49%>
	I have heard a sonnet begin so to one's mistress.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE 7><50%>
	Your mistress bears well.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 7><51%>
	The Dauphin longs for morning.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 7><51%>
	By the white hand of my lady, he's a gallant prince.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 7><51%>
	He is simply the most active gentleman of France.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 7><51%>
	He never did harm, that I heard of.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 7><51%>
	I know him to be valiant.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 7><51%>
	What's he?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 7><51%>
	He needs not; it is no hidden virtue in him.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 7><51%>
	'Ill will never said well.'
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 7><51%>
	And I will take up that with 'Give the devil his due.'
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 7><52%>
	You are the better at proverbs, by how much 'A fool's bolt is soon shot.'
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 7><52%>
	'Tis not the first time you were overshot.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 7><52%>
	What a wretched and peevish fellow is this King of England, to mope with his fatbrained followers so far out of his knowledge!
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 7><52%>
	That they lack; for if their heads had any intellectual armour they could never wear such heavy head-pieces.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 7><52%>
	Foolish curs! that run winking into the mouth of a Russian bear and have their heads crushed like rotten apples. You may as well say that's a valiant flea that dare eat his breakfast on the lip of a lion.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 7><52%>
	Ay, but these English are shrewdly out of beef.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 7><53%>
	It is now two o'clock: but, let me see, by ten
	We shall have each a hundred Englishmen.
	Now entertain conjecture of a time
	When creeping murmur and the poring dark
	Fills the wide vessel of the universe.
	From camp to camp, through the foul womb of night,
	The hum of either army stilly sounds,
	That the fix'd sentinels almost receive
	The secret whispers of each other's watch:
	Fire answers fire, and through their paly flames
	Each battle sees the other's umber'd face:
	Steed threatens steed, in high and boastful neighs
	Piercing the night's dull ear; and from the tents
	The armourers, accomplishing the knights,
	With busy hammers closing rivets up,
	Give dreadful note of preparation.
	The country cocks do crow, the clocks do toll,
	And the third hour of drowsy morning name.
	Proud of their numbers, and secure in soul,
	The confident and over-lusty French
	Do the low-rated English play at dice;
	And chide the cripple tardy-gaited night
	Who, like a foul and ugly witch, doth limp
	So tediously away. The poor condemned English,
	Like sacrifices, by their watchful fires
	Sit patiently, and inly ruminate
	The morning's danger, and their gesture sad
	Investing lank-lean cheeks and war-worn coats
	Presenteth them unto the gazing moon
	So many horrid ghosts. O! now, who will behold
	The royal captain of this ruin'd band
	Walking from watch to watch, from tent to tent,
	Let him cry 'Praise and glory on his head!'
	For forth he goes and visits all his host,—
	Bids them good morrow with a modest smile,
	And calls them brothers, friends, and countrymen.
	Upon his royal face there is no note
	How dread an army hath enrounded him;
	Nor doth he dedicate one jot of colour
	Unto the weary and all-watched night:
	But freshly looks and overbears attaint
	With cheerful semblance and sweet majesty;
	That every wretch, pining and pale before,
	Beholding him, plucks comfort from his looks,
	A largess universal, like the sun
	His liberal eye doth give to every one,
	Thawing cold fear. Then mean and gentle all,
	Behold, as may unworthiness define,
	A little touch of Harry in the night.
	And so our scene must to the battle fly;
	Where,—O for pity,—we shall much disgrace,
	With four or five most vile and ragged foils,
	Right ill dispos'd in brawl ridiculous,
	The name of Agincourt. Yet sit and see;
	Minding true things by what their mockeries be.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	The sun doth gild our armour: up, my lords!
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	O brave spirit!
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	Rien puis? l'air et le feu.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	O seigneur! le jour est perdu! tout est perdu!
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	Is this the king we sent to for his ransom?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	We are enough yet living in the field
	To smother up the English in our throngs,
	If any order might be thought upon.
