<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 1><15%>
	Base tike, call'st thou me host?
	Now, by this hand, I swear, I scorn the term;
	Nor shall my Nell keep lodgers.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	Pish for thee, Iceland dog! thou prickeared cur of Iceland!
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	Solus, egregious dog? O viper vile!
	The solus in thy most mervailous face;
	The solus in thy teeth, and in thy throat,
	And in thy hateful lungs, yea, in thy maw, perdy;
	And, which is worse, within thy nasty mouth!
	I do retort the solus in thy bowels;
	For I can take, and Pistol's cock is up,
	And flashing fire will follow.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	O braggart vile and damned furious wight!
	The grave doth gape, and doting death is near;
	Therefore exhale.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	An oath of mickle might, and fury shall abate.
	Give me thy fist, thy fore-foot to me give;
	Thy spirits are most tall.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Coupe le gorge!
	That is the word. I thee defy again.
	O hound of Crete, think'st thou my spouse to get?
	No; to the spital go,
	And from the powdering-tub of infamy
	Fetch forth the lazar kite of Cressid's kind,
	Doll Tearsheet she by name, and her espouse:
	I have, and I will hold, the quondam Quickly
	For the only she; and—pauca, there's enough.
	Go to
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Let floods o'erswell, and fiends for food howl on!
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Base is the slave that pays.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	As manhood shall compound: push home.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	Sword is an oath, and oaths must have their course.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	A noble shalt thou have, and present pay;
	And liquor likewise will I give to thee,
	And friendship shall combine, and brotherhood:
	I'll live by Nym, and Nym shall live by me.
	Is not this just? for I shall sutler be
	Unto the camp, and profits will accrue.
	Give me thy hand.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	In cash most justly paid.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	Nym, thou hast spoke the right;
	His heart is fracted and corroborate.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	Let us condole the knight; for, lambkins, we will live.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 3><24%>
	No; for my manly heart doth yearn.
	Bardolph, be blithe; Nym, rouse thy vaunting veins;
	Boy, bristle thy courage up; for Falstaff he is dead,
	And we must yearn therefore.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 3><25%>
	Come, let's away. My love, give me thy lips.
	Look to my chattels and my moveables:
	Let senses rule, the word is, 'Pitch and pay;'
	Trust none;
	For oaths are straws, men's faiths are wafercakes,
	And hold-fast is the only dog, my duck:
	Therefore, caveto be thy counsellor.
	Go, clear thy crystals. Yoke-fellows in arms,
	Let us to France; like horse-leeches, my boys,
	To suck, to suck, the very blood to suck!
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 3><26%>
	Touch her soft mouth, and march.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 3><26%>
	Let housewifery appear: keep close, I thee command.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 2><33%>
	The plain-song is most just, for humours do abound:
	Knocks go and come: God's vassals drop and die;
	And sword and shield
	In bloody field
	Doth win immortal fame.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 2><33%>
	And I:
	If wishes would prevail with me,
	My purpose should not fail with me,
	But thither would I hie.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 2><33%>
	Be merciful, great duke, to men of mould!
	Abate thy rage, abate thy manly rage!
	Abate thy rage, great duke!
	Good bawcock, bate thy rage; use lenity, sweet chuck!
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 6><43%>
	Captain, I thee beseech to do me favours:
	The Duke of Exeter doth love thee well.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 6><44%>
	Bardolph, a soldier firm and sound of heart,
	And of buxom valour, hath, by cruel fate
	And giddy Fortune's furious fickle wheel,
	That goddess blind,
	That stands upon the rolling restless stone,—
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 6><44%>
	Fortune is Bardolph's foe, and frowns on him;
	For he hath stol'n a pax, and hanged must a' be,
	A damned death!
	Let gallows gape for dog, let man go free
	And let not hemp his wind-pipe suffocate.
	But Exeter hath given the doom of death
	For pax of little price.
	Therefore, go speak; the duke will hear thy voice;
	And let not Bardolph's vital thread be cut
	With edge of penny cord and vile reproach:
	Speak, captain, for his life, and I will thee requite.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 6><44%>
	Why then, rejoice therefore.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 6><45%>
	Die and be damn'd; and figo for thy friendship!
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 6><45%>
	The fig of Spain!
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 1><55%>
	Qui va là?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 1><55%>
	Discuss unto me; art thou officer?
	Or art thou base, common and popular?
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 1><55%>
	Trail'st thou the puissant pike?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	As good a gentleman as the emperor.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	The king's a bawcock, and a heart of gold,
	A lad of life, an imp of fame:
	Of parents good, of fist most valiant:
	I kiss his dirty shoe, and from my heart-string
	I love the lovely bully. What's thy name?
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	Le Roy! a Cornish name: art thou of Cornish crew?
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	Know'st thou Fluellen?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	Tell him, I'll knock his leek about his pate
	Upon Saint Davy's day.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	Art thou his friend?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	The figo for thee then!
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	My name is Pistol called.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	Yield, cur!
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	Quality? Calen O custure me! Art thou a gentleman?
	What is thy name? discuss.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	O Signieur Dew should be a gentleman:—
	Perpend my words, O Signieur Dew, and mark:
	O Signieur Dew, thou diest on point of fox
	Except, O signieur, thou do give to me
	Egregious ransom.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	Moy shall not serve; I will have forty moys;
	Or I will fetch thy rim out at thy throat
	In drops of crimson blood.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	Brass, cur!
	Thou damned and luxurious mountain goat,
	Offer'st me brass?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	Sayst thou me so? is that a ton of moys?
	Come hither, boy: ask me this slave in French
	What is his name.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Master Fer! I'll fer him, and firk him, and ferret him. Discuss the same in French unto him.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Bid him prepare, for I will cut his throat.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Ouy, cuppele gorge, permafoy.
	Peasant, unless thou give me crowns, brave crowns;
	Or mangled shalt thou be by this my sword.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	What are his words?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Tell him, my fury shall abate, and I
	The crowns will take.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Expound unto me, boy.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 4><72%>
	As I suck blood, I will some mercy show.—
	Follow me!
<SPEECH 52><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Ha! art thou bedlam? dost thou thirst, base Troyan,
	To have me fold up Parca's fatal web?
	Hence! I am qualmish at the smell of leek.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Not for Cadwallader and all his goats.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Base Troyan, thou shalt die.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Must I bite?
<SPEECH 56><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	By this leek, I will most horribly revenge. I eat and eat, I swear—
<SPEECH 57><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Quiet thy cudgel: thou dost see I eat.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Good.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Me a groat!
<SPEECH 60><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	I take thy groat in earnest of revenge.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	All hell shall stir for this.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Doth Fortune play the huswife with me now?
	News have I that my Nell is dead i' the spital
	Of malady of France:
	And there my rendezvous is quite cut off.
	Old I do wax, and from my weary limbs
	Honour is cudgelled. Well, bawd I'll turn,
	And something lean to cutpurse of quick hand.
	To England will I steal, and there I'll steal:
	And patches will I get unto these cudgell'd scars,
	And swear I got them in the Gallia wars.
