<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 3><66%>
	God's arm strike with us! 'tis a fearful odds.
	God be wi' you, princes all; I'll to my charge:
	If we no more meet till we meet in heaven,
	Then, joyfully, my noble Lord of Bedford,
	My dear Lord Gloucester, and my good Lord Exeter,
	And my kind kinsman, warriors all, adieu!
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 3><68%>
	My sov'reign lord, bestow yourself with speed:
	The French are bravely in their battles set,
	And will with all expedience charge on us.
