<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	She is importunate, indeed distract:
	Her mood will needs be pitied.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	She speaks much of her father; says she hears
	There's tricks i' the world; and hems, and beats her heart;
	Spurns enviously at straws; speaks things in doubt,
	That carry but half sense: her speech is nothing,
	Yet the unshaped use of it doth move
	The hearers to collection; they aim at it,
	And botch the words up fit to their own thoughts;
	Which, as her winks, and nods, and gestures yield them,
	Indeed would make one think there might be thought,
	Though nothing sure, yet much unhappily.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	Save yourself, my lord;
	The ocean, overpeering of his list,
	Eats not the flats with more impetuous haste
	Than young Laertes, in a riotous head,
	O'erbears your officers. The rabble call him lord;
	And, as the world were now but to begin,
	Antiquity forgot, custom not known,
	The ratifiers and props of every word,
	They cry, 'Choose we; Laertes shall be king!'
	Caps, hands, and tongues, applaud it to the clouds,
	'Laertes shall be king, Laertes king!'
