<SPEECH 1><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Then she is well, and nothing can be ill;
	Her body sleeps in Capel's monument,
	And her immortal part with angels lives.
	I saw her laid low in her kindred's vault,
	And presently took post to tell it you.
	O! pardon me for bringing these ill news,
	Since you did leave it for my office, sir.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	I do beseech you, sir, have patience:
	Your looks are pale and wild, and do import
	Some misadventure.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	No, my good lord.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	I will be gone, sir, and not trouble you.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	</STAGE DIR> For all this same, I'll hide me here about:
	His looks I fear, and his intents I doubt.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	Here's one, a friend, and one that knows you well.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	It doth so, holy sir; and there's my master,
	One that you love.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	Romeo.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	Full half an hour.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	I dare not, sir.
	My master knows not but I am gone hence;
	And fearfully did menace me with death
	If I did stay to look on his intents.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 5><SCENE 3><94%>
	As I did sleep under this yew-tree here,
	I dreamt my master and another fought,
	And that my master slew him.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 5><SCENE 3><99%>
	I brought my master news of Juliet's death;
	And then in post he came from Mantua
	To this same place, to this same monument.
	This letter he early bid me give his father,
	And threaten'd me with death, going in the vault,
	If I departed not and left him there.
