<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 5><19%>
	When good manners shall lie all in one or two men's hands, and they unwashed too, 'tis a foul thing.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	Ay, boy; ready.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 5><20%>
	Cheerly, boys; be brisk awhile, and the longer liver take all.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 2><76%>
	You shall have none ill, sir; for
	I'll try if they can lick their fingers.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 2><76%>
	Marry, sir, 'tis an ill cook that cannot lick his own fingers: therefore he that cannot lick his fingers goes not with me.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 4><SCENE 4><80%>
	I have a head, sir, that will find out logs,
	And never trouble Peter for the matter.
