<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	What! art thou drawn among these heartless hinds?
	Turn-thee, Benvolio, look upon thy death.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	What! drawn, and talk of peace? I hate the word,
	As I hate hell, all Montagues, and thee.
	Have at thee, coward!
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	This, by his voice, should be a Montague.
	Fetch me my rapier, boy. What! dares the slave
	Come hither, cover'd with an antick face,
	To fleer and scorn at our solemnity?
	Now, by the stock and honour of my kin,
	To strike him dead I hold it not a sin.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	Uncle, this is a Montague, our foe;
	A villain that is hither come in spite,
	To scorn at our solemnity this night.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 5><21%>
	'Tis he, that villain Romeo.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 5><22%>
	It fits, when such a villain is a guest:
	I'll not endure him.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 5><22%>
	Why, uncle, 'tis a shame.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 5><22%>
	Patience perforce with wilful choler meeting
	Makes my flesh tremble in their different greeting.
	I will withdraw; but this intrusion shall
	Now seeming sweet convert to bitter gall.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Follow me close, for I will speak to them. Gentlemen, good den! a word with one of you.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	You shall find me apt enough to that, sir, an you will give me occasion.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Mercutio, thou consort'st with Romeo,—
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	Well, peace be with you, sir. Here comes my man.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	Romeo, the hate I bear thee can afford
	No better term than this,—thou art a villain.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	Boy, this shall not excuse the injuries
	That thou hast done me; therefore turn and draw.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	What wouldst thou have with me?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	</STAGE DIR> I am for you.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	Thou wretched boy, that didst consort him here,
	Shalt with him hence.
