<SPEECH 1><ACT 3><SCENE 1><32%>
	Good Signior Angelo, you must excuse us all;
	My wife is shrewish when I keep not hours;
	Say that I linger'd with you at your shop
	To see the making of her carkanet,
	And that to-morrow you will bring it home.
	But here's a villain, that would face me down
	He met me on the mart, and that I beat him,
	And charg'd him with a thousand marks in gold,
	And that I did deny my wife and house.
	Thou drunkard, thou, what didst thou mean by this?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 3><SCENE 1><33%>
	I think thou art an ass.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 3><SCENE 1><33%>
	You are sad, Signior Balthazar: pray God, our cheer
	May answer my good will and your good welcome here.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 3><SCENE 1><33%>
	O, Signior Balthazar, either at flesh or fish,
	A table-full of welcome makes scarce one dainty dish.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE 1><34%>
	And welcome more common, for that's nothing but words.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE 1><34%>
	Ay, to a niggardly host and more sparing guest:
	But though my cates be mean, take them in good part;
	Better cheer may you have, but not with better heart.
	But soft! my door is lock'd. Go bid them let us in.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE 1><35%>
	Who talks within there? ho! open the door.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 1><35%>
	Wherefore? for my dinner: I have not din'd to-day.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 1><35%>
	What art thou that keep'st me out from the house I owe?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 1><36%>
	Do you hear, you minion? you'll let us in, I trow?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 1><36%>
	Thou baggage, let me in.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 1><37%>
	You'll cry for this, minion, if I beat the door down.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 1><37%>
	Are you there, wife? you might have come before.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 1><38%>
	There is something in the wind, that we cannot get in.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 1><38%>
	Go fetch me something: I'll break ope the gate.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 1><39%>
	Well, I'll break in. Go borrow me a crow.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 1><39%>
	Go get thee gone: fetch me an iron crow.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 1><40%>
	You have prevail'd: I will depart in quiet,
	And, in despite of mirth, mean to be merry.
	I know a wench of excellent discourse,
	Pretty and witty, wild and yet, too, gentle:
	There will we dine: this woman that I mean,
	My wife,—but, I protest, without desert,—
	Hath oftentimes upbraided me withal:
	To her will we to dinner. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Get you home,
	And fetch the chain; by this I know 'tis made:
	Bring it, I pray you, to the Porpentine;
	For there's the house: that chain will I bestow,
	Be it for nothing but to spite my wife,
	Upon mine hostess there. Good sir, make haste.
	Since mine own doors refuse to entertain me,
	I'll knock elsewhere, to see if they'll disdain me.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Do so. This jest shall cost me some expense.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 1><52%>
	While I go to the goldsmith's house, go thou
	And buy a rope's end, that I will bestow
	Among my wife and her confederates,
	For locking me out of my doors by day.
	But soft! I see the goldsmith. Get thee gone;
	Buy thou a rope, and bring it home to me.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 4><SCENE 1><52%>
	A man is well holp up that trusts to you:
	I promised your presence and the chain;
	But neither chain nor goldsmith came to me.
	Belike you thought our love would last too long,
	If it were chain'd together, and therefore came not.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 1><53%>
	I am not furnish'd with the present money;
	Besides, I have some business in the town.
	Good signior, take the stranger to my house,
	And with you take the chain, and bid my wife
	Disburse the sum on the receipt thereof:
	Perchance I will be there as soon as you.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 1><53%>
	No; bear it with you, lest I come not time enough.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 1><53%>
	An if I have not, sir, I hope you have,
	Or else you may return without your money.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 1><54%>
	Good Lord! you use this dalliance to excuse
	Your breach of promise to the Porpentine.
	I should have child you for not bringing it,
	But, like a shrew, you first begin to brawl.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 1><54%>
	Why, give it to my wife and fetch your money.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 1><54%>
	Fie! now you run this humour out of breath.
	Come, where's the chain? I pray you, let me see it.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 1><54%>
	I answer you! what should I answer you?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 1><55%>
	I owe you none till I receive the chain.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 1><55%>
	You gave me none: you wrong me much to say so.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 1><55%>
	Consent to pay thee that I never had!
	Arrest me, foolish fellow, if thou dar'st.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 1><55%>
	I do obey thee till I give thee bail.
	But, sirrah, you shall buy this sport as dear
	As all the metal in your shop will answer.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	How now! a madman! Why, thou peevish sheep,
	What ship of Epidamnum stays for me?
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 1><56%>
	Thou drunken slave, I sent thee for a rope;
	And told thee to what purpose, and what end.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 1><57%>
	I will debate this matter at more leisure,
	And teach your ears to list me with more heed.
	To Adriana, villain, hie thee straight;
	Give her this key, and tell her, in the desk
	That's cover'd o'er with Turkish tapestry,
	There is a purse of ducats: let her send it.
	Tell her I am arrested in the street,
	And that shall bail me. Hie thee, slave, be gone!
	On, officer, to prison till it come.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 4><67%>
	Fear me not, man; I will not break away:
	I'll give thee, ere I leave thee, so much money,
	To warrant thee, as I am 'rested for.
	My wife is in a wayward mood to-day,
	And will not lightly trust the messenger.
	That I should be attach'd in Ephesus,
	I tell you, 'twill sound harshly in her ears.
	Here comes my man: I think he brings the money.
	How now, sir! have you that I sent you for?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	But where's the money?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	Five hundred ducats, villain, for a rope?
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	To what end did I bid thee hie thee home?
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	And to that end, sir, I will welcome you.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	Thou whoreson, senseless villain!
<SPEECH 42><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	Thou art sensible in nothing but blows, and so is an ass.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 4><SCENE 4><69%>
	Come, go along; my wife is coming yonder.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 4><SCENE 4><69%>
	Wilt thou still talk?
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	There is my hand, and let it feel your ear.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	Peace, doting wizard, peace! I am not mad.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	You minion, you, are these your customers?
	Did this companion with the saffron face
	Revel and feast it at my house to-day,
	Whilst upon me the guilty doors were shut
	And I denied to enter in my house?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Din'd at home! Thou villain, what say'st thou?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Were not my doors lock'd up and I shut out?
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	And did not she herself revile me there?
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Did not her kitchen-maid rail, taunt, and scorn me?
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	And did not I in rage depart from thence?
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 4><72%>
	Thou hast suborn'd the goldsmith to arrest me.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 4><72%>
	Went'st not thou to her for a purse of ducats?
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 4><72%>
	Say, wherefore didst thou lock me forth to-day?
	And why dost thou deny the bag of gold?
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 4><73%>
	Dissembling harlot! thou art false in all;
	And art confederate with a damned pack
	To make a loathsome abject scorn of me;
	But with these nails I'll pluck out those false eyes
	That would behold in me this shameful sport.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 4><73%>
	What, will you murder me? Thou gaoler, thou,
	I am thy prisoner: wilt thou suffer them
	To make a rescue?
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 4><74%>
	O most unhappy strumpet!
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 4><74%>
	Out on thee, villain! wherefore dost thou mad me?
<SPEECH 60><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Justice, most gracious duke! O! grant me justice,
	Even for the service that long since I did thee,
	When I bestrid thee in the wars and took
	Deep scars to save thy life; even for the blood
	That then I lost for thee, now grant me justice.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	Justice, sweet prince, against that woman there!
	She whom thou gav'st to me to be my wife,
	That hath abused and dishonour'd me,
	Even in the strength and height of injury!
	Beyond imagination is the wrong
	That she this day hath shameless thrown on me.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	This day, great duke, she shut the doors upon me,
	While she with harlots feasted in my house.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	My liege, I am advised what I say:
	Neither disturb'd with the effect of wine,
	Nor heady-rash, provok'd with raging ire,
	Albeit my wrongs might make one wiser mad.
	This woman lock'd me out this day from dinner:
	That goldsmith there, were he not pack'd with her,
	Could witness it, for he was with me then;
	Who parted with me to go fetch a chain,
	Promising to bring it to the Porpentine,
	Where Balthazar and I did dine together.
	Our dinner done, and he not coming thither,
	I went to seek him: in the street I met him,
	And in his company that gentleman.
	There did this perjur'd goldsmith swear me down
	That I this day of him receiv'd the chain,
	Which, God he knows, I saw not; for the which
	He did arrest me with an officer.
	I did obey, and sent my peasant home
	For certain ducats: he with none return'd.
	Then fairly I bespoke the officer
	To go in person with me to my house.
	By the way we met
	My wife, her sister, and a rabble more
	Of vile confederates: along with them
	They brought one Pinch, a hungry lean-fac'd villain,
	A mere anatomy, a mountebank,
	A threadbare juggler, and a fortune-teller,
	A needy, hollow-ey'd, sharp-looking wretch,
	A living-dead man. This pernicious slave,
	Forsooth, took on him as a conjurer,
	And, gazing in mine eyes, feeling my pulse,
	And with no face, as 'twere, out-facing me,
	Cries out, I was possess'd. Then, altogether
	They fell upon me, bound me, bore me thence,
	And in a dark and dankish vault at home
	There left me and my man, both bound together;
	Till, gnawing with my teeth my bonds in sunder,
	I gain'd my freedom, and immediately
	Ran hither to your Grace; whom I beseech
	To give me ample satisfaction
	For these deep shames and great indignities.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 5><SCENE 1><91%>
	I never came within these abbey walls;
	Nor ever didst thou draw thy sword on me;
	I never saw the chain, so help me heaven!
	And this is false you burden me withal.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	'Tis true, my liege; this ring I had of her.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	I never saw you in my life till now.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	Neither.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 5><SCENE 1><94%>
	I never saw my father in my life.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 5><SCENE 1><94%>
	The duke and all that know me in the city
	Can witness with me that it is not so:
	I ne'er saw Syracusa in my life.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 5><SCENE 1><96%>
	I came from Corinth, my most gracious lord,—
<SPEECH 71><ACT 5><SCENE 1><96%>
	Brought to this town by that most famous warrior,
	Duke Menaphon, your most renowned uncle.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 5><SCENE 1><97%>
	No; I say nay to that.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 5><SCENE 1><97%>
	And you, sir, for this chain arrested me.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 5><SCENE 1><98%>
	These ducats pawn I for my father here.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 5><SCENE 1><98%>
	There, take it; and much thanks for my good cheer.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 5><SCENE 1><99%>
	Dromio, what stuff of mine hast thou embark'd?
