<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	Always obedient to your Grace's will,
	I come to know your pleasure.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Now, good my lord,
	Let there be some more test made of my metal,
	Before so noble and so great a figure
	Be stamp'd upon it.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Yet, give leave, my lord,
	That we may bring you something on the way.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	The heavens give safety to your purposes!
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	'Tis so with me. Let us withdraw together,
	And we may soon our satisfaction have
	Touching that point.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 1><15%>
	We must not make a scarecrow of the law,
	Setting it up to fear the birds of prey,
	And let it keep one shape, till custom make it
	Their perch and not their terror.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	'Tis one thing to be tempted, Escalus,
	Another thing to fall. I not deny,
	The jury, passing on the prisoner's life,
	May in the sworn twelve have a thief or two
	Guiltier than him they try; what's open made to justice,
	That justice seizes: what know the laws
	That thieves do pass on thieves? 'Tis very pregnant,
	The jewel that we find, we stoop and take it
	Because we see it; but what we do not see
	We tread upon, and never think of it.
	You may not so extenuate his offence
	For I have had such faults; but rather tell me,
	When I, that censure him, do so offend,
	Let mine own judgment pattern out my death,
	And nothing come in partial. Sir, he must die.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	Where is the provost?
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	See that Claudio
	Be executed by nine to-morrow morning:
	Bring him his confessor, let him be prepar'd;
	For that's the utmost of his pilgrimage.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	How now, sir! What's your name, and what's the matter?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Benefactors! Well; what benefactors are they? are they not malefactors?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Go to: what quality are they of? Elbow is your name? why dost thou not speak, Elbow?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	What are you, sir?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	This will last out a night in Russia,
	When nights are longest there: I'll take my leave,
	And leave you to the hearing of the cause,
	Hoping you'll find good cause to whip them all.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 2><25%>
	Now, what's the matter, provost?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 2><25%>
	Did I not tell thee, yea? hadst thou not order?
	Why dost thou ask again?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Go to; let that be mine:
	Do you your office, or give up your place,
	And you shall well be spar'd.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Dispose of her
	To some more fitter place; and that with speed.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Hath he a sister?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Well, let her be admitted.
	See you the fornicatress be remov'd:
	Let her have needful, but not lavish, means;
	There shall be order for't.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Stay a little while.—<STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> You're welcome: what's your will?
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Well; what's your suit?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Well; the matter?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Condemn the fault, and not the actor of it?
	Why, every fault's condemn'd ere it be done.
	Mine were the very cipher of a function,
	To fine the faults whose fine stands in record,
	And let go by the actor.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Maiden, no remedy.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	I will not do't.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	Look, what I will not, that I cannot do.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	He's sentenc'd: 'tis too late.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Pray you, be gone.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Your brother is a forfeit of the law,
	And you but waste your words.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Be you content, fair maid;
	It is the law, not I, condemn your brother:
	Were he my kinsman, brother, or my son,
	It should be thus with him: he must die to-morrow.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	The law hath not been dead, though it hath slept:
	Those many had not dar'd to do that evil,
	If that the first that did th' edict infringe
	Had answer'd for his deed: now 'tis awake,
	Takes note of what is done, and, like a prophet,
	Looks in a glass, that shows what future evils,
	Either new, or by remissness new-conceiv'd,
	And so in progress to be hatch'd and born,
	Are now to have no successive degrees,
	But, ere they live, to end.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	I show it most of all when I show justice;
	For then I pity those I do not know,
	Which a dismiss'd offence would after gall,
	And do him right, that, answering one foul wrong,
	Lives not to act another. Be satisfied:
	Your brother dies to-morrow: be content.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	Why do you put these sayings upon me?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	She speaks, and 'tis
	Such sense that my sense breeds with it. Fare you well.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	I will bethink me. Come again to-morrow.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	How! bribe me?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Well; come to me to-morrow.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	</STAGE DIR> Amen:
	For I am that way going to temptation,
	Where prayers cross.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	At any time 'fore noon.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	From thee; even from thy virtue!
	What's this? what's this? Is this her fault or mine?
	The tempter or the tempted, who sins most?
	Ha!
	Not she; nor doth she tempt: but it is I,
	That, lying by the violet in the sun,
	Do as the carrion does, not as the flower,
	Corrupt with virtuous season. Can it be
	That modesty may more betray our sense
	Than woman's lightness? Having waste ground enough,
	Shall we desire to raze the sanctuary,
	And pitch our evils there? O, fie, fie, fie!
	What dost thou, or what art thou, Angelo?
	Dost thou desire her foully for those things
	That make her good? O, let her brother live!
	Thieves for their robbery have authority
	When judges steal themselves. What! do I love her,
	That I desire to hear her speak again,
	And feast upon her eyes? What is't I dream on?
	O cunning enemy, that, to catch a saint,
	With saints dost bait thy hook! Most dangerous
	Is that temptation that doth goad us on
	To sin in loving virtue: never could the strumpet,
	With all her double vigour, art and nature,
	Once stir my temper; but this virtuous maid
	Subdues me quite. Ever till now,
	When men were fond, I smil'd and wonder'd how.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 2><SCENE 4><34%>
	When I would pray and think, I think and pray
	To several subjects: heaven hath my empty words,
	Whilst my invention, hearing not my tongue,
	Anchors on Isabel: heaven in my mouth,
	As if I did but only chew his name,
	And in my heart the strong and swelling evil
	Of my conception. The state, whereon I studied,
	Is like a good thing, being often read,
	Grown fear'd and tedious; yea, my gravity,
	Wherein, let no man hear me, I take pride,
	Could I with boot change for an idle plume,
	Which the air beats for vain. O place! O form!
	How often dost thou with thy case, thy habit,
	Wrench awe from fools, and tie the wiser souls
	To thy false seeming! Blood, thou art blood:
	Let's write good angel on the devil's horn,
	'Tis not the devil's crest.
	How now! who's there?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 2><SCENE 4><35%>
	Teach her the way.
	O heavens!
	Why does my blood thus muster to my heart,
	Making both it unable for itself,
	And dispossessing all my other parts
	Of necessary fitness?
	So play the foolish throngs with one that swounds;
	Come all to help him, and so stop the air
	By which he should revive: and even so
	The general, subject to a well-wish'd king,
	Quit their own part, and in obsequious fondness
	Crowd to his presence, where their untaught love
	Must needs appear offence.
	How now, fair maid!
<SPEECH 44><ACT 2><SCENE 4><35%>
	That you might know it, would much better please me,
	Than to demand what 'tis. Your brother cannot live.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	Yet may he live awhile; and, it may be,
	As long as you or I: yet he must die.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	Yea.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	Ha! fie, these filthy vices! It were as good
	To pardon him that hath from nature stolen
	A man already made, as to remit
	Their saucy sweetness that do coin heaven's image
	In stamps that are forbid: 'tis all as easy
	Falsely to take away a life true made,
	As to put metal in restrained means
	To make a false one.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	Say you so? then I shall pose you quickly.
	Which had you rather, that the most just law
	Now took your brother's life; or, to redeem him,
	Give up your body to such sweet uncleanness
	As she that he hath stain'd?
<SPEECH 49><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	I talk not of your soul. Our compell'd sins
	Stand more for number than for accompt.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 2><SCENE 4><36%>
	Nay, I'll not warrant that; for I can speak
	Against the thing I say. Answer to this:
	I, now the voice of the recorded law,
	Pronounce a sentence on your brother's life:
	Might there not be a charity in sin
	To save this brother's life?
<SPEECH 51><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Pleas'd you to do't, at peril of your soul,
	Were equal poise of sin and charity.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Nay, but hear me.
	Your sense pursues not mine: either you are ignorant,
	Or seem so craftily; and that's not good.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Thus wisdom wishes to appear most bright
	When it doth tax itself; as these black masks
	Proclaim an enshield beauty ten times louder
	Than beauty could, display'd. But mark me;
	To be received plain, I'll speak more gross:
	Your brother is to die.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	And his offence is so, as it appears
	Accountant to the law upon that pain.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 2><SCENE 4><37%>
	Admit no other way to save his life,—
	As I subscribe not that, nor any other,
	But in the loss of question,—that you, his sister,
	Finding yourself desir'd of such a person,
	Whose credit with the judge, or own great place,
	Could fetch your brother from the manacles
	Of the all-building law; and that there were
	No earthly mean to save him, but that either
	You must lay down the treasures of your body
	To this suppos'd, or else to let him suffer;
	What would you do?
<SPEECH 56><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Then must your brother die.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Were not you then as cruel as the sentence
	That you have slander'd so?
<SPEECH 58><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	You seem'd of late to make the law a tyrant;
	And rather prov'd the sliding of your brother
	A merriment than a vice.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	We are all frail.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 2><SCENE 4><38%>
	Nay, women are frail too.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	I think it well:
	And from this testimony of your own sex,—
	Since I suppose we are made to be no stronger
	Than faults may shake our frames,—let me be bold;
	I do arrest your words. Be that you are,
	That is, a woman; if you be more, you're none;
	If you be one, as you are well express'd
	By all external warrants, show it now,
	By putting on the destin'd livery.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Plainly conceive, I love you.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	He shall not, Isabel, if you give me love.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Believe me, on mine honour,
	My words express my purpose.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 2><SCENE 4><39%>
	Who will believe thee, Isabel?
	My unsoil'd name, the austereness of my life,
	My vouch against you, and my place i' the state,
	Will so your accusation overweigh,
	That you shall stifle in your own report
	And smell of calumny. I have begun;
	And now I give my sensual race the rein:
	Fit thy consent to my sharp appetite;
	Lay by all nicety and prolixious blushes,
	That banish what they sue for; redeem thy brother
	By yielding up thy body to my will,
	Or else he must not only die the death,
	But thy unkindness shall his death draw out
	To lingering sufferance. Answer me to-morrow,
	Or, by the affection that now guides me most,
	I'll prove a tyrant to him. As for you,
	Say what you can, my false o'erweighs your true.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 4><SCENE 4><78%>
	In most uneven and distracted manner.
	His actions show much like to madness: pray heaven his wisdom be not tainted! And why meet him at the gates, and redeliver our authorities there?
<SPEECH 67><ACT 4><SCENE 4><78%>
	And why should we proclaim it in an hour before his entering, that if any crave redress of injustice, they should exhibit their petitions in the street?
<SPEECH 68><ACT 4><SCENE 4><78%>
	Well, I beseech you, let it be proclaim'd:
	Betimes i' the morn I'll call you at your house;
	Give notice to such men of sort and suit
	As are to meet him.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 4><SCENE 4><78%>
	Good night.—
	This deed unshapes me quite, makes me unpregnant
	And dull to all proceedings. A deflower'd maid,
	And by an eminent body that enforc'd
	The law against it! But that her tender shame
	Will not proclaim against her maiden loss,
	How might she tongue me! Yet reason dares her no:
	For my authority bears so credent bulk,
	That no particular scandal once can touch:
	But it confounds the breather. He should have liv'd,
	Save that his riotous youth, with dangerous sense,
	Might in the times to come have ta'en revenge,
	By so receiving a dishonour'd life
	With ransom of such shame. Would yet he had liv'd!
	Alack! when once our grace we have forgot,
	Nothing goes right: we would, and we would not.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 5><SCENE 1><81%>
	Happy return be to your royal Grace!
<SPEECH 71><ACT 5><SCENE 1><81%>
	You make my bonds still greater.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	My lord, her wits, I fear me, are not firm:
	She hath been a suitor to me for her brother
	Cut off by course of justice,—
<SPEECH 73><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	And she will speak most bitterly and strange.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Charges she moe than me?
<SPEECH 75><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	This is a strange abuse. Let's see thy face.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	My lord, I must confess I know this woman;
	And five years since there was some speech of marriage
	Betwixt myself and her, which was broke off,
	Partly for that her promised proportions
	Came short of composition; but, in chief
	For that her reputation was disvalu'd
	In levity: since which time of five years
	I never spake with her, saw her, nor heard from her,
	Upon my faith and honour.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	I did but smile till now:
	Now, good my lord, give me the scope of justice;
	My patience here is touch'd. I do perceive
	These poor informal women are no more
	But instruments of some more mightier member
	That sets them on. Let me have way, my lord,
	To find this practice out.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	What can you vouch against him, Signior Lucio?
	Is this the man that you did tell us of?
<SPEECH 79><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	Hark how the villain would close now, after his treasonable abuses!
<SPEECH 80><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	What! resists he? Help him, Lucio.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 5><SCENE 1><94%>
	O my dread lord!
	I should be guiltier than my guiltiness,
	To think I can be undiscernible
	When I perceive your Grace, like power divine,
	Hath look'd upon my passes. Then, good prince,
	No longer session hold upon my shame,
	But let my trial be mine own confession:
	Immediate sentence then and sequent death
	Is all the grace I beg.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 5><SCENE 1><94%>
	I was, my lord.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 5><SCENE 1><98%>
	I am sorry that such sorrow I procure;
	And so deep sticks it in my penitent heart
	That I crave death more willingly than mercy:
	'Tis my deserving, and I do entreat it.
