<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 4><12%>
	Are not these large enough?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 4><12%>
	It is a man's voice. Gentle Isabella,
	Turn you the key, and know his business of him:
	You may, I may not; you are yet unsworn.
	When you have vow'd, you must not speak with men
	But in the presence of the prioress:
	Then, if you speak, you must not show your face,
	Or, if you show your face, you must not speak.
	He calls again; I pray you, answer him.
