<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	I do it not in evil disposition,
	But from Lord Angelo by special charge.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Away, sir! you must go.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	Here, if it like your honour.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 2><25%>
	Pray you, do. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> I'll know
	His pleasure; may be he will relent. Alas!
	He hath but as offended in a dream:
	All sects, all ages smack of this vice, and he
	To die for it!
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 2><25%>
	Is it your will Claudio shall die to-morrow?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 2><25%>
	Lest I might be too rash.
	Under your good correction, I have seen,
	When, after execution, Judgment hath
	Repented o'er his doom.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	I crave your honour's pardon.
	What shall be done, sir, with the groaning Juliet?
	She's very near her hour.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	Ay, my good lord; a very virtuous maid,
	And to be shortly of a sisterhood,
	If not already.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 2><26%>
	God save your honour!
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 2><27%>
	</STAGE DIR> Heaven give thee moving graces!
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	</STAGE DIR> Pray heaven she win him!
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	I am the provost. What's your will, good friar?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	I would do more than that, if more were needful.
	Look, here comes one: a gentlewoman of mine,
	Who, falling in the flaws of her own youth,
	Hath blister'd her report. She is with child,
	And he that got it, sentenc'd; a young man
	More fit to do another such offence,
	Than die for this.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	As I do think, to-morrow.
	</STAGE DIR> I have provided for you: stay a while,
	And you shall be conducted.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	'Tis pity of him.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 1><42%>
	Who's there? come in: the wish deserves a welcome.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 1><42%>
	And very welcome. Look, signior; here's your sister.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	As many as you please.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	What's your will, father?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	In good time.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	A bawd of eleven years' continuance, may it please your honour.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	So please you, this friar hath been with him, and advised him for the entertainment of death.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 2><63%>
	Come hither, sirrah. Can you cut off a man's head?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 2><63%>
	Come, sir, leave me your snatches, and yield me a direct answer. To-morrow morning are to die Claudio and Barnardine. Here is in our prison a common executioner, who in his office lacks a helper: if you will take it on you to assist him, it shall redeem you from your gyves; if not, you shall have your full time of imprisonment, and your deliverance with an unpitied whipping, for you have been a notorious bawd.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	What ho, Abhorson! Where's Abhorson, there?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	Sirrah, here's a fellow will help you to-morrow in your execution. If you think it meet, compound with him by the year, and let him abide here with you; if not, use him for the present, and dismiss him. He cannot plead his estimation with you; he hath been a bawd.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	Go to, sir; you weigh equally; a feather will turn the scale.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 2><65%>
	Are you agreed?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 2><65%>
	You, sirrah, provide your block and your axe to-morrow four o'clock.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 2><65%>
	Call hither Barnardine and Claudio:
	The one has my pity; not a jot the other,
	Being a murderer, though he were my brother.
	Look, here's the warrant, Claudio, for thy death:
	'Tis now dead midnight, and by eight to-morrow
	Thou must be made immortal. Where's Barnardine?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	Who can do good on him?
	Well, go; prepare yourself. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> But hark, what noise?—
	Heaven give your spirits comfort!—<STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> By and by.
	I hope it is some pardon or reprieve
	For the most gentle Claudio.
	Welcome, father.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	None since the curfew rung.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	No.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	What comfort is for Claudio?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	It is a bitter deputy.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 2><67%>
	There he must stay until the officer
	Arise to let him in; he is call'd up.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 2><67%>
	None, sir, none.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 2><67%>
	Happily
	You something know; yet, I believe there comes
	No countermand: no such example have we.
	Besides, upon the very siege of justice,
	Lord Angelo hath to the public ear
	Profess'd the contrary.
	This is his lordship's man.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 2><67%>
	I shall obey him.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	I told you; Lord Angelo, belike thinking me remiss in mine office, awakens me with this unwonted putting on; methinks strangely, for he hath not used it before.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	Whatsoever you may hear to the contrary, let Claudio be executed by four of the clock; and, in the afternoon, Barnardine. For my better satisfaction, let me have Claudio's head sent me by five. Let this be duly performed; with a thought that more depends on it than we must yet deliver. Thus fail not to do your office, as you will answer it at your peril.
	What say you to this, sir?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	A Bohemian born, but here nursed up and bred; one that is a prisoner nine years old.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	His friends still wrought reprieves for him; and, indeed, his fact, till now in the government of Lord Angelo, came not to an undoubtful proof.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	Most manifest, and not denied by himself.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 2><68%>
	A man that apprehends death no more dreadfully but as a drunken sleep; careless, reckless, and fearless of what's past, present, or to come; insensible of mortality, and desperately mortal.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 2><69%>
	He will hear none. He hath evermore had the liberty of the prison: give him leave to escape hence, he would not: drunk many times a day, if not many days entirely drunk. We have very oft awaked him, as if to carry him to execution, and showed him a seeming warrant for it: it hath not moved him at all.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 2><69%>
	Pray, sir, in what?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 2><69%>
	Alack! how may I do it, having the hour limited, and an express command, under penalty, to deliver his head in the view of Angelo? I may make my case as Claudio's to cross this in the smallest.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	Angelo hath seen them both, and will discover the favour.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	Pardon me, good father; it is against my oath.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	To him, and to his substitutes.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	But what likelihood is in that?
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	I know them both.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Now, sir, how do you find the prisoner?
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	Here in the prison, father,
	There died this morning of a cruel fever
	One Ragozine, a most notorious pirate,
	A man of Claudio's years; his beard and head
	Just of his colour. What if we do omit
	This reprobate till he were well inclin'd,
	And satisfy the deputy with the visage
	Of Ragozine, more like to Claudio?
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	This shall be done, good father, presently.
	But Barnardine must die this afternoon:
	And how shall we continue Claudio,
	To save me from the danger that might come
	If he were known alive?
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	I am your free dependant.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	Here is the head; I'll carry it myself.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	I'll make all speed.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 5><SCENE 1><97%>
	It was commanded so.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 5><SCENE 1><97%>
	No, my good lord; it was by private message.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 5><SCENE 1><97%>
	Pardon me, noble lord:
	I thought it was a fault, but knew it not,
	Yet did repent me, after more advice;
	For testimony whereof, one in the prison,
	That should by private order else have died
	I have reserv'd alive.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 5><SCENE 1><97%>
	His name is Barnardine.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 5><SCENE 1><98%>
	This, my lord.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 5><SCENE 1><98%>
	This is another prisoner that I sav'd,
	That should have died when Claudio lost his head,
	As like almost to Claudio as himself.
