<SPEECH 1><ACT 5><SCENE 3><87%>
	Speak to the business, Master secretary:
	Why are we met in council?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 5><SCENE 3><88%>
	Let him come in.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 5><SCENE 3><88%>
	My good lord archbishop, I'm very sorry
	To sit here at this present and behold
	That chair stand empty: but we all are men,
	In our own natures frail, and capable
	Of our flesh; few are angels: out of which frailty
	And want of wisdom, you, that best should teach us,
	Have misdemean'd yourself, and not a little,
	Toward the king first, then his laws, in filling
	The whole realm, by your teaching and your chaplains,—
	For so we are inform'd,—with new opinions,
	Divers and dangerous; which are heresies,
	And, not reform'd, may prove pernicious.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	This is too much;
	Forbear, for shame, my lords.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	Then thus for you, my lord: it stands agreed,
	I take it, by all voices, that forthwith
	You be convey'd to the Tower a prisoner;
	There to remain till the king's further pleasure
	Be known unto us. Are you all agreed, lords?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	This is the king's ring.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	Thus far,
	My most dread sov'reign, may it like your Grace
	To let my tongue excuse all. What was purpos'd
	Concerning his imprisonment, was rather—
	If there be faith in men—meant for his trial
	And fair purgation to the world, than malice,
	I'm sure, in me.
