<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 4><43%>
	Madam, you are call'd back.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 2><73%>
	How does your Grace?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 2><73%>
	Yes, madam; but I think your Grace,
	Out of the pain you suffer'd, gave no ear to't.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 2><73%>
	Well, the voice goes, madam:
	For after the stout Earl Northumberland
	Arrested him at York, and brought him forward,
	As a man sorely tainted, to his answer,
	He fell sick suddenly, and grew so ill
	He could not sit his mule.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 2><73%>
	At last, with easy roads, he came to Leicester;
	Lodg'd in the abbey, where the reverend abbot,
	With all his covent, honourably receiv'd him:
	To whom he gave these words: 'O! father abbot,
	An old man, broken with the storms of state,
	Is come to lay his weary bones among ye;
	Give him a little earth for charity.'
	So went to bed, where eagerly his sickness
	Pursu'd him still; and three nights after this,
	About the hour of eight,—which he himself
	Foretold should be his last,—full of repentance,
	Continual meditations, tears, and sorrows,
	He gave his honours to the world again,
	His blessed part to heaven, and slept in peace.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 4><SCENE 2><74%>
	Noble madam,
	Men's evil manners live in brass; their virtues
	We write in water. May it please your highness
	To hear me speak his good now?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 4><SCENE 2><74%>
	This cardinal,
	Though from a humble stock, undoubtedly
	Was fashion'd to much honour from his cradle.
	He was a scholar, and a ripe and good one;
	Exceeding wise, fair-spoken, and persuading;
	Lofty and sour to them that lov'd him not;
	But, to those men that sought him sweet as summer.
	And though he were unsatisfied in getting,—
	Which was a sin,—yet in bestowing, madam,
	He was most princely. Ever witness for him
	Those twins of learning that he rais'd in you,
	Ipswich, and Oxford! one of which fell with him,
	Unwilling to outlive the good that did it;
	The other, though unfinish'd, yet so famous,
	So excellent in art, and still so rising,
	That Christendom shall ever speak his virtue.
	His overthrow heap'd happiness upon him;
	For then, and not till then, he felt himself,
	And found the blessedness of being little:
	And, to add greater honours to his age
	Than man could give him, he died fearing God.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 4><SCENE 2><75%>
	She is asleep: good wench, let's sit down quiet,
	For fear we wake her: softly, gentle Patience.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 2><76%>
	Madam, we are here.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 2><76%>
	None, madam.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 2><77%>
	I am most joyful, madam, such good dreams
	Possess your fancy.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 2><77%>
	She is going, wench. Pray, pray.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 2><77%>
	You are to blame,
	Knowing she will not lose her wonted greatness,
	To use so rude behaviour; go to, kneel.
