<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	I thank your Grace,
	Healthful; and ever since a fresh admirer
	Of what I saw there.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	'Twixt Guynes and Arde:
	I was then present, saw them salute on horseback;
	Beheld them, when they lighted, how they clung
	In their embracement, as they grew together;
	Which had they, what four thron'd ones could have weigh'd
	Such a compounded one?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Then you lost
	The view of earthly glory: men might say,
	Till this time, pomp was single, but now married
	To one above itself. Each following day
	Became the next day's master, till the last
	Made former wonders its. To-day the French
	All clinquant, all in gold, like heathen gods,
	Shone down the English; and to-morrow they
	Made Britain India: every man that stood
	Show'd like a mine. Their dwarfish pages were
	As cherubins, all gilt: the madams, too,
	Not us'd to toil, did almost sweat to bear
	The pride upon them, that their very labour
	Was to them as a painting. Now this masque
	Was cried incomparable; and the ensuing night
	Made it a fool, and beggar. The two kings,
	Equal in lustre, were now best, now worst,
	As presence did present them; him in eye,
	Still him in praise; and, being present both,
	'Twas said they saw but one; and no discerner
	Durst wag his tongue in censure. When these suns—
	For so they phrase 'em—by their heralds challeng'd
	The noble spirits to arms, they did perform
	Beyond thought's compass; that former fabulous story,
	Being now seen possible enough, got credit,
	That Bevis was believ'd.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	As I belong to worship, and affect
	In honour honesty, the tract of every thing
	Would by a good discourser lose some life,
	Which action's self was tongue to. All was royal;
	To the disposing of it nought rebell'd,
	Order gave each thing view; the office did
	Distinctly his full function.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	One certes, that promises no element
	In such a business.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	All this was order'd by the good discretion
	Of the right reverend Cardinal of York.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	Surely, sir,
	There's in him stuff that puts him to these ends;
	For, being not propp'd by ancestry, whose grace
	Chalks successors their way, nor call'd upon
	For high feats done to the crown; neither allied
	To eminent assistants; but, spider-like,
	Out of his self-drawing web, he gives us note,
	The force of his own merit makes his way;
	A gift that heaven gives for him, which buys
	A place next to the king.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Grievingly I think,
	The peace between the French and us not values
	The cost that did conclude it.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Which is budded out;
	For France hath flaw'd the league, and hath attach'd
	Our merchants' goods at Bourdeaux.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Marry, is't.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	Like it your Grace,
	The state takes notice of the private difference
	Betwixt you and the cardinal. I advise you,—
	And take it from a heart that wishes towards you
	Honour and plenteous safety,—that you read
	The cardinal's malice and his potency
	Together; to consider further that
	What his high hatred would effect wants not
	A minister in his power. You know his nature,
	That he's revengeful; and I know his sword
	Hath a sharp edge: it's long, and 't may be said,
	It reaches far; and where 'twill not extend,
	Thither he darts it. Bosom up my counsel,
	You'll find it wholesome. Lo where comes that rock
	That I advise your shunning.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	What! are you chaf'd?
	Ask God for temperance; that's the appliance only
	Which your disease requires.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Stay, my lord,
	And let your reason with your choler question
	What 'tis you go about. To climb steep hills
	Requires slow pace at first: anger is like
	A full-hot horse, who being allow'd his way,
	Self-mettle tires him. Not a man in England
	Can advise me like you: be to yourself
	As you would to your friend.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Be advis'd;
	Heat not a furnace for your foe so hot
	That it do singe yourself. We may outrun
	By violent swiftness that which we run at,
	And lose by overrunning. Know you not,
	The fire that mounts the liquor till it run o'er,
	In seeming to augment it wastes it? Be advis'd:
	I say again, there is no English soul
	More stronger to direct you than yourself,
	If with the sap of reason you would quench,
	Or but allay, the fire of passion.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Say not, 'treasonous.'
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Faith, and so it did.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	I am sorry
	To hear this of him; and could wish he were
	Something mistaken in 't.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	Not almost appears,
	It doth appear; for, upon these taxations,
	The clothiers all, not able to maintain
	The many to them 'longing, have put off
	The spinsters, carders, fullers, weavers, who,
	Unfit for other life, compell'd by hunger
	And lack of other means, in desperate manner
	Daring the event to the teeth, are all in uproar,
	And danger serves among them.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	Well met, my Lord Chamberlain.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	What's the cause?
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	'Tis so:
	This is the cardinal's doing, the king-cardinal:
	That blind priest, like the eldest son of Fortune,
	Turns what he list. The king will know him one day.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	How holily he works in all his business,
	And with what zeal! for, now he has crack'd the league
	Between us and the emperor, the queen's great nephew,
	He dives into the king's soul, and there scatters
	Dangers, doubts, wringing of the conscience,
	Fears, and despairs; and all these for his marriage:
	And out of all these, to restore the king,
	He counsels a divorce; a loss of her,
	That like a jewel has hung twenty years
	About his neck, yet never lost her lustre;
	Of her, that loves him with that excellence
	That angels love good men with; even of her,
	That, when the greatest stroke of fortune falls,
	Will bless the king: and is not this course pious?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	We had need pray,
	And heartily, for our deliverance;
	Or this imperious man will work us all
	From princes into pages. All men's honours
	Lie like one lump before him, to be fashion'd
	Into what pitch he please.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Let's in;
	And with some other business put the king
	From these sad thoughts, that work too much upon him.
	My lord, you'll bear us company?
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Thanks, my good Lord Chamberlain.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	Pray God he be not angry.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	A gracious king that pardons all offences
	Malice ne'er meant: our breach of duty this way
	Is business of estate; in which we come
	To know your royal pleasure.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	</STAGE DIR> This priest has no pride in him!
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	</STAGE DIR> If it do,
	I'll venture one have-at-him.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	If you will now unite in your complaints,
	And force them with a constancy, the cardinal
	Cannot stand under them: if you omit
	The offer of this time, I cannot promise
	But that you shall sustain moe new disgraces
	With these you bear already.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	O! fear him not;
	His spell in that is out: the king hath found
	Matter against him that for ever mars
	The honey of his language. No, he's settled,
	Not to come off, in his displeasure.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 2><53%>
	Believe it, this is true:
	In the divorce his contrary proceedings
	Are all unfolded; wherein he appears
	As I would wish mine enemy.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	All men's.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	Marry, amen!
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	But, my lord,
	When returns Cranmer?
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	This same Cranmer's
	A worthy fellow, and hath ta'en much pain
	In the king's business.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	So I hear.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	Observe, observe; he's moody.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 2><56%>
	He's discontented.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 2><56%>
	He is vex'd at something.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 2><56%>
	My lord, we have
	Stood here observing him; some strange commotion
	Is in his brain: he bites his lip, and starts;
	Stops on a sudden, looks upon the ground,
	Then lays his finger on his temple; straight
	Springs out into fast gait; then stops again,
	Strikes his breast hard; and anon he casts
	His eye against the moon: in most strange postures
	We have seen him set himself.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	It's heaven's will:
	Some spirit put this paper in the packet
	To bless your eye withal.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 2><60%>
	Hear the king's pleasure, cardinal: who commands you
	To render up the great seal presently
	Into our hands; and to confine yourself
	To Asher-house, my Lord of Winchester's,
	Till you hear further from his highness.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 2><62%>
	Those articles, my lord, are in the king's hand;
	But, thus much, they are foul ones.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 2><63%>
	Then, that in all you writ to Rome, or else
	To foreign princes, Ego et Rex meus
	Was still inscrib'd; in which you brought the king
	To be your servant.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 2><64%>
	And so we'll leave you to your meditations
	How to live better. For your stubborn answer
	About the giving back the great seal to us,
	The king shall know it, and, no doubt, shall thank you.
	So fare you well, my little good Lord Cardinal.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 5><SCENE 3><88%>
	Who waits there?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	Do you think, my lords,
	The king will suffer but the little finger
	Of this man to be vex'd?
