<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Which is the duke's own person?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	I myself reprehend his own person, for I am his Grace's tharborough: but I would see his own person in flesh and blood.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Signior Arm—Arm—commends you. There's villany abroad: this letter will tell you more.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	Me, an't please you; I am Antony Dull.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><15%>
	Sir, the duke's pleasure is, that you keep Costard safe: and you must let him take no delight nor no penance, but a' must fast three days a week. For this damsel, I must keep her at the park; she is allowed for the day-woman.
	Fare you well.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><15%>
	Come, Jaquenetta, away!
<SPEECH 7><ACT 4><SCENE 2><40%>
	'Twas not a haud credo; 'twas a pricket.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 4><SCENE 2><40%>
	I said the deer was not a haud credo; 'twas a pricket.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 2><41%>
	You two are book-men: can you tell by your wit,
	What was a month old at Cain's birth, that's not five weeks old as yet?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 2><41%>
	What is Dictynna?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 2><41%>
	'Tis true indeed: the collusion holds in the exchange.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 2><41%>
	And I say the pollusion holds in the exchange, for the moon is never but a month old; and I say beside that 'twas a pricket that the princess killed.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 2><42%>
	</STAGE DIR> If a talent be a claw, look how he claws him with a talent.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 5><SCENE 1><65%>
	Nor understood none neither, sir.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 5><SCENE 1><65%>
	I'll make one in a dance, or so; or I will play the tabor to the Worthies, and let them dance the hay.
