<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	I am resolv'd; 'tis but a three years' fast:
	The mind shall banquet, though the body pine:
	Fat paunches have lean pates, and dainty bits
	Make rich the ribs, but bankrupt quite the wits.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	You swore to that, Berowne, and to the rest.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	He weeds the corn, and still lets grow the weeding.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	Four days ago.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	Marry, that did I.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	To fright them hence with that dread penalty.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Costard the swain and he shall be our sport;
	And, so to study, three years is but short.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	A high hope for a low heaven: God grant us patience!
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	To hear meekly, sir, and to laugh moderately; or to forbear both.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	I beseech you a word: what is she in the white?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Perchance light in the light. I desire her name.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Pray you, sir, whose daughter?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	God's blessing on your beard!
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Nay, my choler is ended.
	She is a most sweet lady.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 4><SCENE 3><48%>
	Ay me! I am forsworn.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 3><48%>
	Am I the first that have been perjur'd so?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 3><48%>
	I fear these stubborn lines lack power to move.
	O sweet Maria, empress of my love!
	These numbers will I tear, and write in prose.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 3><48%>
	This same shall go.
	Did not the heavenly rhetoric of thine eye,
	'Gainst whom the world cannot hold argument,
	Persuade my heart to this false perjury?
	Vows for thee broke deserve not punishment.
	A woman I forswore; but I will prove,
	Thou being a goddess, I forswore not thee:
	My vow was earthly, thou a heavenly love;
	Thy grace, being gain'd, cures all disgrace in me.
	Vows are but breath, and breath a vapour is:
	Then thou, fair sun, which on my earth dost shine,
	Exhal'st this vapour-vow; in thee it is:
	If broken, then, it is no fault of mine:
	If by me broke, what fool is not so wise
	To lose an oath to win a paradise!
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 3><49%>
	By whom shall I send this?—Company! stay.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 3><50%>
	And I had mine!
<SPEECH 21><ACT 4><SCENE 3><51%>
	</STAGE DIR> Dumaine, thy love is far from charity,
	That in love's grief desir'st society:
	You may look pale, but I should blush, I know,
	To be o'erheard and taken napping so.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 3><54%>
	It did move him to passion, and therefore let's hear it.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 3><56%>
	And since her time are colliers counted bright.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 3><56%>
	Look, here's thy love: <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> my foot and her face see.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 3><57%>
	O! some authority how to proceed;
	Some tricks, some quillets, how to cheat the devil.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 3><60%>
	Now to plain-dealing; lay these glozes by;
	Shall we resolve to woo these girls of France?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 5><SCENE 2><75%>
	I know the reason, lady, why you ask.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 5><SCENE 2><75%>
	You have a double tongue within your mask,
	And would afford my speechless visor half.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 5><SCENE 2><75%>
	A calf, fair lady!
<SPEECH 30><ACT 5><SCENE 2><75%>
	Let's part the word.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 5><SCENE 2><75%>
	Look, how you butt yourself in these sharp mocks.
	Will you give horns, chaste lady? do not so.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 5><SCENE 2><76%>
	One word in private with you, ere I die.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 5><SCENE 2><89%>
	The face of an old Roman coin, scarce seen.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	His calf is too big for Hector.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	Stuck with cloves.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 5><SCENE 2><91%>
	That columbine.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 5><SCENE 2><91%>
	I must rather give it the rein, for it runs against Hector.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 5><SCENE 2><95%>
	So did our looks.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	What says Maria?
<SPEECH 40><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	I'll stay with patience; but the time is long.
