<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Good Lord Boyet, my beauty, though but mean,
	Needs not the painted flourish of your praise:
	Beauty is bought by judgment of the eye,
	Not utter'd by base sale of chapmen's tongues.
	I am less proud to hear you tell my worth
	Than you much willing to be counted wise
	In spending your wit in the praise of mine.
	But now to task the tasker: good Boyet,
	You are not ignorant, all-telling fame
	Doth noise abroad, Navarre hath made a vow,
	Till painful study shall out-wear three years,
	No woman may approach his silent court:
	Therefore to us seemth it a needful course,
	Before we enter his forbidden gates,
	To know his pleasure; and in that behalf,
	Bold of your worthiness, we single you
	As our best-moving fair solicitor.
	Tell him, the daughter of the King of France,
	On serious business, craving quick dispatch,
	Importunes personal conference with his Grace.
	Haste, signify so much; while we attend,
	Like humble-visag'd suitors, his high will.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	All pride is willing pride, and yours is so.
	Who are the votaries, my loving lords,
	That are vow-fellows with this virtuous duke?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	Know you the man?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 1><19%>
	Some merry mocking lord, belike; is't so?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 1><19%>
	Such short-liv'd wits do wither as they grow.
	Who are the rest?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 1><19%>
	God bless my ladies! are they all in love,
	That every one her own hath garnished
	With such bedecking ornaments of praise?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	Now, what admittance, lord?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	'Fair,' I give you back again; and 'welcome' I have not yet: the roof of this court is too high to be yours, and welcome to the wide fields too base to be mine.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	I will be welcome, then: conduct me thither.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	Our Lady help my lord! he'll be forsworn.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	Why, will shall break it; will, and nothing else.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	Were my lord so, his ignorance were wise,
	Where now his knowledge must prove ignorance.
	I hear your grace hath sworn out house-keeping:
	'Tis deadly sin to keep that oath, my lord,
	And sin to break it.
	But pardon me, I am too sudden-bold:
	To teach a teacher ill beseemeth me.
	Vouchsafe to read the purpose of my coming,
	And suddenly resolve me in my suit.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><21%>
	You will the sooner that I were away,
	For you'll prove perjur'd if you make me stay.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	You do the king my father too much wrong
	And wrong the reputation of your name,
	In so unseeming to confess receipt
	Of that which hath so faithfully been paid.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	We arrest your word.
	Boyet, you can produce acquittances
	For such a sum from special officers
	Of Charles his father.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	Sweet health and fair desires consort your Grace!
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	It was well done of you to take him at his word.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Good wits will be jangling; but, gentles, agree.
	This civil war of wits were much better us'd
	On Navarre and his book-men, for here 'tis abus'd.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	With what?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Your reason.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Come to our pavilion: Boyet is dispos'd.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 1><34%>
	Was that the king, that spurr'd his horse so hard
	Against the steep uprising of the hill?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 1><34%>
	Whoe'er a' was, a' show'd a mounting mind.
	Well, lords, to-day we shall have our dispatch;
	On Saturday we will return to France.
	Then, forester, my friend, where is the bush
	That we must stand and play the murderer in?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 1><34%>
	I thank my beauty, I am fair that shoot,
	And thereupon thou speak'st the fairest shoot.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 1><34%>
	What, what? first praise me, and again say no?
	O short-liv'd pride! Not fair? alack for woe!
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 1><34%>
	Nay, never paint me now:
	Where fair is not, praise cannot mend the brow.
	Here, good my glass:—<STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Take this for telling true:
	Fair payment for foul words is more than due.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 1><34%>
	See, see! my beauty will be sav'd by merit.
	O heresy in fair, fit for these days!
	A giving hand, though foul, shall have fair praise.
	But come, the bow: now mercy goes to kill,
	And shooting well is then accounted ill.
	Thus will I save my credit in the shoot:
	Not wounding, pity would not let me do't;
	If wounding, then it was to show my skill,
	That more for praise than purpose meant to kill.
	And out of question so it is sometimes,
	Glory grows guilty of detested crimes,
	When, for fame's sake, for praise, an outward part,
	We bend to that the working of the heart;
	As I for praise alone now seek to spill
	The poor deer's blood, that my heart means no ill.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 1><35%>
	Only for praise; and praise we may afford
	To any lady that subdues a lord.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 1><35%>
	Thou shalt know her, fellow, by the rest that have no heads.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 1><35%>
	The thickest, and the tallest.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 1><36%>
	What's your will, sir? what's your will?
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 1><36%>
	O! thy letter, thy letter; he's a good friend of mine.
	Stand aside, good bearer. Boyet, you can carve;
	Break up this capon.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 1><36%>
	We will read it, I swear.
	Break the neck of the wax, and every one give ear.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 1><37%>
	What plume of feathers is he that indited this letter?
	What vane? what weathercock? did you ever hear better?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 1><37%>
	Else your memory is bad, going o'er it erewhile.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 1><37%>
	Thou, fellow, a word.
	Who gave thee this letter?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 1><37%>
	To whom shouldst thou give it?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 1><38%>
	From which lord, to which lady?
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 1><38%>
	Thou hast mistaken his letter. Come, lords, away.
	Here, sweet, put up this: 'twill be thine another day.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 5><SCENE 2><66%>
	Sweet hearts, we shall be rich ere we depart,
	If fairings come thus plentifully in: lady wall'd about with diamonds!
	Look you what I have from the loving king.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 5><SCENE 2><66%>
	Nothing but this! yes, as much love in rime
	As would be cramm'd up in a sheet of paper,
	Writ o' both sides the leaf, margent and all,
	That he was fain to seal on Cupid's name.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 5><SCENE 2><67%>
	Well bandied both; a set of wit well play'd.
	But Rosaline, you have a favour too:
	Who sent it? and what is it?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 5><SCENE 2><67%>
	Anything like?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 5><SCENE 2><67%>
	Beauteous as ink; a good conclusion.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 5><SCENE 2><67%>
	But what was sent to you from fair Dumaine?
<SPEECH 46><ACT 5><SCENE 2><67%>
	Did he not send you twain?
<SPEECH 47><ACT 5><SCENE 2><68%>
	I think no less. Dost thou not wish in heart
	The chain were longer and the letter short?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 5><SCENE 2><68%>
	We are wise girls to mock our lovers so.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 5><SCENE 2><68%>
	None are so surely caught, when they are catch'd,
	As wit turn'd fool: folly, in wisdom hatch'd,
	Hath wisdom's warrant and the help of school
	And wit's own grace to grace a learned fool.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 5><SCENE 2><69%>
	Here comes Boyet, and mirth is in his face.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 5><SCENE 2><69%>
	Thy news, Boyet?
<SPEECH 52><ACT 5><SCENE 2><69%>
	Saint Denis to Saint Cupid! What are they
	That charge their breath against us? say, scout, say.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 5><SCENE 2><70%>
	But what, but what, come they to visit us?
<SPEECH 54><ACT 5><SCENE 2><70%>
	And will they so? the gallants shall be task'd:
	For, ladies, we will every one be mask'd,
	And not a man of them shall have the grace,
	Despite of suit, to see a lady's face.
	Hold, Rosaline, this favour thou shalt wear,
	And then the king will court thee for his dear:
	Hold, take thou this, my sweet, and give me thine,
	So shall Berowne take me for Rosaline,
	And change you favours too; so shall your loves
	Woo contrary, deceiv'd by these removes.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 5><SCENE 2><71%>
	The effect of my intent is, to cross theirs:
	They do it but in mocking merriment;
	And mock for mock is only my intent.
	Their several counsels they unbosom shall
	To loves mistook and so be mock'd withal
	Upon the next occasion that we meet,
	With visages display'd, to talk and greet.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 5><SCENE 2><71%>
	No, to the death, we will not move a foot:
	Nor to their penn'd speech render we no grace;
	But while 'tis spoke each turn away her face.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 5><SCENE 2><71%>
	Therefore I do it; and I make no doubt,
	The rest will ne'er come in, if he be out.
	There's no such sport as sport by sport o'erthrown,
	To make theirs ours and ours none but our own:
	So shall we stay, mocking intended game,
	And they, well mock'd, depart away with shame.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 5><SCENE 2><74%>
	Honey, and milk, and sugar; there are three.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 5><SCENE 2><75%>
	Seventh sweet, adieu:
	Since you can cog, I'll play no more with you.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 5><SCENE 2><75%>
	Let it not be sweet.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 5><SCENE 2><75%>
	Gall! bitter.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 5><SCENE 2><76%>
	Twenty adieus, my frozen Muscovits.
	Are these the breed of wits so wonder'd at?
<SPEECH 63><ACT 5><SCENE 2><76%>
	O poverty in wit, kingly-poor flout!
	Will they not, think you, hang themselves to-night?
	Or ever, but in visors, show their faces?
	This pert Berowne was out of countenance quite.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 5><SCENE 2><76%>
	Berowne did swear himself out of all suit.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 5><SCENE 2><77%>
	Qualm, perhaps.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 5><SCENE 2><77%>
	Go, sickness as thou art!
<SPEECH 67><ACT 5><SCENE 2><77%>
	And quick Berowne hath plighted faith to me.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 5><SCENE 2><77%>
	Will they return?
<SPEECH 69><ACT 5><SCENE 2><77%>
	How blow? how blow? speak to be understood.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 5><SCENE 2><77%>
	Avaunt perplexity! What shall we do
	If they return in their own shapes to woo?
<SPEECH 71><ACT 5><SCENE 2><78%>
	Whip to your tents, as roes run over land.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 5><SCENE 2><79%>
	'Fair,' in 'all hail,' is foul, as I conceive.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 5><SCENE 2><79%>
	Then wish me better: I will give you leave.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 5><SCENE 2><79%>
	This field shall hold me, and so hold your vow:
	Nor God, nor I, delights in perjur'd men.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 5><SCENE 2><79%>
	You nick-name virtue; vice you should have spoke;
	For virtue's office never breaks men's troth.
	Now, by my maiden honour, yet as pure
	As the unsullied lily, I protest,
	A world of torments though I should endure,
	I would not yield to be your house's guest;
	So much I hate a breaking cause to be
	Of heavenly oaths, vow'd with integrity.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 5><SCENE 2><80%>
	Not so, my lord; it is not so, I swear;
	We have had pastime here and pleasant game.
	A mess of Russians left us but of late.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 5><SCENE 2><80%>
	Ay, in truth, my lord;
	Trim gallants, full of courtship and of state.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 5><SCENE 2><81%>
	Amaz'd, my lord? Why looks your highness sad?
<SPEECH 79><ACT 5><SCENE 2><82%>
	No, they are free that gave these tokens to us.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 5><SCENE 2><82%>
	The fairest is confession.
	Were you not here, but even now, disguis'd?
<SPEECH 81><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	And were you well advis'd?
<SPEECH 82><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	When you then were here,
	What did you whisper in your lady's ear?
<SPEECH 83><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	When she shall challenge this, you will reject her.
<SPEECH 84><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	Peace! peace! forbear;
	Your oath once broke, you force not to forswear.
<SPEECH 85><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	I will; and therefore keep it. Rosaline,
	What did the Russian whisper in your ear?
<SPEECH 86><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	God give thee joy of him! the noble lord
	Most honourably doth uphold his word.
<SPEECH 87><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	Pardon me, sir, this jewel did she wear;
	And Lord Berowne, I thank him, is my dear.
	What, will you have me, or your pearl again?
<SPEECH 88><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	Nay, my good lord, let me o'errule you now.
	That sport best pleases that doth least know how;
	Where zeal strives to content, and the contents
	Die in the zeal of those which it presents;
	Their form confounded makes most form in mirth,
	When great things labouring perish in their birth.
<SPEECH 89><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	Doth this man serve God?
<SPEECH 90><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	He speaks not like a man of God's making,
<SPEECH 91><ACT 5><SCENE 2><87%>
	Great thanks, great Pompey.
<SPEECH 92><ACT 5><SCENE 2><88%>
	The conqueror is dismay'd. Proceed, good Alexander.
<SPEECH 93><ACT 5><SCENE 2><88%>
	Stand aside, good Pompey.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	Alas! poor Maccabæus, how hath he been baited.
<SPEECH 95><ACT 5><SCENE 2><91%>
	Speak, brave Hector; we are much delighted.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	Welcome, Marcade;
	But that thou interrupt'st our merriment.
<SPEECH 97><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	Dead, for my life!
<SPEECH 98><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	Boyet, prepare: I will away to-night.
<SPEECH 99><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	Prepare, I say. I thank you, gracious lords,
	For all your fair endeavours; and entreat,
	Out of a new-sad soul, that you vouchsafe
	In your rich wisdom to excuse or hide
	The liberal opposition of our spirits,
	If over-boldly we have borne ourselves
	In the converse of breath; your gentleness
	Was guilty of it. Farewell, worthy lord!
	A heavy heart bears not a nimble tongue,
	Excuse me so, coming so short of thanks
	For my great suit so easily obtain'd.
<SPEECH 100><ACT 5><SCENE 2><94%>
	I understand you not: my griefs are double.
<SPEECH 101><ACT 5><SCENE 2><95%>
	We have receiv'd your letters full of love;
	Your favours, the embassadors of love;
	And, in our maiden council, rated them
	At courtship, pleasant jest, and courtesy,
	As bombast and as lining to the time.
	But more devout than this in our respects
	Have we not been; and therefore met your loves
	In their own fashion, like a merriment.
<SPEECH 102><ACT 5><SCENE 2><95%>
	A time, methinks, too short
	To make a world-without-end bargain in.
	No, no, my lord, your Grace is perjur'd much,
	Full of dear guiltiness; and therefore this:
	If for my love,—as there is no such cause,—
	You will do aught, this shall you do for me:
	Your oath I will not trust; but go with speed
	To some forlorn and naked hermitage,
	Remote from all the pleasures of the world;
	There stay, until the twelve celestial signs
	Have brought about their annual reckoning.
	If this austere insociable life
	Change not your offer made in heat of blood;
	If frosts and fasts, hard lodging and thin weeds,
	Nip not the gaudy blossoms of your love,
	But that it bear this trial and last love;
	Then, at the expiration of the year,
	Come challenge me, challenge me by these deserts,
	And, by this virgin palm now kissing thine,
	I will be thine; and, till that instant, shut
	My woful self up in a mourning house,
	Raining the tears of lamentation
	For the remembrance of my father's death.
	If this thou do deny, let our hands part;
	Neither intitled in the other's heart.
<SPEECH 103><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	</STAGE DIR> Ay, sweet my lord; and so I take my leave.
<SPEECH 104><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	Was not that Hector?
