<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 3><42%>
	My lord of Hereford, my message is to you.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 3><42%>
	Mistake me not, my lord; 'tis not my meaning
	To raze one title of your honour out:
	To you, my lord, I come, what lord you will,
	From the most gracious regent of this land,
	The Duke of York, to know what pricks you on
	To take advantage of the absent time
	And fright our native peace with self-born arms.
