<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	If that thy valour stand on sympathies,
	There is my gage, Aumerle, in gage to thine:
	By that fair sun which shows me where thou stand'st,
	I heard thee say, and vauntingly thou spak'st it,
	That thou wert cause of noble Gloucester's death.
	If thou deny'st it twenty times, thou liest;
	And I will turn thy falsehood to thy heart,
	Where it was forged, with my rapier's point.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	Now, by my soul, I would it were this hour.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 1><70%>
	'Tis very true: you were in presence then;
	And you can witness with me this is true.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 1><70%>
	Surrey, thou best.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 1><70%>
	How fondly dost thou spur a forward horse!
	If I dare eat, or drink, or breathe, or live,
	I dare meet Surrey in a wilderness,
	And spit upon him, whilst I say he lies,
	And lies, and lies: there is my bond of faith
	To tie thee to my strong correction.
	As I intend to thrive in this new world,
	Aumerle is guilty of my true appeal:
	Besides, I heard the banish'd Norfolk say
	That thou, Aumerle, didst send two of thy men
	To execute the noble duke at Calais.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 5><SCENE 6><99%>
	My lord, I have from Oxford sent to London
	The heads of Brocas and Sir Bennet Seely,
	Two of the dangerous consorted traitors
	That sought at Oxford thy dire overthrow.
