<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 1><70%>
	My Lord Fitzwater, I do remember well
	The very time Aumerle and you did talk.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 1><70%>
	As false, by heaven, as heaven itself is true.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 1><70%>
	Dishonourable boy!
	That he shall lie so heavy on my sword
	That it shall render vengeance and revenge,
	Till thou the lie-giver and that lie do lie
	In earth as quiet as thy father's skull.
	In proof whereof, there is my honour's pawn:
	Engage it to the trial if thou dar'st.
