<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><11%>
	Sir, you have sav'd my longing, and I feed
	Most hungerly on your sight.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><16%>
	My heart is ever at your service, my lord.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><16%>
	So they were bleeding-new, my lord, there's no meat like 'em: I could wish my best friend at such a feast.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><22%>
	Ay, defil'd land, my lord.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE 5><49%>
	Honour, health, and compassion to the senate!
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE 5><49%>
	I am a humble suitor to your virtues;
	For pity is the virtue of the law,
	And none but tyrants use it cruelly.
	It pleases time and fortune to lie heavy
	Upon a friend of mine, who, in hot blood,
	Hath stepp'd into the law, which is past depth
	To those that without heed to plunge into 't.
	He is a man, setting his fate aside,
	Of comely virtues;
	Nor did he soil the fact with cowardice,—
	An honour in him which buys out his fault,—
	But, with a noble fury and fair spirit,
	Seeing his reputation touch'd to death,
	He did oppose his foe;
	And with such sober and unnoted passion
	He did behave his anger, ere 'twas spent,
	As if he had but prov'd an argument.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE 5><50%>
	My lord,—
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 5><51%>
	My lords, then, under favour, pardon me,
	If I speak like a captain.
	Why do fond men expose themselves to battle,
	And not endure all threats? sleep upon't,
	And let the foes quietly cut their throats
	Without repugnancy? If there be
	Such valour in the bearing, what make we
	Abroad? why then, women are more valiant
	That stay at home, if bearing carry it,
	And the ass more captain than the lion, the felon
	Loaden with irons wiser than the judge,
	If wisdom be in suffering. O my lords!
	As you are great, be pitifully good:
	Who cannot condemn rashness in cold blood?
	To kill, I grant, is sin's extremest gust;
	But, in defence, by mercy, 'tis most just.
	To be in anger is impiety;
	But who is man that is not angry?
	Weigh but the crime with this.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 5><51%>
	In vain! his service done
	At Lacedæmon and Byzantium
	Were a sufficient briber for his life.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 5><51%>
	I say, my lords, he has done fair service,
	And slain in fight many of your enemies.
	How full of valour did he bear himself
	In the last conflict, and made plenteous wounds!
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 5><52%>
	Hard fate! he might have died in war.
	My lords, if not for any parts in him,—
	Though his right arm might purchase his own time,
	And be in debt to none,—yet, more to move you,
	Take my deserts to his, and join 'em both;
	And, for I know your reverend ages love
	Security, I'll pawn my victories, all
	My honour to you, upon his good returns.
	If by this crime he owes the law his life,
	Why, let the war receive't in valiant gore;
	For law is strict, and war is nothing more.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 5><52%>
	Must it be so? it must not be. My lords,
	I do beseech you, know me.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 5><52%>
	Call me to your remembrances.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 5><52%>
	I cannot think but your age has forgot me;
	It could not else be I should prove so base,
	To sue, and be denied such common grace.
	My wounds ache at you.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 5><53%>
	Banish me!
	Banish your dotage; banish usury,
	That makes the senate ugly.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 5><53%>
	Now the gods keep you old enough; that you may live
	Only in bone, that none may look on you!
	I am worse than mad: I have kept back their foes,
	While they have told their money and let out
	Their coin upon large interest; I myself
	Rich only in large hurts: all those for this?
	Is this the balsam that the usuring senate
	Pours into captains' wounds? Banishment!
	It comes not ill; I hate not to be banish'd;
	It is a cause worthy my spleen and fury,
	That I may strike at Athens. I'll cheer up
	My discontented troops, and lay for hearts.
	'Tis honour with most lands to be at odds;
	Soldiers should brook as little wrongs as gods.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 3><65%>
	What art thou there? speak.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 3><65%>
	What is thy name? Is man so hateful to thee,
	That art thyself a man?
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 3><65%>
	I know thee well,
	But in thy fortunes am unlearn'd and strange.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 3><66%>
	How came the noble Timon to this change?
<SPEECH 21><ACT 4><SCENE 3><66%>
	Noble Timon, what friendship may I do thee?
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 3><66%>
	What is it, Timon?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 3><66%>
	I have heard in some sort of thy miseries.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 3><66%>
	I see them now; then was a blessed time.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 3><66%>
	Pardon him, sweet Timandra, for his wits
	Are drown'd and lost in his calamities.
	I have but little gold of late, brave Timon,
	The want whereof doth daily make revolt
	In my penurious band: I have heard and griev'd
	How cursed Athens, mindless of thy worth,
	Forgetting thy great deeds, when neighbour states,
	But for thy sword and fortune, trod upon them,—
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	I am thy friend, and pity thee, dear Timon.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Why, fare thee well:
	Here is some gold for thee.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	When I have laid proud Athens on a heap,—
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Ay, Timon, and have cause.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 3><67%>
	Why me, Timon?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 3><68%>
	Hast thou gold yet? I'll take the gold thou giv'st me,
	Not all thy counsel.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 3><70%>
	Strike up the drum towards Athens! Farewell, Timon:
	If I thrive well, I'll visit thee again.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 3><70%>
	I never did thee harm.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 3><70%>
	Call'st thou that harm?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 3><70%>
	We but offend him. Strike!
<SPEECH 36><ACT 5><SCENE 4><96%>
	Sound to this coward and lascivious town
	Our terrible approach.
	Till now you have gone on, and fill'd the time
	With all licentious measure, making your wills
	The scope of justice; till now myself and such
	As slept within the shadow of your power
	Have wander'd with our travers'd arms, and breath'd
	Our sufferance vainly. Now the time is flush,
	When crouching marrow, in the bearer strong,
	Cries of itself, 'No more:' now breathless wrong
	Shall sit and pant in your great chairs of ease,
	And pursy insolence shall break his wind
	With fear and horrid flight.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 5><SCENE 4><99%>
	Then there's my glove;
	Descend, and open your uncharged ports:
	Those enemies of Timon's and mine own
	Whom you yourselves shall set out for reproof,
	Fall, and no more; and, to atone your fears
	With my more noble meaning, not a man
	Shall pass his quarter, or offend the stream
	Of regular justice in your city's bounds,
	But shall be render'd to your public laws
	At heaviest answer.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 5><SCENE 4><99%>
	Descend, and keep your words.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 5><SCENE 4><99%>
	Here lies a wretched corse, of wretched soul bereft:
	Seek not my name: a plague consume you wicked caitiffs left!
	Here lie I, Timon; who, alive, all living men did hate:
	Pass by, and curse thy fill; but pass and stay not here thy gait.
	These well express in thee thy latter spirits:
	Though thou abhorr'dst in us our human griefs,
	Scorn'dst our brain's flow and those our droplets which
	From niggard nature fall, yet rich conceit
	Taught thee to make vast Neptune weep for aye
	On thy low grave, on faults forgiven. Dead
	Is noble Timon; of whose memory
	Hereafter more. Bring me into your city,
	And I will use the olive with my sword;
	Make war breed peace; make peace stint war; make each
	Prescribe to other as each other's leech.
	Let our drums strike.
