<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	As you have said, my lord.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 3><SCENE 1><35%>
	I thank you, sir.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 3><SCENE 1><36%>
	His health is well, sir.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 3><SCENE 1><36%>
	Faith, nothing but an empty box, sir; which, in my lord's behalf, I come to entreat your honour to supply; who, having great and instant occasion to use fifty talents, hath sent to your lordship to furnish him, nothing doubting your present assistance therein.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE 1><37%>
	Your lordship speaks your pleasure.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE 1><37%>
	Is't possible the world should so much differ,
	And we alive that liv'd? Fly, damned baseness,
	To him that worships thee.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE 1><38%>
	May these add to the number that may scald thee!
	Let molten coin be thy damnation,
	Thou disease of a friend, and not himself!
	Has friendship such a faint and milky heart
	It turns in less than two nights? O you gods!
	I feel my master's passion. This slave unto his honour
	Has my lord's meat in him:
	Why should it thrive and turn to nutriment
	When he is turn'd to poison?
	O! may diseases only work upon 't,
	And, when he's sick to death, let not that part of nature
	Which my lord paid for, be of any power
	To expel sickness, but prolong his hour.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 4><46%>
	No, indeed, he is not.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 4><46%>
	I need not tell him that; he knows you are too diligent.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 4><47%>
	</STAGE DIR> Servilius, help! my lord! my lord!
