<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Why, how now, Ajax! wherefore do you this?
	How now, Thersites! what's the matter, man?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Ay; what's the matter?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	So I do: what's the matter?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	'Well!' why, so I do.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	I know that, fool.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	What?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Nay, good Ajax.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Nay, I must hold you.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Peace, fool!
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Will you set your wit to a fool's?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	What's the quarrel?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Your last service was sufferance, 'twas not voluntary; no man is beaten voluntary: Ajax was here the voluntary, and you as under an impress.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	What, with me too, Thersites?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	What, what?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	There's for you, Patroclus.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><27%>
	Marry, this, sir, is proclaim'd through all our host:
	That Hector, by the fifth hour of the sun,
	Will, with a trumpet, 'twixt our tents and Troy
	To morrow morning call some knight to arms
	That hath a stomach; and such a one that dare
	Maintain—I know not what: 'tis trash. Farewell.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><27%>
	I know not: it is put to lottery; otherwise,
	He knew his man.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	Who's there?
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	Where, where? Art thou come? Why, my cheese, my digestion, why hast thou not served thyself in to my table so many meals? Come, what's Agamemnon?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	O! tell, tell.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	He is a privileged man. Proceed, Thersites.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Derive this; come.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Patroclus, I'll speak with nobody. Come in with me, Thersites.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 3><52%>
	What! comes the general to speak with me?
	You know my mind; I'll fight no more 'gainst Troy.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 3><53%>
	No.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 3><53%>
	Good day, good day.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 3><53%>
	What! does the cuckold scorn me?
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 3><53%>
	Good morrow, Ajax.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 3><53%>
	Good morrow.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 3><53%>
	What mean these fellows? Know they not Achilles?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 3><53%>
	What! am I poor of late?
	'Tis certain, greatness, once fall'n out with fortune,
	Must fall out with men too: what the declin'd is
	He shall as soon read in the eyes of others
	As feel in his own fall; for men, like butterflies,
	Show not their mealy wings but to the summer,
	And not a man, for being simply man,
	Hath any honour, but honour for those honours
	That are without him, as places, riches, and favour,
	Prizes of accident as oft as merit:
	Which when they fall, as being slippery standers,
	The love that lean'd on them as slippery too,
	Do one pluck down another, and together
	Die in the fall. But 'tis not so with me:
	Fortune and I are friends: I do enjoy
	At ample point all that I did possess,
	Save these men's looks; who do, methinks, find out
	Something not worth in me such rich beholding
	As they have often given. Here is Ulysses:
	I'll interrupt his reading.
	How now, Ulysses!
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 3><54%>
	What are you reading?
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 3><54%>
	This is not strange, Ulysses!
	The beauty that is borne here in the face
	The bearer knows not, but commends itself
	To others' eyes: nor doth the eye itself—
	That most pure spirit of sense—behold itself,
	Not going from itself; but eye to eye oppos'd
	Salutes each other with each other's form;
	For speculation turns not to itself
	Till it hath travell'd and is mirror'd there
	Where it may see itself. This is not strange at all.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 3><55%>
	I do believe it; for they pass'd by me
	As misers do by beggars, neither gave to me
	Good word or look: what! are my deeds forgot?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 3><56%>
	Of this my privacy
	I have strong reasons.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 3><56%>
	Ha! known!
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	Shall Ajax fight with Hector?
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	I see my reputation is at stake;
	My fame is shrewdly gor'd.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	Go call Thersites hither, sweet Patroclus:
	I'll send the fool to Ajax and desire him
	T' invite the Trojan lords after the combat
	To see us here unarmed. I have a woman's longing,
	An appetite that I am sick withal,
	To see great Hector in his weeds of peace;
	To talk with him and to behold his visage,
	Even to my full of view. A labour sav'd!
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	What?
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	How so?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	How can that be?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	Thou must be my ambassador to him, Thersites.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	To him, Patroclus: tell him, I humbly desire the valiant Ajax to invite the most valorous Hector to come unarmed to my tent; and to procure safe-conduct for his person of the magnanimous and most illustrious, six-or-seven-times-honoured captain-general of the Grecian army, Agamemnon, et cætera. Do this.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	Why, but he is not in this tune, is he?
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	Come, thou shalt bear a letter to him straight.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	My mind is troubled, like a fountain stirr'd;
	And I myself see not the bottom of it.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	'Tis but early days.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	I'll take that winter from your lips, fair lady:
	Achilles bids you welcome.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	'Tis done like Hector; but securely done,
	A little proudly, and great deal misprising
	The knight oppos'd.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	If not Achilles, nothing.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	A maiden battle, then? O! I perceive you.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 5><77%>
	I shall forestall thee, Lord Ulysses, thou!
	Now, Hector, I have fed mine eyes on thee;
	I have with exact view perus'd thee, Hector,
	And quoted joint by joint.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 5><77%>
	I am Achilles.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 5><77%>
	Behold thy fill.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 5><77%>
	Thou art too brief: I will the second time,
	As I would buy thee, view thee limb by limb.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 5><77%>
	Tell me, you heavens, in which part of his body
	Shall I destroy him? whether there, or there, or there?
	That I may give the local wound a name,
	And make distinct the very breach whereout
	Hector's great spirit flew. Answer me, heavens!
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 5><78%>
	I tell thee, yea.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 5><78%>
	Dost thou entreat me, Hector?
	To-morrow do I meet thee, fell as death;
	To-night all friends.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 5><SCENE 1><79%>
	I'll heat his blood with Greekish wine to-night,
	Which with my scimitar I'll cool to-morrow.
	Patroclus, let us feast him to the height.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 5><SCENE 1><79%>
	How now, thou core of envy!
	Thou crusty batch of nature, what's the news?
<SPEECH 62><ACT 5><SCENE 1><79%>
	From whence, fragment?
<SPEECH 63><ACT 5><SCENE 1><80%>
	My sweet Patroclus, I am thwarted quite
	From my great purpose in to-morrow's battle.
	Here is a letter from Queen Hecuba,
	A token from her daughter, my fair love,
	Both taxing me and gaging me to keep
	An oath that I have sworn. I will not break it:
	Fall Greeks; fail fame; honour or go or stay;
	My major vow lies here, this I'll obey.
	Come, come, Thersites, help to trim my tent;
	This night in banqueting must all be spent.
	Away, Patroclus!
<SPEECH 64><ACT 5><SCENE 1><81%>
	Welcome, brave Hector; welcome, princes all.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	Good-night and welcome both at once, to those
	That go or tarry.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	Old Nestor tarries; and you too, Diomed,
	Keep Hector company an hour or two.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	Come, come, enter my tent.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 5><SCENE 5><95%>
	Where is this Hector?
	Come, come, thou boy-queller, show thy face;
	Know what it is to meet Achilles angry:
	Hector! where's Hector? I will none but Hector.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 5><SCENE 6><95%>
	Now I do see thee. Ha! have at thee, Hector!
<SPEECH 70><ACT 5><SCENE 6><95%>
	I do disdain thy courtesy, proud Trojan.
	Be happy that my arms are out of use:
	My rest and negligence befriend thee now,
	But thou anon shalt hear of me again;
	Till when, go seek thy fortune.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 5><SCENE 7><96%>
	Come here about me, you my Myrmidons;
	Mark what I say. Attend me where I wheel:
	Strike not a stroke, but keep yourselves in breath:
	And when I have the bloody Hector found,
	Empale him with your weapons round about;
	In fellest manner execute your aims.
	Follow me, sirs, and my proceedings eye:
	It is decreed, Hector the great must die.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 5><SCENE 8><97%>
	Look, Hector, how the sun begins to set;
	How ugly night comes breathing at his heels:
	Even with the vail and darking of the sun,
	To close the day up, Hector's life is done.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 5><SCENE 8><97%>
	Strike, fellows, strike! this is the man I seek.
	So, Ilion, fall thou next! now, Troy, sink down!
	Here lies thy heart, thy sinews, and thy bone.
	On! Myrmidons, and cry you all amain,
	'Achilles hath the mighty Hector slain.'—
	Hark! a retreat upon our Grecian part.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 5><SCENE 8><98%>
	The dragon wing of night o'erspreads the earth,
	And, stickler-like, the armies separates.
	My half-supp'd sword, that frankly would have fed,
	Pleas'd with this dainty bait, thus goes to bed.—
	Come, tie his body to my horse's tail;
	Along the field I will the Trojan trail.
