<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	Call here my varlet, I'll unarm again:
	Why should I war without the walls of Troy,
	That find such cruel battle here within?
	Each Trojan that is master of his heart,
	Let him to field; Troilus, alas! has none.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	The Greeks are strong, and skilful to their strength.
	Fierce to their skill, and to their fierceness valiant;
	But I am weaker than a woman's tear,
	Tamer than sleep, fonder than ignorance,
	Less valiant than the virgin in the night,
	And skilless as unpractis'd infancy.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Have I not tarried?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Have I not tarried?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Still have I tarried.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Patience herself, what goddess e'er she be,
	Doth lesser blench at sufferance than I do.
	At Priam's royal table do I sit;
	And when fair Cressid comes into my thoughts,—
	So, traitor! 'when she comes'!—When is she thence?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	I was about to tell thee: when my heart,
	As wedged with a sigh, would rive in twain,
	Lest Hector or my father should perceive me,
	I have—as when the sun doth light a storm—
	Buried this sigh in wrinkle of a smile;
	But sorrow, that is couch'd in seeming gladness,
	Is like that mirth fate turns to sudden sadness.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	O Pandarus! I tell thee, Pandarus,—
	When I do tell thee, there my hopes lie drown'd,
	Reply not in how many fathoms deep
	They lie indrench'd. I tell thee I am mad
	In Cressid's love: thou answer'st, she is fair;
	Pour'st in the open ulcer of my heart
	Her eyes, her hair, her cheek, her gait, her voice;
	Handlest in thy discourse, O! that her hand,
	In whose comparison all whites are ink,
	Writing their own reproach; to whose soft seizure
	The cygnet's down is harsh, and spirit of sense
	Hard as the palm of ploughman: this thou tell'st me,
	As true thou tell'st me, when I say I love her;
	But, saying thus, instead of oil and balm,
	Thou lay'st in every gash that love hath given me
	The knife that made it.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	Thou dost not speak so much.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	Good Pandarus, how now, Pandarus!
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	What! art thou angry, Pandarus? what! with me?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	Say I she is not fair?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	Pandarus,—
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	Sweet Pandarus,—
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Peace, you ungracious clamours! peace, rude sounds!
	Fools on both sides! Helen must needs bo fair,
	When with your blood you daily paint her thus.
	I cannot fight upon this argument;
	It is too starv'd a subject for my sword.
	But Pandarus,—O gods! how do you plague me.
	I cannot come to Cressid but by Pandar;
	And he's as tetchy to be woo'd to woo
	As she is stubborn-chaste against all suit.
	Tell me, Apollo, for thy Daphne's love,
	What Cressid is, what Pandar, and what we?
	Her bed is India; there she lies, a pearl:
	Between our Ilium and where she resides
	Let it be call'd the wild and wandering flood;
	Ourself the merchant, and this sailing Pandar
	Our doubtful hope, our convoy and our bark.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Because not there: this woman's answer sorts,
	For womanish it is to be from thence.
	What news, Æneas, from the field to-day?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	By whom, Æneas?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Let Paris bleed: 'tis but a scar to scorn;
	Paris is gor'd with Menelaus' horn.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Better at home, if 'would I might' were 'may.'
	But to the sport abroad: are you bound thither?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Come, go we then together.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	Fie, fie! my brother,
	Weigh you the worth and honour of a king
	So great as our dread father in a scale
	Of common ounces? will you with counters sum
	The past proportion of his infinite?
	And buckle in a waist most fathomless
	With spans and inches so diminutive
	As fears and reasons? fie, for godly shame!
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	You are for dreams and slumbers, brother priest;
	You fur your gloves with reason. Here are your reasons:
	You know an enemy intends you harm;
	You know a sword employ'd is perilous,
	And reason flies the object of all harm:
	Who marvels then, when Helenus beholds
	A Grecian and his sword, if he do set
	The very wings of reason to his heels,
	And fly like chidden Mercury from Jove,
	Or like a star disorb'd? Nay, if we talk of reason,
	Let's shut our gates and sleep: manhood and honour
	Should have hare-hearts, would they but fat their thoughts
	With this cramm'd reason: reason and respect
	Make livers pale, and lustihood deject.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 2><28%>
	What is aught but as 'tis valu'd?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	I take to-day a wife, and my election
	Is led on in the conduct of my will;
	My will enkindled by mine eyes and ears,
	Two traded pilots 'twixt the dangerous shores
	Of will and judgment. How may I avoid,
	Although my will distaste what it elected,
	The wife I chose? there can be no evasion
	To blench from this and to stand firm by honour.
	We turn not back the silks upon the merchant
	When we have soil'd them, nor the remainder viands
	We do not throw in unrespective sink
	Because we now are full. It was thought meet
	Paris should do some vengeance on the Greeks:
	Your breath of full consent bellied his sails;
	The seas and winds—old wranglers—took a truce
	And did him service: he touch'd the ports desir'd,
	And for an old aunt whom the Greeks held captive
	He brought a Grecian queen, whose youth and freshness
	Wrinkles Apollo's, and makes stale the morning.
	Why keep we her? the Grecians keep our aunt:
	Is she worth keeping? why, she is a pearl,
	Whose price hath launch'd above a thousand ships,
	And turn'd crown'd kings to merchants.
	If you'll avouch 'twas wisdom Paris went,—
	As you must needs, for you all cried 'Go, go,'—
	If you'll confess he brought home noble prize,—
	As you must needs, for you all clapp'd your hands,
	And cry'd 'Inestimable!'—why do you now
	The issue of your proper wisdoms rate,
	And do a deed that Fortune never did,
	Beggar the estimation which you priz'd
	Richer than sea and land? O! theft most base,
	That we have stol'n what we do fear to keep!
	But thieves unworthy of a thing so stol'n,
	That in their country did them that disgrace
	We fear to warrant in our native place.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	'Tis our mad sister, I do know her voice
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 2><30%>
	Why, brother Hector,
	We may not think the justness of each act
	Such and no other than event doth form it,
	Nor once deject the courage of our minds,
	Because Cassandra's mad: her brain-sick raptures
	Cannot distaste the goodness of a quarrel
	Which hath our several honours all engag'd
	To make it gracious. For my private part,
	I am no more touch'd than all Priam's sons;
	And Jove forbid there should be done amongst us
	Such things as might offend the weakest spleen
	To fight for and maintain.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	Why, there you touch'd the life of our design:
	Were it not glory that we more affected
	Than the performance of our heaving spleens,
	I would not wish a drop of Trojan blood
	Spent more in her defence. But, worthy Hector,
	She is a theme of honour and renown,
	A spur to valiant and magnanimous deeds,
	Whose present courage may beat down our foes,
	And fame in time to come canonize us;
	For, I presume, brave Hector would not lose
	So rich advantage of a promis'd glory
	As smiles upon the forehead of this action
	For the wide world's revenue.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 2><45%>
	Sirrah, walk off.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 2><45%>
	No, Pandarus: I stalk about her door,
	Like a strange soul upon the Stygian banks
	Staying for waftage. O! be thou my Charon,
	And give me swift transportance to those fields
	Where I may wallow in the lily-beds
	Propos'd for the deserver! O gentle Pandarus!
	From Cupid's shoulder pluck his painted wings,
	And fly with me to Cressid.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 2><45%>
	I am giddy, expectation whirls me round.
	The imaginary relish is so sweet
	That it enchants my sense. What will it be
	When that the watery palate tastes indeed
	Love's thrice-repured nectar? death, I fear me,
	Swounding destruction, or some joy too fine,
	Too subtle-potent, tun'd too sharp in sweetness
	For the capacity of my ruder powers:
	I fear it much; and I do fear besides
	That I shall lose distinction in my joys;
	As doth a battle, when they charge on heaps
	The enemy flying.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 2><46%>
	Even such a passion doth embrace my bosom;
	My heart beats thicker than a fev'rous pulse;
	And all my powers do their bestowing lose,
	Like vassalage at unawares encountering
	The eye of majesty.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 2><46%>
	You have bereft me of all words, lady.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	O Cressida! how often have I wished me thus!
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	What should they grant? what makes this pretty abruption? What too curious dreg espies my sweet lady in the fountain of our love?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	Fears make devils of cherubins; they never see truly.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	O! let my lady apprehend no fear: in all Cupid's pageant there is presented no monster.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	Nothing but our undertakings; when we vow to weep seas, live in fire, eat rocks, tame tigers; thinking it harder for our mistress to devise imposition enough than for us to undergo any difficulty imposed. This is the monstruosity in love, lady, that the will is infinite, and the execution confined; that the desire is boundless, and the act a slave to limit.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 2><47%>
	Are there such? such are not we. Praise us as we are tasted, allow us as we prove; our head shall go bare, till merit crown it. No perfection in reversion shall have a praise in present: we will not name desert before his birth, and, being born, his addition shall be humble. Few words to fair faith: Troilus shall be such to Cressid, as what envy can say worst shall be a mock for his truth; and what truth can speak truest not truer than Troilus.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	You know now your hostages; your uncle's word, and my firm faith.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 2><48%>
	Why was my Cressid then so hard to win?
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	And shall, albeit sweet music issues thence.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	Your leave, sweet Cressid?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	What offends you, lady?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	You cannot shun yourself.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	Well know they what they speak that speak so wisely.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	O! that I thought it could be in a woman—
	As if it can I will presume in you—
	To feed for aye her lamp and flames of love;
	To keep her constancy in plight and youth,
	Outliving beauty's outward, with a mind
	That doth renew swifter than blood decays:
	Or that persuasion could but thus convince me,
	That my integrity and truth to you
	Might be affronted with the match and weight
	Of such a winnow'd purity in love;
	How were I then uplifted! but, alas!
	I am as true as truth's simplicity,
	And simpler than the infancy of truth.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	O virtuous fight!
	When right with right wars who shall be most right.
	True swains in love shall in the world to come
	Approve their truths by Troilus: when their rimes,
	Full of protest, of oath, and big compare,
	Want similes, truth tir'd with iteration,
	As true as steel, as plantage to the moon,
	As sun to day, as turtle to her mate,
	As iron to adamant, as earth to the centre,
	Yet, after all comparisons of truth,
	As truth's authentic author to be cited,
	'As true as Troilus' shall crown up the verse
	And sanctify the numbers.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	Amen.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 2><62%>
	Dear, trouble not yourself: the morn is cold.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 2><62%>
	Trouble him not;
	To bed, to bed: sleep kill those pretty eyes,
	And give as soft attachment to thy senses
	As infants' empty of all thought!
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 2><62%>
	I prithee now, to bed.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 2><62%>
	O Cressida! but that the busy day,
	Wak'd by the lark, hath rous'd the ribald crows,
	And dreaming night will hide our joys no longer,
	I would not from thee.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 2><62%>
	Beshrew the witch! with venomous wights she stays
	As tediously as hell, but flies the grasps of love
	With wings more momentary-swift than thought.
	You will catch cold, and curse me.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 2><63%>
	It is your uncle.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 2><63%>
	Ha, ha!
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	How now! what's the matter?
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	Is it so concluded?
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	How my achievements mock me!
	I will go meet them: and, my Lord Æneas,
	We met by chance; you did not find me here.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 3><65%>
	Walk into her house;
	I'll bring her to the Grecian presently:
	And to his hand when I deliver her,
	Think it an altar, and thy brother Troilus
	A priest, there offering to it his own heart.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 4><SCENE 4><66%>
	Cressid, I love thee in so strain'd a purity,
	That the bless'd gods, as angry with my fancy,
	More bright in zeal than the devotion which
	Cold lips blow to their deities, take thee from me.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 4><SCENE 4><67%>
	A hateful truth.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 4><SCENE 4><67%>
	From Troy and Troilus.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 4><SCENE 4><67%>
	And suddenly; where injury of chance
	Puts back leave-taking, justles roughly by
	All time of pause, rudely beguiles our lips
	Of all rejoindure, forcibly prevents
	Our lock'd embrasures, strangles our dear vows
	Even in the birth of our own labouring breath.
	We two, that with so many thousand sighs
	Did buy each other, must poorly sell ourselves
	With the rude brevity and discharge of one.
	Injurious time now with a robber's haste
	Crams his rich thievery up, he knows not how:
	As many farewells as be stars in heaven,
	With distinct breath and consign'd kisses to them,
	He fumbles up into a loose adieu,
	And scants us with a single famish'd kiss,
	Distasted with the salt of broken tears.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 4><SCENE 4><67%>
	Hark! you are call'd: some say the Genius so
	Cries 'Come!' to him that instantly must die.
	Bid them have patience; she shall come anon.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 4><SCENE 4><67%>
	No remedy.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 4><SCENE 4><67%>
	Hear me, my love. Be thou but true of heart,—
<SPEECH 67><ACT 4><SCENE 4><67%>
	Nay, we must use expostulation kindly,
	For it is parting from us:
	I speak not 'be thou true,' as fearing thee,
	For I will throw my glove to Death himself,
	That there's no maculation in thy heart;
	But, 'be thou true,' say I, to fashion in
	My sequent protestation; be thou true,
	And I will see thee.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	And I'll grow friend with danger. Wear this sleeve.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	I will corrupt the Grecian sentinels,
	To give thee nightly visitation.
	But yet, be true.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	Hear why I speak it, love:
	The Grecian youths are full of quality;
	They're loving, well compos'd, with gifts of nature,
	Flowing and swelling o'er with arts and exercise:
	How novelty may move, and parts with person,
	Alas! a kind of godly jealousy,—
	Which, I beseech you, call a virtuous sin,—
	Makes me afear'd.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	Die I a villain, then!
	In this I do not call your faith in question
	So mainly as my merit: I cannot sing,
	Nor heel the high lavolt, nor sweeten talk,
	Nor play at subtle games; fair virtues all,
	To which the Grecians are most prompt and pregnant:
	But I can tell that in each grace of these
	There lurks a still and dumb-discoursive devil
	That tempts most cunningly. But be not tempted.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	No.
	But something may be done that we will not:
	And sometimes we are devils to ourselves
	When we will tempt the frailty of our powers,
	Presuming on their changeful potency.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 4><SCENE 4><68%>
	Come, kiss; and let us part.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 4><SCENE 4><69%>
	Good brother, come you hither;
	And bring Æneas and the Grecian with you.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 4><SCENE 4><69%>
	Who, I? alas, it is my vice, my fault:
	While others fish with craft for great opinion,
	I with great truth catch mere simplicity;
	Whilst some with cunning gild their copper crowns,
	With truth and plainness I do wear mine bare.
	Fear not my truth; the moral of my wit
	Is plain, and true; there's all the reach of it.
	Welcome, Sir Diomed! Here is the lady
	Which for Antenor we deliver you:
	At the port, lord, I'll give her to thy hand,
	And by the way possess thee what she is.
	Entreat her fair; and, by my soul, fair Greek,
	If e'er thou stand at mercy of my sword,
	Name Cressid, and thy life shall be as safe
	As Priam is in Ilion.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 4><SCENE 4><69%>
	Grecian, thou dost not use me courteously,
	To shame the zeal of my petition to thee
	In praising her: I tell thee, lord of Greece,
	She is as far high-soaring o'er thy praises
	As thou unworthy to be call'd her servant.
	I charge thee use her well, even for my charge;
	For, by the dreadful Pluto, if thou dost not,
	Though the great bulk Achilles be thy guard,
	I'll cut thy throat.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 4><SCENE 4><70%>
	Come, to the port. I'll tell thee, Diomed,
	This brave shall oft make thee to hide thy head.
	Lady, give me your hand, and, as you walk,
	To our own selves bend we our needful talk.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 4><SCENE 5><74%>
	Hector, thou sleep'st; awake thee!
<SPEECH 79><ACT 4><SCENE 5><79%>
	My Lord Ulysses, tell me, I beseech you,
	In what place of the field doth Calchas keep?
<SPEECH 80><ACT 4><SCENE 5><79%>
	Shall I, sweet lord, be bound to thee so much,
	After we part from Agamemnon's tent,
	To bring me thither?
<SPEECH 81><ACT 4><SCENE 5><79%>
	O, sir! to such as boasting show their scars
	A mock is due. Will you walk on, my lord?
	She was belov'd, she lov'd; she is, and doth:
	But still sweet love is food for fortune's tooth.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	Sweet sir, you honour me.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	Cressid comes forth to him.
<SPEECH 84><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	Yea, so familiar!
<SPEECH 85><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	What should she remember?
<SPEECH 86><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	Hold, patience!
<SPEECH 87><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	Thy better must.
<SPEECH 88><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	O plague and madness!
<SPEECH 89><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	Behold, I pray you!
<SPEECH 90><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	I pray thee, stay.
<SPEECH 91><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	I pray you, stay. By hell, and all hell's torments,
	I will not speak a word!
<SPEECH 92><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	Doth that grieve thee?
	O wither'd truth!
<SPEECH 93><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	By Jove,
	I will be patient.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	She strokes his cheek!
<SPEECH 95><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	Nay, stay; by Jove, I will not speak a word:
	There is between my will and all offences
	A guard of patience: stay a little while.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	Fear me not, sweet lord;
	I will not be myself, nor have cognition
	Of what I feel: I am all patience.
<SPEECH 97><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	O beauty! where is thy faith?
<SPEECH 98><ACT 5><SCENE 2><84%>
	I will be patient; outwardly I will.
<SPEECH 99><ACT 5><SCENE 2><85%>
	I did swear patience.
<SPEECH 100><ACT 5><SCENE 2><85%>
	Wert thou the devil, and wor'st it on thy horn,
	It should be challeng'd.
<SPEECH 101><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	It is.
<SPEECH 102><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	To make a recordation to my soul
	Of every syllable that here was spoke.
	But if I tell how these two did co-act,
	Shall I not lie in publishing a truth?
	Sith yet there is a credence in my heart,
	An esperance so obstinately strong,
	That doth invert the attest of eyes and ears,
	As if those organs had deceptions functions,
	Created only to calumniate.
	Was Cressid here?
<SPEECH 103><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	She was not, sure.
<SPEECH 104><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	Why, my negation hath no taste of madness.
<SPEECH 105><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	Let it not be believ'd for womanhood!
	Think we had mothers; do not give advantage
	To stubborn critics, apt, without a theme,
	For depravation, to square the general sex
	By Cressid's rule: rather think this not Cressid.
<SPEECH 106><ACT 5><SCENE 2><87%>
	Nothing at all, unless that this were she.
<SPEECH 107><ACT 5><SCENE 2><87%>
	This she? no, this is Diomed's Cressida.
	If beauty have a soul, this is not she;
	If souls guide vows, if vows be sanctimony,
	If sanctimony be the gods' delight,
	If there be rule in unity itself,
	This is not she. O madness of discourse,
	That cause sets up with and against itself;
	Bi-fold authority! where reason can revolt
	Without perdition, and loss assume all reason
	Without revolt: this is, and is not, Cressid.
	Within my soul there doth conduce a fight
	Of this strange nature that a thing inseparate
	Divides more wider than the sky and earth;
	And yet the spacious breadth of this division
	Admits no orifice for a point as subtle
	As Ariachne's broken woof to enter.
	Instance, O instance! strong as Pluto's gates;
	Cressid is mine, tied with the bonds of heaven:
	Instance, O instance! strong as heaven itself;
	The bonds of heaven are slipp'd, dissolv'd, and loos'd;
	And with another knot, five-finger-tied,
	The fractions of her faith, orts of her love,
	The fragments, scraps, the bits, and greasy reliques
	Of her o'er-eaten faith, are bound to Diomed.
<SPEECH 108><ACT 5><SCENE 2><87%>
	Ay, Greek; and that shall be divulged well
	In characters as red as Mars his heart
	Inflam'd with Venus: never did young man fancy
	With so eternal and so fix'd a soul.
	Hark, Greek: as much as I do Cressid love,
	So much by weight hate I her Diomed;
	That sleeve is mine that he'll bear on his helm;
	Were it a casque compos'd by Vulcan's skill,
	My sword should bite it. Not the dreadful spout
	Which shipmen do the hurricano call,
	Constring'd in mass by the almighty sun,
	Shall dizzy with more clamour Neptune's ear
	In his descent than shall my prompted sword
	Falling on Diomed.
<SPEECH 109><ACT 5><SCENE 2><88%>
	O Cressid! O false Cressid! false, false, false!
	Let all untruths stand by thy stained name,
	And they'll seem glorious.
<SPEECH 110><ACT 5><SCENE 2><88%>
	Have with you, prince. My courteous lord, adieu.
	Farewell, revolted fair! and Diomed,
	Stand fast, and wear a castle on thy head!
<SPEECH 111><ACT 5><SCENE 2><88%>
	Accept distracted thanks.
<SPEECH 112><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	Brother, you have a vice of mercy in you,
	Which better fits a lion than a man.
<SPEECH 113><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	When many times the captive Grecian falls,
	Even in the fan and wind of your fair sword,
	You bid them rise, and live.
<SPEECH 114><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	Fool's play, by heaven, Hector.
<SPEECH 115><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	For the love of all the gods,
	Let's leave the hermit pity with our mothers,
	And when we have our armours buckled on,
	The venom'd vengeance ride upon our swords,
	Spur them to ruthful work, rein them from ruth.
<SPEECH 116><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	Hector, then 'tis wars.
<SPEECH 117><ACT 5><SCENE 3><90%>
	Who should withhold me?
	Not fate, obedience, nor the hand of Mars
	Beckoning with fiery truncheon my retire;
	Not Priamus and Hecuba on knees,
	Their eyes o'ergalled with recourse of tears;
	Nor you, my brother, with your true sword drawn,
	Oppos'd to hinder me, should stop my way,
	But by my ruin.
<SPEECH 118><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	This foolish, dreaming, superstitious girl
	Makes all these bodements.
<SPEECH 119><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	Away! Away!
<SPEECH 120><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	They are at it, hark! Proud Diomed, believe,
	I come to lose my arm, or win my sleeve.
<SPEECH 121><ACT 5><SCENE 3><91%>
	What now?
<SPEECH 122><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	Let me read.
<SPEECH 123><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	Words, words, mere words, no matter from the heart;
	The effect doth operate another way.
	Go, wind to wind, there turn and change together.
	My love with words and errors still she feeds,
	But edifies another with her deeds.
<SPEECH 124><ACT 5><SCENE 4><93%>
	Fly not; for shouldst thou take the river Styx,
	I would swim after.
<SPEECH 125><ACT 5><SCENE 6><95%>
	O traitor Diomed! Turn thy false face, thou traitor!
	And pay thy life thou ow'st me for my horse!
<SPEECH 126><ACT 5><SCENE 6><95%>
	Come, both you cogging Greeks; have at you both!
<SPEECH 127><ACT 5><SCENE 6><96%>
	Ajax hath ta'en Æneas: shall it be?
	No, by the flame of yonder glorious heaven,
	He shall not carry him: I'll be ta'en too,
	Or bring him off. Fate, hear me what I say!
	I reck not though I end my life to-day.
<SPEECH 128><ACT 5><SCENE X.— ><98%>
	Hector is slain.
<SPEECH 129><ACT 5><SCENE X.— ><98%>
	He's dead; and at the murderer's horse's tail,
	In beastly sort, dragg'd through the shameful field.
	Frown on, you heavens, effect your rage with speed!
	Sit, gods, upon your thrones, and smile at Troy!
	I say, at once let your brief plagues be mercy,
	And linger not our sure destructions on!
<SPEECH 130><ACT 5><SCENE X.— ><99%>
	You understand me not that tell me so.
	I do not speak of flight, of fear, of death;
	But dare all imminence that gods and men
	Address their dangers in. Hector is gone:
	Who shall tell Priam so, or Hecuba?
	Let him that will a screech-owl aye be call'd
	Go in to Troy, and say there Hector's dead:
	There is a word will Priam turn to stone,
	Make wells and Niobes of the maids and wives,
	Cold statues of the youth; and, in a word,
	Scare Troy out of itself. But march away:
	Hector is dead; there is no more to say.
	Stay yet. You vile abominable tents,
	Thus proudly pight upon our Phrygian plains,
	Let Titan rise as early as he dare,
	I'll through and through you! And, thou great-siz'd coward,
	No space of earth shall sunder our two hates:
	I'll haunt thee like a wicked conscience still,
	That mouldeth goblins swift as frenzy's thoughts.
	Strike a free march to Troy! with comfort go:
	Hope of revenge shall hide our inward woe.
<SPEECH 131><ACT 5><SCENE X.— ><99%>
	Hence, broker lackey! ignomy and shame
	Pursue thy life, and live aye with thy name!
