<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	If the great gods be just, they shall assist
	The deeds of justest men.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Whiles we are suitors to their throne, decays
	The thing we sue for.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	I shall do well:
	The people love me, and the sea is mine;
	My powers are crescent, and my auguring hope
	Says it will come to the full. Mark Antony
	In Egypt sits at dinner, and will make
	No wars without doors; Cæsar gets money where
	He loses hearts; Lepidus flatters both,
	Of both is flatter'd; but he neither loves,
	Nor either cares for him.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Where have you this? 'tis false.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	He dreams; I know they are in Rome together,
	Looking for Antony. But all the charms of love,
	Salt Cleopatra, soften thy wan'd lip!
	Let witchcraft join with beauty, lust with both!
	Tie up the libertine in a field of feasts,
	Keep his brain fuming; Epicurean cooks
	Sharpen with cloyless sance his appetite,
	That sleep and feeding may prorogue his honour
	Even till a Lethe'd dulness!
	How now, Varrius!
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	I could have given less matter
	A better ear. Menas, I did not think
	This amorous surfeiter would have donn'd his helm
	For such a petty war; his soldiership
	Is twice the other twain. But let us rear
	The higher our opinion, that our stirring
	Can from the lap of Egypt's widow pluck
	The ne'er-lust-wearied Antony.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	I know not, Menas,
	How lesser enmities may give way to greater.
	Were 't not that we stand up against them all
	'Twere pregnant they should square between themselves,
	For they have entertained cause enough
	To draw their swords; but how the fear of us
	May cement their divisions and bind up
	The petty difference, we yet not know.
	Be it as our gods will have 't! It only stands
	Our lives upon, to use our strongest hands.
	Come, Menas.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 6><32%>
	Your hostages I have, so have you mine;
	And we shall talk before we fight.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 6><32%>
	To you all three,
	The senators alone of this great world,
	Chief factors for the gods, I do not know
	Wherefore my father should revengers want,
	Having a son and friends; since Julius Cæsar,
	Who at Philippi the good Brutus ghosted,
	There saw you labouring for him. What was 't
	That mov'd pale Cassius to conspire? and what
	Made the all-honour'd, honest Roman, Brutus,
	With the arm'd rest, courtiers of beauteous freedom,
	To drench the Capitol, but that they would
	Have one man but a man? And that is it
	Hath made me rig my navy, at whose burden
	The anger'd ocean foams, with which I meant
	To scourge the ingratitude that despiteful Rome
	Cast on my noble father.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 6><32%>
	At land, indeed,
	Thou dost o'er-count me of my father's house;
	But, since the cuckoo builds not for himself,
	Remain in 't as thou mayst.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 6><33%>
	You have made me offer
	Of Sicily, Sardinia; and I must
	Rid all the sea of pirates; then, to send
	Measures of wheat to Rome; this 'greed upon,
	To part with unhack'd edges, and bear back
	Our targets undinted.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 6><33%>
	Know, then,
	I came before you here a man prepar'd
	To take this offer; but Mark Antony
	Put me to some impatience. Though I lose
	The praise of it by telling, you must know,
	When Cæsar and your brother were at blows,
	Your mother came to Sicily and did find
	Her welcome friendly.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 6><33%>
	Let me have your hand:
	I did not think, sir, to have met you here.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 6><33%>
	Well, I know not
	What counts harsh Fortune casts upon my face,
	But in my bosom shall she never come
	To make my heart her vassal.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 6><33%>
	I hope so, Lepidus. Thus we are agreed.
	I crave our composition may be written
	And seal'd between us.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	We'll feast each other ere we part; and let's
	Draw lots who shall begin.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	No, Antony, take the lot:
	But, first or last, your fine Egyptian cookery
	Shall have the fame. I have heard that Julius Cæsar
	Grew fat with feasting there.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	I have fair meanings, sir.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	Then, so much have I heard;
	And I have heard Apollodorus carried—
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	What, I pray you?
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	I know thee now; how far'st thou, soldier?
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	Let me shake thy hand;
	I never hated thee. I have seen thee fight,
	When I have envied thy behaviour.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	Enjoy thy plainness,
	It nothing ill becomes thee.
	Aboard my galley I invite you all:
	Will you lead, lords?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	Come.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 7><37%>
	Sit,—and some wine! A health to Lepidus!
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 7><37%>
	Say in mine ear; what is't?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 7><37%>
	Forbear me till anon.
	This wine for Lepidus!
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 7><37%>
	Go hang, sir, hang! Tell me of that? away!
	Do as I bid you. Where's this cup I call'd for?
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	I think thou'rt mad. The matter?
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	Thou hast serv'd me with much faith. What 's else to say?
	Be jolly, lords.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	What sayst thou?
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	How should that be?
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	Hast thou drunk well?
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	Show me which way.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	Ah! this thou shouldst have done,
	And not have spoke on 't. In me 'tis villany;
	In thee 't had been good service. Thou must know
	'Tis not my profit that does lead mine honour;
	Mine honour it. Repent that e'er thy tongue
	Hath so betray'd thine act; being done unknown,
	I should have found it afterwards well done,
	But must condemn it now. Desist, and drink.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 7><39%>
	This health to Lepidus!
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 7><39%>
	Fill till the cup be hid.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 7><39%>
	This is not yet an Alexandrian feast.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 7><39%>
	Let 's ha 't, good soldier.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 7><40%>
	I'll try you on the shore.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 7><40%>
	O, Antony!
	You have my father s house,—But, what? we are friends.
	Come down into the boat.
