<SPEECH 1><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Noble Ventidius,
	Whilst yet with Parthian blood thy sword is warm,
	The fugitive Parthians follow; spur through Media,
	Mesopotamia, and the shelters whither
	The routed fly; so thy grand captain Antony
	Shall set thee on triumphant chariots and
	Put garlands on thy head.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Thou hast, Ventidius, that
	Without the which a soldier, and his sword,
	Grants scarce distinction. Thou wilt write to Antony?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Where is he now?
