<SPEECH 1><ACT 3><SCENE 7><52%>
	O noble emperor! do not fight by sea;
	Trust not to rotten planks: do you misdoubt
	This sword and these my wounds? Let the Egyptians
	And the Phœnicians go a-ducking; we
	Have used to conquer, standing on the earth,
	And fighting foot to foot.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 3><SCENE 7><53%>
	By Hercules, I think I am i' the right.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 3><SCENE 7><53%>
	You keep by land
	The legions and the horse whole, do you not?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 3><SCENE 7><53%>
	While he was yet in Rome
	His power went out in such distractions as
	Beguil'd all spies.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE 7><53%>
	They say, one Taurus.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 4><SCENE 4><69%>
	A thousand, sir,
	Early though 't be, have on their riveted trim,
	And at the port expect you.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	The gods make this a happy day to Antony!
<SPEECH 8><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	Hadst thou done so,
	The kings that have revolted, and the soldier
	That has this morning left thee, would have still
	Follow'd thy heels.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	Who!
	One ever near thee: call for Enobarbus,
	He shall not hear thee; or from Cæsar's camp
	Say, 'I am none of thine.'
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	Sir,
	He is with Cæsar.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	Most certain.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 6><71%>
	Enobarbus, Antony
	Hath after thee sent all thy treasure, with
	His bounty overplus: the messenger
	Came on my guard; and at thy tent is now
	Unloading of his mules.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 6><71%>
	Mock not, Enobarbus.
	I tell you true: best you saf'd the bringer
	Out of the host; I must attend mine office
	Or would have done 't myself. Your emperor
	Continues still a Jove.
