<SPEECH 1><ACT 3><SCENE X.— ><58%>
	Cæsar, I go.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 3><SCENE X.— ><58%>
	Cæsar, I shall.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><60%>
	Hear it apart.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><60%>
	So, haply, are they friends to Antony.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><60%>
	So.
	Thus then, thou most renown'd: Cæsar entreats,
	Not to consider in what case thou stand'st,
	Further than he is Cæsar.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><60%>
	He knows that you embrace not Antony
	As you did love, but as you fear'd him.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><60%>
	The scars upon your honour therefore he
	Does pity, as constrained blemishes,
	Not as deserv'd.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><61%>
	Shall I say to Cæsar
	What you require of him? for he partly begs
	To be desir'd to give. It much would please him,
	That of his fortunes you should make a staff
	To lean upon; but it would warm his spirits
	To hear from me you had left Antony,
	And put yourself under his shroud,
	The universal landlord.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><61%>
	My name is Thyreus.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><61%>
	'Tis your noblest course.
	Wisdom and fortune combating together,
	If that the former dare but what it can,
	No chance may shake it. Give me grace to lay
	My duty on your hand.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><61%>
	One that but performs
	The bidding of the fullest man, and worthiest
	To have command obey'd.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE XI.— ><62%>
	Mark Antony,—
