<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	My Lord Bassanio, since you have found Antonio,
	We too will leave you; but, at dinner-time,
	I pray you, have in mind where we must meet.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Well, we will leave you then till dinner-time.
	I must be one of these same dumb-wise men,
	For Gratiano never lets me speak.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 4><30%>
	Nay, we will slink away in supper-time,
	Disguise us at my lodging, and return
	All in an hour.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 4><30%>
	'Tis now but four o'clock: we have two hours
	To furnish us.
	Friend Launcelot, what's the news?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 4><30%>
	I know the hand: in faith, 'tis a fair hand;
	And whiter than the paper it writ on
	Is the fair hand that writ.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 4><30%>
	Whither goest thou?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 4><30%>
	Hold here, take this: tell gentle Jessica
	I will not fail her; speak it privately.
	Go, gentlemen,
	Will you prepare you for this masque to-night?
	I am provided of a torch-bearer.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 4><31%>
	Meet me and Gratiano
	At Gratiano's lodging some hour hence.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 4><31%>
	I must needs tell thee all. She hath directed
	How I shall take her from her father's house;
	What gold and jewels she is furnish'd with;
	What page's suit she hath in readiness.
	If e'er the Jew her father come to heaven,
	It will be for his gentle daughter's sake;
	And never dare misfortune cross her foot,
	Unless she do it under this excuse,
	That she is issue to a faithless Jew.
	Come, go with me: peruse this as thou goest.
	Fair Jessica shall be my torch-bearer.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 6><34%>
	Sweet friends, your patience for my long abode;
	Not I, but my affairs, have made you wait:
	When you shall please to play the thieves for wives,
	I'll watch as long for you then. Approach;
	Here dwells my father Jew. Ho! who's within?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 6><35%>
	Lorenzo, and thy love.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 6><35%>
	Heaven and thy thoughts are witness that thou art.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 6><35%>
	Descend, for you must be my torch-bearer.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 6><35%>
	So are you, sweet,
	Even in the lovely garnish of a boy.
	But come at once;
	For the close night doth play the runaway,
	And we are stay'd for at Bassanio's feast.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 6><36%>
	Beshrew me, but I love her heartily;
	For she is wise, if I can judge of her,
	And fair she is, if that mine eyes be true,
	And true she is, as she hath prov'd herself;
	And therefore, like herself, wise, fair, and true,
	Shall she be placed in my constant soul.
	What, art thou come? On, gentlemen; away!
	Our masquing mates by this time for us stay.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	I thank your honour. For my part, my lord,
	My purpose was not to have seen you here;
	But meeting with Salanio by the way,
	He did entreat me, past all saying nay,
	To come with him along.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	Madam, although I speak it in your presence,
	You have a noble and a true conceit
	Of god-like amity; which appears most strongly
	In bearing thus the absence of your lord.
	But if you knew to whom you show this honour,
	How true a gentleman you send relief,
	How dear a lover of my lord your husband,
	I know you would be prouder of the work
	Than customary bounty can enforce you.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 4><65%>
	Madam, with all my heart:
	I shall obey you in all fair commands.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 4><65%>
	Fair thoughts and happy hours attend on you!
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 5><68%>
	I shall grow jealous of you shortly, Launcelot, if you thus get my wife into corners.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 5><68%>
	I shall answer that better to the commonwealth than you can the getting up of the negro's belly: the Moor is with child by you, Launcelot.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 5><68%>
	How every fool can play upon the word! I think the best grace of wit will shortly turn into silence, and discourse grow commendable in none only but parrots. Go in, sirrah: bid them prepare for dinner.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 5><68%>
	Goodly Lord, what a wit-snapper are you! then bid them prepare dinner.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 5><69%>
	Will you cover, then, sir?
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 5><69%>
	Yet more quarrelling with occasion! Wilt thou show the whole wealth of thy wit in an instant? I pray thee, understand a plain man in his plain meaning: go to thy fellows; bid them cover the table, serve in the meat, and we will come in to dinner.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 5><69%>
	O dear discretion, how his words are suited!
	The fool hath planted in his memory
	An army of good words: and I do know
	A many fools, that stand in better place,
	Garnish'd like him, that for a tricksy word
	Defy the matter. How cheer'st thou, Jessica?
	And now, good sweet, say thy opinion;
	How dost thou like the Lord Bassanio's wife?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 5><70%>
	Even such a husband
	Hast thou of me as she is for a wife.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 5><70%>
	I will anon; first, let us go to dinner.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 5><70%>
	No, pray thee, let it serve for table-talk; Then howsoe'er thou speak'st, 'mong other things I shall digest it.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 5><SCENE 1><88%>
	The moon shines bright: in such a night as this,
	When the sweet wind did gently kiss the trees
	And they did make no noise, in such a night
	Troilus methinks mounted the Troyan walls,
	And sigh'd his soul toward the Grecian tents,
	Where Cressid lay that night.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	In such a night
	Stood Dido with a willow in her hand
	Upon the wild sea-banks, and waft her love
	To come again to Carthage.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	In such a night
	Did Jessica steal from the wealthy Jew,
	And with an unthrift love did run from Venice,
	As far as Belmont.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	In such a night
	Did pretty Jessica, like a little shrew,
	Slander her love, and he forgave it her.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	Who comes so fast in silence of the night?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 5><SCENE 1><89%>
	A friend! what friend? your name, I pray you, friend.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 5><SCENE 1><90%>
	Who comes with her?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 5><SCENE 1><90%>
	He is not, nor we have not heard from him.
	But go we in, I pray thee, Jessica,
	And ceremoniously let us prepare
	Some welcome for the mistress of the house.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 5><SCENE 1><90%>
	Who calls?
<SPEECH 39><ACT 5><SCENE 1><90%>
	Leave hollaing, man; here.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 5><SCENE 1><90%>
	Here.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 5><SCENE 1><90%>
	Sweet soul, let's in, and there expect their coming.
	And yet no matter; why should we go in?
	My friend Stephano, signify, I pray you,
	Within the house, your mistress is at hand;
	And bring your music forth into the air.
	How sweet the moonlight sleeps upon this bank!
	Here will we sit, and let the sounds of music
	Creep in our ears: soft stillness and the night
	Become the touches of sweet harmony.
	Sit, Jessica: look, how the floor of heaven
	Is thick inlaid with patines of bright gold:
	There's not the smallest orb which thou behold'st
	But in his motion like an angel sings,
	Still quiring to the young-eyed cherubins;
	Such harmony is in immortal souls;
	But, whilst this muddy vesture of decay
	Doth grossly close it in, we cannot hear it.
	Come, ho! and wake Diana with a hymn:
	With sweetest touches pierce your mistress' ear,
	And draw her home with music.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 5><SCENE 1><91%>
	The reason is, your spirits are attentive:
	For do but note a wild and wanton herd,
	Or race of youthful and unhandled colts,
	Fetching mad bounds, bellowing and neighing loud,
	Which is the hot condition of their blood;
	If they but hear perchance a trumpet sound,
	Or any air of music touch their ears,
	You shall perceive them make a mutual stand,
	Their savage eyes turn'd to a modest gaze
	By the sweet power of music: therefore the poet
	Did feign that Orpheus drew trees, stones, and floods;
	Since nought so stockish, hard, and full of rage,
	But music for the time doth change his nature.
	The man that hath no music in himself,
	Nor is not mov'd with concord of sweet sounds,
	Is fit for treasons, stratagems, and spoils;
	The motions of his spirit are dull as night,
	And his affections dark as Erebus:
	Let no such man be trusted. Mark the music.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	That is the voice,
	Or I am much deceiv'd, of Portia.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	Dear lady, welcome home.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	Madam, they are not yet;
	But there is come a messenger before,
	To signify their coming.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	Your husband is at hand; I hear his trumpet:
	We are no tell-tales, madam; fear you not.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 5><SCENE 1><99%>
	Fair ladies, you drop manna in the way
	Of starved people.
