<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	By my troth, Nerissa, my little body is aweary of this great world.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Good sentences and well pronounced.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	If to do were as easy as to know what were good to do, chapels had been churches, and poor men's cottages princes' palaces. It is a good divine that follows his own instructions: I can easier teach twenty what were good to be done, than be one of the twenty to follow mine own teaching. The brain may devise laws for the blood, but a hot temper leaps o'er a cold decree: such a hare is madness the youth, to skip o'er the meshes of good counsel the cripple. But this reasoning is not in the fashion to choose me a husband. O me, the word 'choose!' I may neither choose whom I would nor refuse whom I dislike; so is the will of a living daughter curbed by the will of a dead father. Is it not hard, Nerissa, that I cannot choose one nor refuse none?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	I pray thee, over-name them, and as thou namest them, I will describe them; and, according to my description, level at my affection.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	Ay, that's a colt indeed, for he doth nothing but talk of his horse; and he makes it a great appropriation to his own good parts that he can shoe him himself. I am much afeard my lady his mother played false with a smith.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	He doth nothing but frown, as who should say, 'An you will not have me, choose.' He hears merry tales, and smiles not: I fear he will prove the weeping philosopher when he grows old, being so full of unmannerly sadness in his youth. I had rather be married to a death's-head with a bone in his mouth than to either of these. God defend me from these two!
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	God made him, and therefore let him pass for a man. In truth, I know it is a sin to be a mocker; but, he! why, he hath a horse better than the Neapolitan's, a better bad habit of frowning than the Count Palatine; he is every man in no man; if a throstle sing, he falls straight a-capering; he will fence with his own shadow: if I should marry him, I should marry twenty husbands. If he would despise me, I would forgive him, for if he love me to madness, I shall never requite him.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	You know I say nothing to him, for he understands not me, nor I him: he hath neither Latin, French, nor Italian; and you will come into the court and swear that I have a poor pennyworth in the English. He is a proper man's picture, but, alas! who can converse with a dumb-show? How oddly he is suited! I think he bought his doublet in Italy, his round hose in France, his bonnet in Germany, and his behaviour every where.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	That he hath a neighbourly charity in him, for he borrowed a box of the ear of the Englishman, and swore he would pay him again when he was able: I think the Frenchman became his surety and sealed under for another.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	Very vilely in the morning, when he is sober, and most vilely in the afternoon, when he is drunk: when he is best, he is a little worse than a man, and when he is worst, he is little better than a beast. An the worst fall that ever fell, I hope I shall make shift to go without him.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Therefore, for fear of the worst, I pray thee, set a deep glass of Rhenish wine on the contrary casket, for, if the devil be within and that temptation without, I know he will choose it. I will do anything, Nerissa, ere I will be married to a sponge.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	If I live to be as old as Sibylla, I will die as chaste as Diana, unless I be obtained by the manner of my father's will. I am glad this parcel of wooers are so reasonable, for there is not one among them but I dote on his very absence, and I pray God grant them a fair departure.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	Yes, yes: it was Bassanio; as I think, he was so called.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	I remember him well, and I remember him worthy of thy praise.
	How now! what news?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	If I could bid the fifth welcome with so good heart as I can bid the other four farewell, I should be glad of his approach: if he have the condition of a saint and the complexion of a devil, I had rather he should shrive me than wive me. Come, Nerissa. Sirrah, go before.
	Whiles we shut the gate upon one wooer, another knocks at the door.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	In terms of choice I am not solely led
	By nice direction of a maiden's eyes;
	Besides, the lottery of my destiny
	Bars me the right of voluntary choosing:
	But if my father had not scanted me
	And hedg'd me by his wit, to yield myself
	His wife who wins me by that means I told you,
	Yourself, renowned prince, then stood as fair
	As any comer I have look'd on yet
	For my affection.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><20%>
	You must take your chance;
	And either not attempt to choose at all,
	Or swear before you choose, if you choose wrong,
	Never to speak to lady afterward
	In way of marriage: therefore be advis'd.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><21%>
	First, forward to the temple: after dinner
	Your hazard shall be made.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 7><37%>
	Go, draw aside the curtains, and discover
	The several caskets to this noble prince.
	Now make your choice.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 7><37%>
	The one of them contains my picture, prince:
	If you choose that, then I am yours withal.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 7><39%>
	There, take it, prince; and if my form lie there,
	Then I am yours.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 7><39%>
	A gentle riddance. Draw the curtains: go.
	Let all of his complexion choose me so.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 1><42%>
	Behold, there stands the caskets, noble prince:
	If you choose that wherein I am contain'd,
	Straight shall our nuptial rites be solemniz'd;
	But if you fail, without more speech, my lord,
	You must be gone from hence immediately.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 1><42%>
	To these injunctions every one doth swear
	That comes to hazard for my worthless self.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 1><44%>
	Too long a pause for that which you find there.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 1><44%>
	To offend, and judge, are distinct offices,
	And of opposed natures.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 1><44%>
	Thus hath the candle sing'd the moth.
	O, these deliberate fools! when they do choose,
	They have the wisdom by their wit to lose.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 1><45%>
	Come, draw the curtain, Nerissa.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 1><45%>
	Here; what would my lord?
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 1><45%>
	No more, I pray thee: I am half afeard
	Thou wilt say anon he is some kin to thee,
	Thou spend'st such high-day wit in praising him.
	Come, come, Nerissa; for I long to see
	Quick Cupid's post that comes so mannerly.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	I pray you, tarry: pause a day or two
	Before you hazard; for, in choosing wrong.
	I lose your company: therefore, forbear awhile.
	There's something tells me, but it is not love,
	I would not lose you; and you know yourself,
	Hate counsels not in such a quality.
	But lest you should not understand me well,—
	And yet a maiden hath no tongue but thought,—
	I would detain you here some month or two
	Before you venture for me. I could teach you
	How to choose right, but then I am forsworn;
	So will I never be: so may you miss me;
	But if you do, you'll make me wish a sin,
	That I had been forsworn. Beshrew your eyes,
	They have o'erlook'd me and divided me:
	One half of me is yours, the other half yours,
	Mine own, I would say; but if mine, then yours,
	And so all yours. O! these naughty times
	Put bars between the owners and their rights;
	And so, though yours, not yours. Prove it so,
	Let fortune go to hell for it, not I.
	I speak too long; but 'tis to peise the time,
	To eke it and to draw it out in length,
	To stay you from election.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	Upon the rack, Bassanio! then confess
	What treason there is mingled with your love.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	Ay, but I fear you speak upon the rack,
	Where men enforced do speak anything.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	Well then, confess, and live.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	Away then! I am lock'd in one of them:
	If you do love me, you will find me out.
	Nerissa and the rest, stand all aloof.
	Let music sound while he doth make his choice;
	Then, if he lose, he makes a swan-like end,
	Fading in music: that the comparison
	May stand more proper, my eye shall be the stream
	And watery death-bed for him. He may win;
	And what is music then? then music is
	Even as the flourish when true subjects bow
	To a new-crowned monarch: such it is
	As are those dulcet sounds in break of day
	That creep into the dreaming bridegroom's ear,
	And summon him to marriage. Now he goes,
	With no less presence, but with much more love,
	Than young Alcides, when he did redeem
	The virgin tribute paid by howling Troy
	To the sea-monster: I stand for sacrifice;
	The rest aloof are the Dardanian wives,
	With bleared visages, come forth to view
	The issue of the exploit. Go, Hercules!
	Live thou, I live: with much, much more dismay
	I view the fight than thou that mak'st the fray.
	Tell me where is fancy bred,
	Or in the heart or in the head?
	How begot, how nourished?
	Reply, reply.
	It is engender'd in the eyes,
	With gazing fed; and fancy dies
	In the cradle where it lies
	Let us all ring fancy's knell;
	I'll begin it,—Ding, dong, bell.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 2><54%>
	</STAGE DIR> How all the other passions fleet to air,
	As doubtful thoughts, and rash-embrac'd despair,
	And shuddering fear, and green-ey'd jealousy.
	O love! be moderate; allay thy ecstasy;
	In measure rain thy joy; scant this excess;
	I feel too much thy blessing; make it less,
	For fear I surfeit!
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 2><55%>
	You see me, Lord Bassanio, where I stand,
	Such as I am: though for myself alone
	I would not be ambitious in my wish,
	To wish myself much better; yet, for you
	I would be trebled twenty times myself;
	A thousand times more fair, ten thousand times
	More rich;
	That only to stand high in your account,
	I might in virtues, beauties, livings, friends,
	Exceed account: but the full sum of me
	Is sum of nothing; which, to term in gross,
	Is an unlesson'd girl, unschool'd, unpractis'd;
	Happy in this, she is not yet so old
	But she may learn; happier than this,
	She is not bred so dull but she can learn;
	Happiest of all is that her gentle spirit
	Commits itself to yours to be directed,
	As from her lord, her governor, her king.
	Myself and what is mine to you and yours
	Is now converted: but now I was the lord
	Of this fair mansion, master of my servants,
	Queen o'er myself; and even now, but now,
	This house, these servants, and this same myself
	Are yours, my lord. I give them with this ring;
	Which when you part from, lose, or give away,
	Let it presage the ruin of your love,
	And be my vantage to exclaim on you.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Is this true, Nerissa?
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	So do I, my lord:
	They are entirely welcome.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 2><59%>
	There are some shrewd contents in yon same paper,
	That steal the colour from Bassanio's cheek:
	Some dear friend dead, else nothing in the world
	Could turn so much the constitution
	Of any constant man. What, worse and worse!
	With leave, Bassanio; I am half yourself,
	And I must freely have the half of anything
	That this same paper brings you.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 2><61%>
	Is it your dear friend that is thus in trouble?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 2><61%>
	What sum owes he the Jew?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 2><61%>
	What, no more?
	Pay him six thousand, and deface the bond;
	Double six thousand, and then treble that,
	Before a friend of this description
	Shall lose a hair thorough Bassanio's fault.
	First go with me to church and call me wife,
	And then away to Venice to your friend;
	For never shall you lie by Portia's side
	With an unquiet soul. You shall have gold
	To pay the petty debt twenty times over:
	When it is paid, bring your true friend along.
	My maid Nerissa and myself meantime,
	Will live as maids and widows. Come, away!
	For you shall hence upon your wedding-day.
	Bid your friends welcome, show a merry cheer;
	Since you are dear bought, I will love you dear.
	But let me hear the letter of your friend.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 2><62%>
	O love, dispatch all business, and be gone!
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	I never did repent for doing good,
	Nor shall not now: for in companions
	That do converse and waste the time together,
	Whose souls do bear an equal yoke of love,
	There must be needs a like proportion
	Of lineaments, of manners, and of spirit;
	Which makes me think that this Antonio,
	Being the bosom lover of my lord,
	Must needs be like my lord. If it be so,
	How little is the cost I have bestow'd
	In purchasing the semblance of my soul
	From out the state of hellish cruelty!
	This comes too near the praising of myself;
	Therefore, no more of it: hear other things.
	Lorenzo, I commit into your hands
	The husbandry and manage of my house
	Until my lord's return: for mine own part,
	I have toward heaven breath'd a secret vow
	To live in prayer and contemplation,
	Only attended by Nerissa here,
	Until her husband and my lord's return.
	There is a monastery two miles off,
	And there will we abide. I do desire you
	Not to deny this imposition,
	The which my love and some necessity
	Now lays upon you.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 4><65%>
	My people do already know my mind,
	And will acknowledge you and Jessica
	In place of Lord Bassanio and myself.
	So fare you well till we shall meet again.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 4><65%>
	I thank you for your wish, and am well pleas'd
	To wish it back on you: fare you well, Jessica.
	Now, Balthazar,
	As I have ever found thee honest-true,
	So let me find thee still. Take this same letter,
	And use thou all the endeavour of a man
	In speed to Padua: see thou render this
	Into my cousin's hand, Doctor Bellario;
	And, look, what notes and garments he doth give thee,
	Bring them, I pray thee, with imagin'd speed
	Unto the traject, to the common ferry
	Which trades to Venice. Waste no time in words,
	But get thee gone: I shall be there before thee.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 3><SCENE 4><65%>
	Come on, Nerissa: I have work in hand
	That you yet know not of: we'll see our husbands
	Before they think of us.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 3><SCENE 4><66%>
	They shall, Nerissa; but in such a habit
	That they shall think we are accomplished
	With that we lack. I'll hold thee any wager,
	When we are both accoutred like young men,
	I'll prove the prettier fellow of the two,
	And wear my dagger with the braver grace,
	And speak between the change of man and boy
	With a reed voice, and turn two mincing steps
	Into a manly stride, and speak of frays
	Like a fine bragging youth, and tell quaint lies,
	How honourable ladies sought my love,
	Which I denying, they fell sick and died:
	I could not do withal; then I'll repent,
	And wish, for all that, that I had not kill'd them:
	And twenty of these puny lies I'll tell,
	That men shall swear I have discontinu'd school
	Above a twelvemonth. I have within my mind
	A thousand raw tricks of these bragging Jacks,
	Which I will practise.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 3><SCENE 4><66%>
	Fie, what a question's that,
	If thou wert near a lewd interpreter!
	But come: I'll tell thee all my whole device
	When I am in my coach, which stays for us
	At the park gate; and therefore haste away,
	For we must measure twenty miles to-day.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 1><76%>
	I did, my lord.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 1><77%>
	I am informed throughly of the cause.
	Which is the merchant here, and which the Jew?
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 1><77%>
	Is your name Shylock?
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 1><77%>
	Of a strange nature is the suit you follow;
	Yet in such rule that the Venetian law
	Cannot impugn you as you do proceed.
	</STAGE DIR> You stand within his danger, do you not?
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 1><77%>
	Do you confess the bond?
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 1><77%>
	Then must the Jew be merciful.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 1><77%>
	The quality of mercy is not strain'd,
	It droppeth as the gentle rain from heaven
	Upon the place beneath: it is twice bless'd;
	It blesseth him that gives and him that takes:
	'Tis mightiest in the mightiest; it becomes
	The throned monarch better than his crown;
	His sceptre shows the force of temporal power,
	The attribute to awe and majesty,
	Wherein doth sit the dread and fear of kings;
	But mercy is above this sceptred sway,
	It is enthroned in the hearts of kings,
	It is an attribute to God himself,
	And earthly power doth then show likest God's
	When mercy seasons justice. Therefore, Jew,
	Though justice be thy plea, consider this,
	That in the course of justice none of us
	Should see salvation: we do pray for mercy,
	And that same prayer doth teach us all to render
	The deeds of mercy. I have spoke thus much
	To mitigate the justice of thy plea,
	Which if thou follow, this strict court of Venice
	Must needs give sentence 'gainst the merchant there.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 1><78%>
	Is he not able to discharge the money?
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 1><78%>
	It must not be. There is no power in Venice
	Can alter a decree established:
	'Twill be recorded for a precedent,
	And many an error by the same example
	Will rush into the state. It cannot be.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 4><SCENE 1><79%>
	I pray you, let me look upon the bond.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 4><SCENE 1><79%>
	Shylock, there's thrice thy money offer'd thee.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 4><SCENE 1><79%>
	Why, this bond is forfeit;
	And lawfully by this the Jew may claim
	A pound of flesh, to be by him cut off
	Nearest the merchant's heart. Be merciful:
	Take thrice thy money; bid me tear the bond.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 4><SCENE 1><79%>
	Why then, thus it is:
	You must prepare your bosom for his knife.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 4><SCENE 1><79%>
	For, the intent and purpose of the law
	Hath full relation to the penalty,
	Which here appeareth due upon the bond.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 4><SCENE 1><80%>
	Therefore lay bare your bosom.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 4><SCENE 1><80%>
	It is so. Are there balance here to weigh
	The flesh?
<SPEECH 67><ACT 4><SCENE 1><80%>
	Have by some surgeon, Shylock, on your charge,
	To stop his wounds, lest he do bleed to death.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 4><SCENE 1><80%>
	It is not so express'd; but what of that?
	'Twere good you do so much for charity.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 4><SCENE 1><80%>
	You, merchant, have you anything to say?
<SPEECH 70><ACT 4><SCENE 1><81%>
	Your wife would give you little thanks for that,
	If she were by to hear you make the offer.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 4><SCENE 1><81%>
	A pound of that same merchant's flesh is thine:
	The court awards it, and the law doth give it.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 4><SCENE 1><81%>
	And you must cut this flesh from off his breast:
	The law allows it, and the court awards it.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 4><SCENE 1><81%>
	Tarry a little: there is something else.
	This bond doth give thee here no jot of blood;
	The words expressly are 'a pound of flesh:'
	Then take thy bond, take thou thy pound of flesh;
	But, in the cutting it, if thou dost shed
	One drop of Christian blood, thy lands and goods
	Are, by the laws of Venice, confiscate
	Unto the state of Venice.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 4><SCENE 1><82%>
	Thyself shalt see the act;
	For, as thou urgest justice, be assur'd
	Thou shalt have justice, more than thou desir'st.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 4><SCENE 1><82%>
	Soft!
	The Jew shall have all justice; soft! no haste:—
	He shall have nothing but the penalty.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 4><SCENE 1><82%>
	Therefore prepare thee to cut off the flesh.
	Shed thou no blood; nor cut thou less, nor more,
	But just a pound of flesh: if thou tak'st more,
	Or less, than a just pound, be it but so much
	As makes it light or heavy in the substance,
	Or the division of the twentieth part
	Of one poor scruple, nay, if the scale do turn
	But in the estimation of a hair,
	Thou diest and all thy goods are confiscate.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 4><SCENE 1><83%>
	Why doth the Jew pause? take thy forfeiture.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 4><SCENE 1><83%>
	He hath refus'd it in the open court:
	He shall have merely justice, and his bond.
<SPEECH 79><ACT 4><SCENE 1><83%>
	Thou shalt have nothing but the forfeiture,
	To be so taken at thy peril, Jew.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 4><SCENE 1><83%>
	Tarry, Jew:
	The law hath yet another hold on you.
	It is enacted in the laws of Venice,
	If it be prov'd against an alien
	That by direct or indirect attempts
	He seek the life of any citizen,
	The party 'gainst the which he doth contrive
	Shall seize one half his goods; the other half
	Comes to the privy coffer of the state;
	And the offender's life lies in the mercy
	Of the duke only, 'gainst all other voice.
	In which predicament, I say, thou stand'st;
	For it appears by manifest proceeding,
	That indirectly and directly too
	Thou hast contriv'd against the very life
	Of the defendant; and thou hast incurr'd
	The danger formerly by me rehears'd.
	Down therefore and beg mercy of the duke.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 4><SCENE 1><84%>
	Ay, for the state; not for Antonio.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 4><SCENE 1><84%>
	What mercy can you render him, Antonio?
<SPEECH 83><ACT 4><SCENE 1><85%>
	Art thou contented, Jew? what dost thou say?
<SPEECH 84><ACT 4><SCENE 1><85%>
	Clerk, draw a deed of gift.
<SPEECH 85><ACT 4><SCENE 1><85%>
	I humbly do desire your Grace of pardon:
	I must away this night toward Padua,
	And it is meet I presently set forth.
<SPEECH 86><ACT 4><SCENE 1><86%>
	He is well paid that is well satisfied;
	And I, delivering you, am satisfied,
	And therein do account myself well paid:
	My mind was never yet more mercenary.
	I pray you, know me when we meet again:
	I wish you well, and so I take my leave.
<SPEECH 87><ACT 4><SCENE 1><86%>
	You press me far, and therefore I will yield.
	</STAGE DIR> Give me your gloves, I'll wear them for your sake;
	</STAGE DIR> And, for your love, I'll take this ring from you.
	Do not draw back your hand; I'll take no more;
	And you in love shall not deny me this.
<SPEECH 88><ACT 4><SCENE 1><86%>
	I will have nothing else but only this;
	And now methinks I have a mind to it.
<SPEECH 89><ACT 4><SCENE 1><86%>
	I see, sir, you are liberal in offers:
	You taught me first to beg, and now methinks
	You teach me how a beggar should be answer'd.
<SPEECH 90><ACT 4><SCENE 1><87%>
	That 'scuse serves many men to save their gifts.
	An if your wife be not a mad-woman,
	And know how well I have deserv'd the ring,
	She would not hold out enemy for ever,
	For giving it to me. Well, peace be with you.
<SPEECH 91><ACT 4><SCENE 2><87%>
	Inquire the Jew's house out, give him this deed,
	And let him sign it. We'll away to-night,
	And be a day before our husbands home:
	This deed will be well welcome to Lorenzo.
<SPEECH 92><ACT 4><SCENE 2><88%>
	That cannot be:
	His ring I do accept most thankfully;
	And so, I pray you, tell him: furthermore,
	I pray you, show my youth old Shylock's house.
<SPEECH 93><ACT 4><SCENE 2><88%>
	Thou mayst, I warrant. We shall have old swearing
	That they did give the rings away to men;
	But we'll outface them, and outswear them too.
	Away! make haste: thou know'st where I will tarry.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	That light we see is burning in my hall.
	How far that little candle throws his beams!
	So shines a good deed in a naughty world.
<SPEECH 95><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	So doth the greater glory dim the less:
	A substitute shines brightly as a king
	Until a king be by, and then his state
	Empties itself, as doth an inland brook
	Into the main of waters. Music! hark!
<SPEECH 96><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	Nothing is good, I see, without respect:
	Methinks it sounds much sweeter than by day.
<SPEECH 97><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	The crow doth sing as sweetly as the lark
	When neither is attended, and I think
	The nightingale, if she should sing by day,
	When every goose is cackling, would be thought
	No better a musician than the wren.
	How many things by season season'd are
	To their right praise and true perfection!
	Peace, ho! the moon sleeps with Endymion,
	And would not be awak'd!
<SPEECH 98><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	He knows me, as the blind man knows the cuckoo,
	By the bad voice.
<SPEECH 99><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	We have been praying for our husbands' welfare,
	Which speed, we hope, the better for our words.
	Are they return'd?
<SPEECH 100><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	Go in, Nerissa:
	Give order to my servants that they take
	No note at all of our being absent hence;
	Nor you, Lorenzo; Jessica, nor you.
<SPEECH 101><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	This night methinks is but the daylight sick;
	It looks a little paler: 'tis a day,
	Such as the day is when the sun is hid.
<SPEECH 102><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	Let me give light, but let me not be light;
	For a light wife doth make a heavy husband,
	And never be Bassanio so for me:
	But God sort all! You are welcome home, my lord.
<SPEECH 103><ACT 5><SCENE 1><94%>
	You should in all sense be much bound to him,
	For, as I hear, he was much bound for you.
<SPEECH 104><ACT 5><SCENE 1><94%>
	Sir, you are very welcome to our house:
	It must appear in other ways than words,
	Therefore I scant this breathing courtesy.
<SPEECH 105><ACT 5><SCENE 1><94%>
	A quarrel, ho, already! what's the matter?
<SPEECH 106><ACT 5><SCENE 1><95%>
	You were to blame,—I must be plain with you,—
	To part so slightly with your wife's first gift;
	A thing stuck on with oaths upon your finger,
	And riveted so with faith unto your flesh.
	I gave my love a ring and made him swear
	Never to part with it; and here he stands,
	I dare be sworn for him he would not leave it
	Nor pluck it from his finger for the wealth
	That the world masters. Now, in faith, Gratiano,
	You give your wife too unkind a cause of grief:
	An 'twere to me, I should be mad at it.
<SPEECH 107><ACT 5><SCENE 1><95%>
	What ring gave you, my lord?
	Not that, I hope, that you receiv'd of me.
<SPEECH 108><ACT 5><SCENE 1><96%>
	Even so void is your false heart of truth.
	By heaven, I will ne'er come in your bed
	Until I see the ring.
<SPEECH 109><ACT 5><SCENE 1><96%>
	If you had known the virtue of the ring,
	Or half her worthiness that gave the ring,
	Or your own honour to contain the ring,
	You would not then have parted with the ring.
	What man is there so much unreasonable,
	If you had pleas'd to have defended it
	With any terms of zeal, wanted the modesty
	To urge the thing held as a ceremony?
	Nerissa teaches me what to believe:
	I'll die for't but some woman had the ring.
<SPEECH 110><ACT 5><SCENE 1><97%>
	Let not that doctor e'er come near my house.
	Since he hath got the jewel that I lov'd,
	And that which you did swear to keep for me,
	I will become as liberal as you;
	I'll not deny him anything I have;
	No, not my body, nor my husband's bed.
	Know him I shall, I am well sure of it:
	Lie not a night from home; watch me like Argus:
	If you do not, if I be left alone,
	Now by mine honour, which is yet mine own,
	I'll have that doctor for my bedfellow.
<SPEECH 111><ACT 5><SCENE 1><97%>
	Sir, grieve not you; you are welcome notwithstanding.
<SPEECH 112><ACT 5><SCENE 1><98%>
	Mark you but that!
	In both my eyes he doubly sees himself;
	In each eye, one: swear by your double self,
	And there's an oath of credit.
<SPEECH 113><ACT 5><SCENE 1><98%>
	Then you shall be his surety. Give him this,
	And bid him keep it better than the other.
<SPEECH 114><ACT 5><SCENE 1><98%>
	I had it of him: pardon me, Bassanio,
	For, by this ring, the doctor lay with me.
<SPEECH 115><ACT 5><SCENE 1><98%>
	Speak not so grossly. You are all amaz'd:
	Here is a letter; read it at your leisure;
	It comes from Padus, from Bellario:
	There you shall find that Portia was the doctor,
	Nerissa, there, her clerk: Lorenzo here
	Shall witness I set forth as soon as you
	And even but now return'd; I have not yet
	Enter'd my house. Antonio, you are welcome;
	And I have better news in store for you
	Than you expect: unseal this letter soon;
	There you shall find three of your argosies
	Are richly come to harbour suddenly.
	You shall not know by what strange accident
	I chanced on this letter.
<SPEECH 116><ACT 5><SCENE 1><99%>
	How now, Lorenzo!
	My clerk hath some good comforts too for you.
<SPEECH 117><ACT 5><SCENE 1><100%>
	It is almost morning,
	And yet I am sure you are not satisfied
	Of these events at full. Let us go in;
	And charge us there upon inter'gatories,
	And we will answer all things faithfully.
