<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 3><8%>
	We are sent
	To give thee from our royal master thanks;
	Only to herald thee into his sight,
	Not pay thee.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 3><9%>
	Who was the thane lives yet;
	But under heavy judgment bears that life
	Which he deserves to lose. Whether he was combin'd
	With those of Norway, or did line the rebel
	With hidden help or vantage, or that with both
	He labour'd in his country's wrack, I know not;
	But treasons capital, confess'd and prov'd,
	Have overthrown him.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	Near Birnam wood
	Shall we well meet them; that way are they coming.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	Now does he feel
	His secret murders sticking on his hands;
	Now minutely revolts upbraid his faith-breach;
	Those he commands move only in command,
	Nothing in love; now does he feel his title
	Hang loose about him, like a giant's robe
	Upon a dwarfish thief.
