<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	What is amiss?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 3><36%>
	</STAGE DIR> What should be spoken
	Here where our fate, hid in an auger-hole,
	May rush and seize us? Let's away: our tears
	Are not yet brew'd.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 3><36%>
	To Ireland, I; our separated fortune
	Shall keep us both the safer: where we are,
	There's daggers in men's smiles: the near in blood,
	The nearer bloody.
