<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><21%>
	Knock, sir! whom should I knock? is there any man has rebused your worship?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><21%>
	Knock you here, sir! why, sir, what am I, sir, that I should knock you here, sir?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><21%>
	My master is grown quarrelsome. I should knock you first,
	And then I know after who comes by the worst.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><21%>
	Help, masters, help! my master is mad.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><22%>
	Nay, 'tis no matter, sir, what he 'leges in Latin. If this be not a lawful cause for me to leave his service, look you, sir, he bid me knock him and rap him soundly, sir: well, was it fit for a servant to use his master so; being, perhaps, for aught I see, two-and-thirty, a pip out?
	Whom would to God, I had well knock'd at first,
	Then had not Grumio come by the worst.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><22%>
	Knock at the gate! O heavens! Spake you not these words plain, 'Sirrah, knock me here, rap me here, knock me well, and knock me soundly?' And come you now with 'knocking at the gate?'
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><23%>
	Nay, look you, sir, he tells you flatly what his mind is: why, give him gold enough and marry him to a puppet or an aglet-baby; or an old trot with ne'er a tooth in her head, though she have as many diseases as two-and-fifty horses: why, nothing comes amiss, so money comes withal.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 2><24%>
	I pray you, sir, let him go while the humour lasts. O' my word, an she knew him as well as I do, she would think scolding would do little good upon him. She may, perhaps, call him half a score knaves or so: why, that's nothing: an he begin once, he'll rail in his ropetricks. I'll tell you what, sir, an she stand him but a little, he will throw a figure in her face, and so disfigure her with it that she shall have no more eyes to see withal than a cat. You know him not, sir.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 2><25%>
	Katharine the curst!
	A title for a maid of all titles the worst.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 2><25%>
	Here's no knavery! See, to beguile the old folks, how the young folks lay their heads together!
	Master, master, look about you: who goes there, ha?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 2><26%>
	A proper stripling, and an amorous!
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 2><26%>
	O! this woodcock, what an ass it is.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 2><27%>
	</STAGE DIR> And that his bags shall prove.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 2><27%>
	Will he woo her? ay, or I'll hang her.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 2><28%>
	</STAGE DIR> For he fears none.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 2><28%>
	</STAGE DIR> I would I were as sure of a good dinner.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 2><31%>
	O excellent motion! Fellows, let's be gone.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Ay, sir, they be ready: the oats have eaten the horses.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 1><60%>
	Fie, fie, on all tired jades, on all mad masters, and all foul ways! Was ever man so beaten? was ever man so rayed? was ever man so weary? I am sent before to make a fire, and they are coming after to warm them. Now, were not I a little pot and soon hot, my very lips might freeze to my teeth, my tongue to the roof of my mouth, my heart in my belly, ere I should come by a fire to thaw me; but I, with blowing the fire, shall warm myself; for, considering the weather, a taller man than I will take cold. Holla, ho! Curtis.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 1><60%>
	A piece of ice: if thou doubt it, thou mayst slide from my shoulder to my heel with no greater a run but my head and my neck. A fire, good Curtis.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 4><SCENE 1><60%>
	O! ay, Curtis, ay; and therefore fire, fire; cast on no water.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 1><60%>
	She was, good Curtis, before this frost; but, thou knowest, winter tames man, woman, and beast; for it hath tamed my old master, and my new mistress, and myself, fellow Curtis.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 1><61%>
	Am I but three inches? why, thy horn is a foot; and so long am I at the least. But wilt thou make a fire, or shall I complain on thee to our mistress, whose hand,—she being now at hand,—thou shalt soon feel, to thy cold comfort, for being slow in thy hot office?
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 1><61%>
	A cold world, Curtis, in every office but thine; and therefore, fire. Do thy duty, and have thy duty, for my master and mistress are almost frozen to death.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 1><61%>
	Why, 'Jack, boy! ho, boy!' and as much news as thou wilt.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 1><61%>
	Why therefore fire: for I have caught extreme cold. Where's the cook? is supper ready, the house trimmed, rushes strewed, cobwebs swept; the serving-men in their new fustian, their white stockings, and every officer his wedding-garment on? Be the Jacks fair within, the Jills fair without, and carpets laid, and everything in order?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 1><61%>
	First, know, my horse is tired; my master and mistress fallen out.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 4><SCENE 1><61%>
	Out of their saddles into the dirt; and thereby hangs a tale.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 1><62%>
	Lend thine ear.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 1><62%>
	</STAGE DIR> There.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 1><62%>
	And therefore it is called a sensible tale; and this cuff was but to knock at your ear and beseech listening. Now I begin: Imprimis, we came down a foul hill, my master riding behind my mistress,—
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 1><62%>
	What's that to thee?
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 1><62%>
	Tell thou the tale: but hadst thou not crossed me thou shouldst have heard how her horse fell, and she under her horse; thou shouldst have heard in how miry a place, how she was bemoiled: how he left her with the horse upon her; how he beat me because her horse stumbled; how she waded through the dirt to pluck him off me: how he swore; how she prayed, that never prayed before; how I cried; how the horses ran away; how her bridle was burst; how I lost my crupper; with many things of worthy memory, which now shall die in oblivion, and thou return unexperienced to thy grave.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 1><62%>
	Ay; and that, thou and the proudest of you all shall find when he comes home. But what talk I of this? Call forth Nathaniel, Joseph, Nicholas, Philip, Walter, Sugarsop, and the rest: let their heads be sleekly combed, their blue coats brushed, and their garters of an indifferent knit: let them curtsy with their left legs, and not presume to touch a hair of my master's horsetail till they kiss their hands. Are they all ready?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 4><SCENE 1><63%>
	Call them forth.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 4><SCENE 1><63%>
	Why, she hath a face of her own.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 4><SCENE 1><63%>
	Thou, it seems, that callest for company to countenance her.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 1><63%>
	Why, she comes to borrow nothing of them.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 1><63%>
	Welcome, you; how now, you; what, you; fellow, you; and thus much for greeting. Now, my spruce companions, is all ready, and all things neat?
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 1><63%>
	E'en at hand, alighted by this; and therefore be not,—Cock's passion, silence! I hear my master.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	Here, sir; as foolish as I was before.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	Nathaniel's coat, sir, was not fully made,
	And Gabriel's pumps were all unpink'd i' the heel,
	There was no link to colour Peter's hat,
	And Walter's dagger was not come from sheathing,
	There were none fine but Adam, Ralph, and Gregory;
	The rest were ragged, old, and beggarly;
	Yet, as they are, here are they come to meet you.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 4><SCENE 1><66%>
	Where is he?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	No, no, forsooth; I dare not, for my life.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	What say you to a neat's foot?
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	I fear it is too choleric a meat.
	How say you to a fat tripe finely broil'd?
<SPEECH 47><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	I cannot tell; I fear 'tis choleric.
	What say you to a piece of beef and mustard?
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Ay, but the mustard is too hot a little.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Nay, then I will not: you shall have the mustard,
	Or else you get no beef of Grumio.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Why then, the mustard without the beef.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	I gave him no order; I gave him the stuff.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Marry, sir, with needle and thread.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Thou hast faced many things.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Face not me: thou hast braved many men; brave not me: I will neither be faced nor braved. I say unto thee, I bid thy master cut out the gown; but I did not bid him cut it to pieces: ergo, thou liest.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	The note lies in's throat if he say I said so.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Master, if ever I said loose-bodied gown, sew me in the skirts of it, and beat me to death with a bottom of brown thread. I said, a gown.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	I confess the cape.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	I confess two sleeves.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Error i' the bill, sir; error i' the bill. I commanded the sleeves should be cut out and sewed up again; and that I'll prove upon thee, though thy little finger be armed in a thimble.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	I am for thee straight: take thou the bill, give me thy mete-yard, and spare not me.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	You are i' the right, sir; 'tis for my mistress.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Villain, not for thy life! take up my mistress' gown for thy master's use!
<SPEECH 63><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	O, sir, the conceit is deeper than you think for.
	Take up my mistress' gown to his master's use!
	O, fie, fie, fie!
