<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><13%>
	</STAGE DIR> I pray you, sir, is it your will
	To make a stale of me amongst these mates?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><13%>
	I' faith, sir, you shall never need to fear:
	I wis it is not half way to her heart;
	But if it were, doubt not her care should be
	To comb your noddle with a three-legg'd stool,
	And paint your face, and use you like a fool.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><14%>
	A pretty peat! it is best
	Put finger in the eye, an she knew why.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><15%>
	Why, and I trust I may go too; may I not?
	What! shall I be appointed hours, as though, belike,
	I knew not what to take, and what to leave? Ha!
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	Of all thy suitors, here I charge thee, tell
	Whom thou lov'st best: see thou dissemble not.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	Minion, thou liest. Is't not Hortensio?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	O! then, belike, you fancy riches more:
	You will have Gremio to keep you fair.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 1><32%>
	If that be jest, then all the rest was so.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 1><32%>
	Her silence flouts me, and I'll be reveng'd.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><32%>
	What! will you not suffer me? Nay, now I see
	She is your treasure, she must have a husband;
	I must dance bare-foot on her wedding-day,
	And, for your love to her, lead apes in hell.
	Talk not to me: I will go sit and weep
	Till I can find occasion of revenge.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><38%>
	Well have you heard, but something hard of hearing:
	They call me Katharine that do talk of me.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><38%>
	Mov'd! in good time: let him that mov'd you hither
	Remove you hence. I knew you at the first,
	You were a moveable.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	A joint-stool.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	Asses are made to bear, and so are you.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	No such jade as bear you, if me you mean.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	Too light for such a swain as you to catch,
	And yet as heavy as my weight should be.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	Well ta'en, and like a buzzard.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	Ay, for a turtle, as he takes a buzzard.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	If I be waspish, best beware my sting.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	Ay, if the fool could find it where it lies.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	In his tongue.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	Yours, if you talk of tails; and so farewell.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 1><39%>
	That I'll try.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	So may you lose your arms:
	If you strike me, you are no gentleman;
	And if no gentleman, why then no arms.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	What is your crest? a coxcomb?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	No cock of mine; you crow too like a craven.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	It is my fashion when I see a crab.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	There is, there is.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	Had I a glass, I would.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	Well aim'd of such a young one.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	Yet you are wither'd.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	I care not.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 1><40%>
	I chafe you, if I tarry: let me go.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 1><41%>
	Go, fool, and whom thou keep'st command.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 1><41%>
	Where did you study all this goodly speech?
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 1><41%>
	A witty mother! witless else her son.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 1><41%>
	Yes; keep you warm.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 1><42%>
	Call you me daughter? now, I promise you
	You have show'd a tender fatherly regard,
	To wish me wed to one half lunatic;
	A mad-cap ruffian and a swearing Jack,
	That thinks with oaths to face the matter out.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 1><42%>
	I'll see thee hang'd on Sunday first.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	No shame but mine: I must, forsooth, be forc'd
	To give my hand oppos'd against my heart
	Unto a mad-brain rudesby, full of spleen;
	Who woo'd in haste and means to wed at leisure.
	I told you, I, he was a frantic fool,
	Hiding his bitter jests in blunt behaviour;
	And to be noted for a merry man,
	He'll woo a thousand, 'point the day of marriage,
	Make friends invite, and proclaim the banns;
	Yet never means to wed where he hath woo'd.
	Now must the world point at poor Katharine,
	And say, 'Lo! there is mad Petruchio's wife,
	If it would please him come and marry her.'
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	Would Katharine had never seen him though!
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Let me entreat you.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Are you content to stay?
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Now, if you love me, stay.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Nay, then,
	Do what thou canst, I will not go to-day;
	No, nor to-morrow, nor till I please myself,
	The door is open, sir, there lies your way;
	You may be jogging whiles your boots are green;
	For me, I'll not be gone till I please myself.
	'Tis like you'll prove a jolly surly groom,
	That take it on you at the first so roundly.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	I will be angry: what hast thou to do?
	Father, be quiet; he shall stay my leisure.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Gentlemen, forward to the bridal dinner:
	I see a woman may be made a fool,
	If she had not a spirit to resist.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	Patience, I pray you; 'twas a fault unwilling.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	I pray you, husband, be not so disquiet:
	The meat was well if you were so contented.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 3><72%>
	The more my wrong the more his spite appears.
	What, did he marry me to famish me?
	Beggars, that come unto my father's door,
	Upon entreaty have a present alms;
	If not, elsewhere they meet with charity:
	But I, who never knew how to entreat,
	Nor never needed that I should entreat,
	Am starv'd for meat, giddy for lack of sleep;
	With oaths kept waking, and with brawling fed.
	And that which spites me more than all these wants,
	He does it under name of perfect love;
	As who should say, if I should sleep or eat
	'Twere deadly sickness, or else present death.
	I prithee go and get me some repast;
	I care not what, so it be wholesome food.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	'Tis passing good: I prithee let me have it.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	I like it well: good Grumio, fetch it me.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	A dish that I do love to feed upon.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Why, then the beef, and let the mustard rest.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Then both, or one, or anything thou wilt.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Go, get thee gone, thou false deluding slave,
	That feed'st me with the very name of meat.
	Sorrow on thee and all the pack of you,
	That triumph thus upon my misery!
	Go, get thee gone, I say.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 3><73%>
	Faith, as cold as can be.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	I pray you, let it stand.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	I thank you, sir.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	I'll have no bigger: this doth fit the time,
	And gentlewomen wear such caps as these.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	Why, sir, I trust I may have leave to speak,
	And speak I will; I am no child, no babe:
	Your betters have endur'd me say my mind,
	And if you cannot, best you stop your ears.
	My tongue will tell the anger of my heart,
	Or else my heart, concealing it, will break:
	And rather than it shall, I will be free
	Even to the uttermost, as I please, in words.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	Love me or love me not, I like the cap,
	And it I will have, or I will have none.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	I never saw a better-fashion'd gown,
	More quaint, more pleasing, nor more commendable.
	Belike you mean to make a puppet of me.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 4><SCENE 3><79%>
	I dare assure you, sir, 'tis almost two;
	And 'twill be supper-time ere you come there.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 4><SCENE 5><83%>
	The moon! the sun: it is not moonlight now.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 4><SCENE 5><84%>
	I know it is the sun that shines so bright.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 4><SCENE 5><84%>
	Forward, I pray, since we have come so far,
	And be it moon, or sun, or what you please.
	An if you please to call it a rush-candle,
	Henceforth I vow it shall be so for me.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 4><SCENE 5><84%>
	I know it is the moon.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 4><SCENE 5><84%>
	Then God be bless'd, it is the blessed sun:
	But sun it is not when you say it is not,
	And the moon changes even as your mind.
	What you will have it nam'd, even that it is;
	And so, it shall be so for Katharine.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 4><SCENE 5><85%>
	Young budding virgin, fair and fresh and sweet,
	Whither away, or where is thy abode?
	Happy the parents of so fair a child;
	Happier the man, whom favourable stars
	Allot thee for his lovely bed-fellow!
<SPEECH 71><ACT 4><SCENE 5><85%>
	Pardon, old father, my mistaking eyes,
	That have been so bedazzled with the sun
	That everything I look on seemeth green:
	Now I perceive thou art a reverend father;
	Pardon, I pray thee, for my mad mistaking.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	Husband, let's follow, to see the end of this ado.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	What! in the midst of the street?
<SPEECH 74><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	No, sir, God forbid; but ashamed to kiss.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	Nay, I will give thee a kiss: now pray thee, love, stay.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	Mistress, how mean you that?
<SPEECH 77><ACT 5><SCENE 2><93%>
	'He that is giddy thinks the world turns round:'
	I pray you, tell me what you meant by that.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 5><SCENE 2><94%>
	A very mean meaning.
<SPEECH 79><ACT 5><SCENE 2><94%>
	And I am mean, indeed, respecting you.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 5><SCENE 2><96%>
	What is your will, sir, that you send for me?
<SPEECH 81><ACT 5><SCENE 2><97%>
	They sit conferring by the parlour fire.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	Fie, fie! unknit that threatening unkind brow,
	And dart not scornful glances from those eyes,
	To wound thy lord, thy king, thy governor:
	It blots thy beauty as frosts do bite the meads,
	Confounds thy fame as whirlwinds shake fair buds,
	And in no sense is meet or amiable.
	A woman mov'd is like a fountain troubled,
	Muddy, ill-seeming, thick, bereft of beauty;
	And while it is so, none so dry or thirsty
	Will deign to sip or touch one drop of it.
	Thy husband is thy lord, thy life, thy keeper,
	Thy head, thy sovereign; one that cares for thee,
	And for thy maintenance commits his body
	To painful labour both by sea and land,
	To watch the night in storms, the day in cold,
	Whilst thou liest warm at home, secure and safe;
	And craves no other tribute at thy hands
	But love, fair looks, and true obedience;
	Too little payment for so great a debt.
	Such duty as the subject owes the prince,
	Even such a woman oweth to her husband;
	And when she's froward, peevish, sullen, sour,
	And not obedient to his honest will,
	What is she but a foul contending rebel,
	And graceless traitor to her loving lord?—
	I am asham'd that women are so simple
	To offer war where they should kneel for peace,
	Or seek for rule, supremacy, and sway,
	When they are bound to serve, love, and obey.
	Why are our bodies soft, and weak, and smooth,
	Unapt to toil and trouble in the world,
	But that our soft conditions and our hearts
	Should well agree with our external parts?
	Come, come, you froward and unable worms!
	My mind hath been as big as one of yours,
	My heart as great, my reason haply more,
	To bandy word for word and frown for frown;
	But now I see our lances are but straws,
	Our strength as weak, our weakness past compare,
	That seeming to be most which we indeed least are.
	Then vail your stomachs, for it is no boot,
	And place your hands below your husband's foot:
	In token of which duty, if he please,
	My hand is ready; may it do him ease.
