<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 5><32%>
	More, more, I prithee, more.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 5><32%>
	I thank it. More! I prithee, more. I can suck melancholy out of a song as a weasel sucks eggs. More! I prithee, more.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 5><32%>
	I do not desire you to please me; I do desire you to sing. Come, more; another stanzo: call you them stanzos?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 5><32%>
	Nay, I care not for their names; they owe me nothing. Will you sing?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 5><33%>
	Well then, if ever I thank any man, I'll thank you: but that they call compliment is like the encounter of two dog-apes, and when a man thanks me heartily, methinks I have given him a penny and he renders me the beggarly thanks. Come, sing; and you that will not, hold your tongues.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 5><33%>
	And I have been all this day to avoid him. He is too disputable for my company: I think of as many matters as he, but I give heaven thanks, and make no boast of them. Come, warble; come.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 5><33%>
	I'll give you a verse to this note, that I made yesterday in despite of my invention.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 5><33%>
	Thus it goes:
	If it do come to pass
	That any man turn ass,
	Leaving his wealth and ease,
	A stubborn will to please,
	Ducdame, ducdame, ducdame:
	Here shall he see
	Gross fools as he,
	An if he will come to me.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 5><34%>
	'Tis a Greek invocation to call fools into a circle. I'll go sleep if I can; if I cannot, I'll rail against all the first-born of Egypt.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 7><35%>
	A fool, a fool! I met a fool i' the forest,
	A motley fool; a miserable world!
	As I do live by food, I met a fool;
	Who laid him down and bask'd him in the sun,
	And rail'd on Lady Fortune in good terms,
	In good set terms, and yet a motley fool.
	'Good morrow, fool,' quoth I. 'No, sir,' quoth he,
	'Call me not fool till heaven hath sent me fortune.'
	And then he drew a dial from his poke,
	And, looking on it with lack-lustre eye,
	Says very wisely, 'It is ten o'clock;
	Thus may we see,' quoth he, 'how the world wags:
	'Tis but an hour ago since it was nine,
	And after one hour more 'twill be eleven;
	And so, from hour to hour we ripe and ripe,
	And then from hour to hour we rot and rot,
	And thereby hangs a tale.' When I did hear
	The motley fool thus moral on the time,
	My lungs began to crow like chanticleer,
	That fools should be so deep-contemplative,
	And I did laugh sans intermission
	An hour by his dial. O noble fool!
	A worthy fool! Motley's the only wear.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 7><36%>
	O worthy fool! One that hath been a courtier,
	And says, if ladies be but young and fair,
	They have the gift to know it; and in his brain,—
	Which is as dry as the remainder biscuit
	After a voyage,—he hath strange places cramm'd
	With observation, the which he vents
	In mangled forms. O that I were a fool!
	I am ambitious for a motley coat.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 7><36%>
	It is my only suit;
	Provided that you weed your better judgments
	Of all opinion that grows rank in them
	That I am wise. I must have liberty
	Withal, as large a charter as the wind,
	To blow on whom I please; for so fools have:
	And they that are most galled with my folly,
	They most must laugh. And why, sir, must they so?
	The 'why' is plain as way to parish church:
	He that a fool doth very wisely hit
	Doth very foolishly, although he smart,
	Not to seem senseless of the bob; if not,
	The wise man's folly is anatomiz'd
	Even by the squandering glances of the fool.
	Invest me in my motley; give me leave
	To speak my mind, and I will through and through
	Cleanse the foul body of th' infected world,
	If they will patiently receive my medicine.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 7><37%>
	What, for a counter, would I do, but good?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 7><37%>
	Why, who cries out on pride,
	That can therein tax any private party?
	Doth it not flow as hugely as the sea,
	Till that the weary very means do ebb?
	What woman in the city do I name,
	When that I say the city-woman bears
	The cost of princes on unworthy shoulders?
	Who can come in and say that I mean her,
	When such a one as she such is her neighbour?
	Or what is he of basest function,
	That says his bravery is not on my cost,—
	Thinking that I mean him,—but therein suits
	His folly to the mettle of my speech?
	There then; how then? what then? Let me see wherein
	My tongue hath wrong'd him: if it do him right,
	Then he hath wrong'd himself; if he be free,
	Why then, my taxing like a wild goose flies,
	Unclaim'd of any man. But who comes here?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	Why, I have eat none yet.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	Of what kind should this cock come of?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 7><38%>
	An you will not be answered with reason,
	I must die.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 7><40%>
	All the world's a stage,
	And all the men and women merely players:
	They have their exits and their entrances;
	And one man in his time plays many parts,
	His acts being seven ages. At first the infant,
	Mewling and puking in the nurse's arms.
	And then the whining school-boy, with his satchel,
	And shining morning face, creeping like snail
	Unwillingly to school. And then the lover,
	Sighing like furnace, with a woful ballad
	Made to his mistress' eyebrow. Then a soldier,
	Full of strange oaths, and bearded like the pard,
	Jealous in honour, sudden and quick in quarrel,
	Seeking the bubble reputation
	Even in the cannon's mouth. And then the justice,
	In fair round belly with good capon lin'd,
	With eyes severe, and beard of formal cut,
	Full of wise saws and modern instances;
	And so he plays his part. The sixth age shifts
	Into the lean and slipper'd pantaloon,
	With spectacles on nose and pouch on side,
	His youthful hose well sav'd, a world too wide
	For his shrunk shank; and his big manly voice,
	Turning again toward childish treble, pipes
	And whistles in his sound. Last scene of all,
	That ends this strange eventful history,
	Is second childishness and mere oblivion,
	Sans teeth, sans eyes, sans taste, sans everything.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	I thank you for your company; but, good faith, I had as lief have been myself alone.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	God be wi' you: let's meet as little as we can.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	I pray you, mar no more trees with writing love-songs in their barks.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	Rosalind is your love's name?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	I do not like her name.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 2><51%>
	What stature is she of?
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	You are full of pretty answers. Have you not been acquainted with goldsmiths' wives, and conn'd them out of rings?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	You have a nimble wit: I think 'twas made of Atalanta's heels. Will you sit down with me? and we two will rail against our mistress the world, and all our misery.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	The worst fault you have is to be in love.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	By my troth, I was seeking for a fool when I found you.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	There I shall see mine own figure.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 2><52%>
	I'll tarry no longer with you. Farewell, good Signior Love.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	</STAGE DIR> O knowledge ill-inhabited, worse than Jove in a thatch'd house!
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	</STAGE DIR> A material fool.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	</STAGE DIR> I would fain see this meeting.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	</STAGE DIR> Proceed, proceed: I'll give her.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	Will you be married, motley?
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	And will you, being a man of your breeding, be married under a bush, like a beggar? Get you to church, and have a good priest that can tell you what marriage is: this fellow will but join you together as they join wainscot; then one of you will prove a shrunk panel, and like green timber, warp, warp.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	Go thou with me, and let me counsel thee.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	I prithee, pretty youth, let me be better acquainted with thee.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	I am so; I do love it better than laughing.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	Why, 'tis good to be sad and say nothing.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	I have neither the scholar's melancholy, which is emulation; nor the musician's, which is fantastical; nor the courtier's, which is proud; nor the soldier's, which is ambitious; nor the lawyer's, which is politic; nor the lady's, which is nice; nor the lover's, which is all these: but it is a melancholy of mine own, compounded of many simples, extracted from many objects, and indeed the sundry contemplation of my travels, which, by often rumination, wraps me in a most humorous sadness.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	Yes, I have gained my experience.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	Nay then, God be wi' you, an you talk in blank verse.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 4><SCENE 2><76%>
	Which is he that killed the deer?
<SPEECH 45><ACT 4><SCENE 2><76%>
	Let's present him to the duke, like a
	Roman conqueror; and it would do well to set the deer's horns upon his head for a branch of victory. Have you no song, forester, for this purpose?
<SPEECH 46><ACT 4><SCENE 2><76%>
	Sing it: 'tis no matter how it be in tune so it make noise enough.
	What shall he have that kill'd the deer?
	His leather skin and horns to wear.
	Then sing him home
	Take thou no scorn to wear the horn;
	It was a crest ere thou wast born:
	Thy father's father wore it,
	And thy father bore it:
	The horn, the horn, the lusty horn
	Is not a thing to laugh to scorn
<SPEECH 47><ACT 5><SCENE 4><93%>
	There is, sure, another flood toward, and these couples are coming to the ark. Here comes a pair of very strange beasts, which in all tongues are called fools.
<SPEECH 48><ACT 5><SCENE 4><93%>
	Good my lord, bid him welcome. This is the motley-minded gentleman that I have so often met in the forest: he hath been a courtier, he swears.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 5><SCENE 4><93%>
	And how was that ta'en up?
<SPEECH 50><ACT 5><SCENE 4><93%>
	How seventh cause? Good my lord, like this fellow.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 5><SCENE 4><94%>
	But, for the seventh cause; how did you find the quarrel on the seventh cause?
<SPEECH 52><ACT 5><SCENE 4><95%>
	And how oft did you say his beard was not well cut?
<SPEECH 53><ACT 5><SCENE 4><95%>
	Can you nominate in order now the degrees of the lie?
<SPEECH 54><ACT 5><SCENE 4><95%>
	Is not this a rare fellow, my lord? he's as good at any thing, and yet a fool.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 5><SCENE 4><97%>
	Let me have audience for a word or two:
	I am the second son of old Sir Rowland,
	That bring these tidings to this fair assembly.
	Duke Frederick, hearing how that every day
	Men of great worth resorted to this forest,
	Address'd a mighty power, which were on foot
	In his own conduct, purposely to take
	His brother here and put him to the sword:
	And to the skirts of this wild wood he came,
	Where, meeting with an old religious man,
	After some question with him, was converted
	Both from his enterprise and from the world;
	His crown bequeathing to his banish'd brother,
	And all their lands restor'd to them again
	That were with him exil'd. This to be true,
	I do engage my life.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 5><SCENE 4><98%>
	Sir, by your patience. If I heard you rightly,
	The duke hath put on a religious life,
	And thrown into neglect the pompous court?
<SPEECH 57><ACT 5><SCENE 4><98%>
	He hath.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 5><SCENE 4><98%>
	To him will I: out of these convertites
	There is much matter to be heard and learn'd.
	</STAGE DIR> You to your former honour I bequeath;
	Your patience and your virtue well deserve it:
	</STAGE DIR> You to a love that your true faith doth merit:
	</STAGE DIR> You to your land, and love, and great allies:
	</STAGE DIR> You to a long and well-deserved bed:
	</STAGE DIR> And you to wrangling; for thy loving voyage
	Is but for two months victual'd. So, to your pleasures:
	I am for other than for dancing measures.
<SPEECH 59><ACT 5><SCENE 4><99%>
	To see no pastime, I: what you would have
	I'll stay to know at your abandon'd cave.
