<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 4><29%>
	O Corin, that thou knew'st how I do love her!
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 4><29%>
	No, Corin; being old, thou canst not guess,
	Though in thy youth thou wast as true a lover
	As ever sigh'd upon a midnight pillow:
	But if thy love were ever like to mine,—
	As sure I think did never man love so,—
	How many actions most ridiculous
	Hast thou been drawn to by thy fantasy?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 4><29%>
	O! thou didst then ne'er love so heartily.
	If thou remember'st not the slightest folly
	That ever love did make thee run into,
	Thou hast not lov'd:
	Or if thou hast not sat as I do now,
	Wearing thy hearer with thy mistress' praise,
	Thou hast not lov'd:
	Or if thou hast not broke from company
	Abruptly, as my passion now makes me,
	Thou hast not lov'd. O Phebe, Phebe, Phebe!
<SPEECH 4><ACT 3><SCENE 5><63%>
	Sweet Phebe, do not scorn me; do not, Phebe:
	Say that you love me not, but say not so
	In bitterness. The common executioner,
	Whose heart the accustom'd sight of death makes hard,
	Falls not the axe upon the humbled neck
	But first begs pardon: will you sterner be
	Than he that dies and lives by bloody drops?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE 5><64%>
	O dear Phebe,
	If ever,—as that ever may be near,—
	You meet in some fresh cheek the power of fancy,
	Then shall you know the wounds invisible
	That love's keen arrows make.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	Sweet Phebe,—
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	Sweet Phebe, pity me.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	Wherever sorrow is, relief would be:
	If you do sorrow at my grief in love,
	By giving love your sorrow and my grief
	Were both extermin'd.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 5><66%>
	I would have you.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 5><67%>
	So holy and so perfect is my love,
	And I in such a poverty of grace,
	That I shall think it a most plenteous crop
	To glean the broken ears after the man
	That the main harvest reaps: loose now and then
	A scatter'd smile, and that I'll live upon.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 5><67%>
	Not very well, but I have met him oft;
	And he hath bought the cottage and the bounds
	That the old carlot once was master of.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 5><68%>
	Phebe, with all my heart.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	My errand is to you, fair youth.
	My gentle Phebe did bid me give you this:
	I know not the contents; but, as I guess
	By the stern brow and waspish action
	Which she did use as she was writing of it,
	It bears an angry tenour: pardon me;
	I am but as a guiltless messenger.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	No, I protest, I know not the contents:
	Phebe did write it.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Sure, it is hers.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	So please you, for I never heard it yet;
	Yet heard too much of Phebe's cruelty.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Call you this railing?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	Call you this chiding?
<SPEECH 19><ACT 5><SCENE 2><88%>
	It is to be all made of sighs and tears;
	And so am I for Phebe.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 5><SCENE 2><88%>
	It is to be all made of faith and service;
	And so am I for Phebe.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 5><SCENE 2><89%>
	It is to be all made of fantasy,
	All made of passion, and all made of wishes;
	All adoration, duty, and observance;
	All humbleness, all patience, and impatience;
	All purity, all trial, all obeisance;
	And so am I for Phebe.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 5><SCENE 2><89%>
	</STAGE DIR> If this be so, why blame you me to love you?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 5><SCENE 2><90%>
	I'll not fail, if I live.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 5><SCENE 4><92%>
	Though to have her and death were both one thing.
