<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	Mars his true moving, even as in the heavens
	So in the earth, to this day is not known.
	Late did he shine upon the English side;
	Now we are victors; upon us he smiles.
	What towns of any moment but we have?
	At pleasure here we lie near Orleans;
	Otherwhiles the famish'd English, like pale ghosts,
	Faintly besiege us one hour in a month.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	Sound, sound alarum! we will rush on them.
	Now for the honour of the forlorn French!
	Him I forgive my death that killeth me
	When he sees me go back one foot or fly.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	Who ever saw the like? what men have I!
	Dogs! cowards! dastards! I would ne'er have fled
	But that they left me 'midst my enemies.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Let's leave this town; for they are hare-brain'd slaves,
	And hunger will enforce them to be more eager:
	Of old I know them; rather with their teeth
	The walls they'll tear down than forsake the siege.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Bastard of Orleans, thrice welcome to us.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	Go, call her in. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> But first, to try her skill,
	Reignier, stand thou as Dauphin in my place:
	Question her proudly; let thy looks be stern:
	By this means shall we sound what skill she hath.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	Thou hast astonish'd me with thy high terms.
	Only this proof I'll of thy valour make,
	In single combat thou shalt buckle with me,
	And if thou vanquishest, thy words are true;
	Otherwise I renounce all confidence.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	Then come, o' God's name; I fear no woman.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 2><10%>
	Stay, stay thy hands! thou art an Amazon,
	And fightest with the sword of Deborah.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Whoe'er helps thee, 'tis thou that must help me:
	Impatiently I burn with thy desire;
	My heart and hands thou hast at once subdu'd.
	Excellent Pucelle, if thy name be so,
	Let me thy servant and not sovereign be;
	'Tis the French Dauphin sueth to thee thus.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	Meantime look gracious on thy prostrate thrall.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 2><11%>
	What she says, I'll confirm: we'll fight it out.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	Was Mahomet inspired with a dove?
	Thou with an eagle art inspired then.
	Helen, the mother of great Constantine,
	Nor yet Saint Philip's daughters were like thee.
	Bright star of Venus, fall'n down on the earth,
	How may I reverently worship thee enough?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 2><12%>
	Presently we'll try. Come, let's away about it:
	No prophet will I trust if she prove false.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 6><22%>
	Divinest creature, Astræa's daughter,
	How shall I honour thee for this success?
	Thy promises are like Adonis' gardens,
	That one day bloom'd and fruitful were the next.
	France, triumph in thy glorious prophetess!
	Recover'd is the town of Orleans:
	More blessed hap did ne'er befall our state.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 6><23%>
	'Tis Joan, not we, by whom the day is won;
	For which I will divide my crown with her;
	And all the priests and friars in my realm
	Shall in procession sing her endless praise.
	A statelier pyramis to her I'll rear
	Than Rhodope's or Memphis ever was:
	In memory of her when she is dead,
	Her ashes, in an urn more precious
	Than the rich-jewell'd coffer of Darius,
	Transported shall be at high festivals
	Before the kings and queens of France.
	No longer on Saint Denis will we cry,
	But Joan la Pucelle shall be France's saint.
	Come in, and let us banquet royally,
	After this golden day of victory.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Is this thy cunning, thou deceitful dame?
	Didst thou at first, to flatter us withal,
	Make us partakers of a little gain,
	That now our loss might be ten times so much?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Duke of Alençon, this was your default,
	That, being captain of the watch to-night,
	Did look no better to that weighty charge.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	And for myself, most part of all this night,
	Within her quarter and mine own precinct
	I was employ'd in passing to and fro,
	About relieving of the sentinels:
	Then how or which way should they first break in?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 2><49%>
	Saint Denis bless this happy stratagem!
	And once again we'll sleep secure in Roan.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	Now shine it like a comet of revenge,
	A prophet to the fall of all our foes!
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 2><50%>
	Your Grace may starve perhaps, before that time.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 3><SCENE 3><54%>
	We have been guided by thee hitherto,
	And of thy cunning had no diffidence:
	One sudden foil shall never breed distrust.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 3><SCENE 3><55%>
	Ay, marry, sweeting, if we could do that,
	France were no place for Henry's warriors;
	Nor should that nation boast it so with us,
	But be extirped from our provinces.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 3><SCENE 3><55%>
	A parley with the Duke of Burgundy!
<SPEECH 26><ACT 3><SCENE 3><56%>
	Speak, Pucelle, and enchant him with thy words.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	Welcome, brave duke! thy friendship makes us fresh.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 3><SCENE 3><57%>
	Now let us on, my lords, and join our powers:
	And seek how we may prejudice the foe.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 4><SCENE 7><77%>
	Had York and Somerset brought rescue in
	We should have found a bloody day of this.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	O, no! forbear; for that which we have fled
	During the life, let us not wrong it dead.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	On what submissive message art thou sent?
<SPEECH 32><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	For prisoners ask'st thou? hell our prison is.
	But tell me whom thou seek'st.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	Go, take their bodies hence.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	So we be rid of them, do with 'em what thou wilt.
	And now to Paris, in this conquering vein:
	All will be ours now bloody Talbot's slain.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 5><SCENE 2><82%>
	These news, my lord, may cheer our drooping spirits;
	'Tis said the stout Parisians do revolt,
	And turn again unto the war-like French.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 5><SCENE 2><82%>
	What tidings send our scouts? I prithee speak.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 5><SCENE 2><82%>
	Somewhat too sudden, sirs, the warning is:
	But we will presently provide for them.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 5><SCENE 2><83%>
	Then on, my lords; and France be fortunate!
<SPEECH 39><ACT 5><SCENE 4><94%>
	Since, lords of England, it is thus agreed,
	That peaceful truce shall be proclaim'd in France,
	We come to be informed by yourselves
	What the conditions of that league must be.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 5><SCENE 4><95%>
	'Tis known already that I am possess'd
	With more than half the Gallian territories,
	And therein reverenc'd for their lawful king:
	Shall I, for lucre of the rest unvanquish'd,
	Detract so much from that prerogative
	As to be call'd but viceroy of the whole?
	No, lord ambassador; I'll rather keep
	That which I have than, coveting for more,
	Be cast from possibility of all.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 5><SCENE 4><96%>
	It shall;
	Only reserv'd, you claim no interest
	In any of our towns of garrison.
