<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 4><81%>
	Hie, good Sir Michael; bear this sealed brief
	With winged haste to the lord marshal;
	This to my cousin Scroop, and all the rest
	To whom they are directed. If you knew
	How much they do import, you would make haste.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 4><81%>
	Like enough you do.
	To-morrow, good Sir Michael, is a day
	Wherein the fortune of ten thousand men
	Must bide the touch; for, sir, at Shrewsbury,
	As I am truly given to understand,
	The king with mighty and quick-raised power
	Meets with Lord Harry: and, I fear, Sir Michael,
	What with the sickness of Northumberland,—
	Whose power was in the first proportion,—
	And what with Owen Glendower's absence thence,
	Who with them was a rated sinew too,
	And comes not in, o'er-rul'd by prophecies,—
	I fear the power of Percy is too weak
	To wage an instant trial with the king.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 4><82%>
	No, Mortimer is not there.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 4><82%>
	And so there is; but yet the king hath drawn
	The special head of all the land together:
	The Prince of Wales, Lord John of Lancaster,
	The noble Westmoreland, and war-like Blunt;
	And many moe corrivals and dear men
	Of estimation and command in arms.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 4><82%>
	I hope no less, yet needful 'tis to fear;
	And, to prevent the worse, Sir Michael, speed:
	For if Lord Percy thrive not, ere the king
	Dismiss his power, he means to visit us,
	For he hath heard of our confederacy,
	And 'tis but wisdom to make strong against him:
	Therefore make haste. I must go write again
	To other friends; and so farewell, Sir Michael.
