<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 4><9%>
	I have seen him in France: we had very many there could behold the sun with as firm eyes as he.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 4><9%>
	And then, his banishment.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 4><9%>
	Sir, we have known together in Orleans.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 4><10%>
	Sir, you o'er-rate my poor kindness. I was glad I did atone my countryman and you; it had been pity you should have been put together with so mortal a purpose as then each bore, upon importance of so slight and trivial a nature.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 4><10%>
	Faith, yes, to be put to the arbitrement of swords, and by such two that would by all likelihood have confounded one the other, or have fallen both.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 4><10%>
	Safely, I think. 'Twas a contention in public, which may, without contradiction, suffer the report. It was much like an argument that fell out last night, where each of us fell in praise of our country mistresses; this gentleman at that time vouching—and upon warrant of bloody affirmation—his to be more fair, virtuous, wise, chaste, constant, qualified, and less attemptable, than any the rarest of our ladies in France.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	Will this hold, think you?
