<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	</STAGE DIR> No faith; not so much as his patience.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	</STAGE DIR> His steel was in debt; it went o' the backside the town.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	</STAGE DIR> No; but he fled forward still, toward your face.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><6%>
	</STAGE DIR> As many inches as you have oceans. Puppies!
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	</STAGE DIR> So would I till you had measured how long a fool you were upon the ground.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	</STAGE DIR> If it be a sin to make a true election, she is damned.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	</STAGE DIR> She shines not upon fools, lest the reflection should hurt her.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	</STAGE DIR> I wish not so; unless it had been the fall of an ass, which is no great hurt.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	Well, my lord.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	</STAGE DIR> If his wit had been like him that broke it, it would have run all out.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	No, my lord; <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> nor crop the ears of them.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	</STAGE DIR> To have smelt like a fool.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	</STAGE DIR> You are cock and capon too; and you crow, cock, with your comb on.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	It is not fit your lordship should undertake every companion that you give offence to.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	Ay, it is fit for your lordship only.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	</STAGE DIR> He's a strange fellow himself, and knows it not.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	</STAGE DIR> You are a fool, granted; therefore your issues, being foolish, do not derogate.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	I'll attend your lordship.
	That such a crafty devil as is his mother
	Should yield the world this ass! a woman that
	Bears all down with her brain, and this her son
	Cannot take two from twenty for his heart
	And leave eighteen. Alas! poor princess,
	Thou divine Imogen, what thou endur'st
	Betwixt a father by thy step-dame govern'd,
	A mother hourly coining plots, a wooer
	More hateful than the foul expulsion is
	Of thy dear husband, than that horrid act
	Of the divorce he'd make. The heavens hold firm
	The walls of thy dear honour; keep unshak'd
	That temple, thy fair mind; that thou mayst stand,
	To enjoy thy banish'd lord and this great land!
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 3><27%>
	Here comes the king.
