<SPEECH 1><ACT 3><SCENE 1><36%>
	When Julius Cæsar—whose remembrance yet
	Lives in men's eyes, and will to ears and tongues
	Be theme and hearing ever—was in this Britain,
	And conquer'd it, Cassibelan, thine uncle,—
	Famous in Cæsar's praises, no whit less
	Than in his feats deserving it,—for him
	And his succession, granted Rome a tribute,
	Yearly three thousand pounds, which by thee lately
	Is left untender'd.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 3><SCENE 1><38%>
	I am sorry, Cymbeline,
	That I am to pronounce Augustus Cæsar—
	Cæsar, that hath more kings his servants than
	Thyself domestic officers—thine enemy.
	Receive it from me, then: war and confusion
	In Cæsar's name pronounce I 'gainst thee: look
	For fury not to be resisted. Thus defied,
	I thank thee for myself.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 3><SCENE 1><38%>
	Let proof speak.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 3><SCENE 1><39%>
	So, sir.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE 5><50%>
	Thanks, royal sir.
	My emperor hath wrote, I must from hence;
	And am right sorry that I must report ye
	My master's enemy.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE 5><50%>
	So, sir: I desire of you
	A conduct over land to Milford-Haven.
	Madam, all joy befall your Grace.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE 5><50%>
	Your hand, my lord.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 5><50%>
	Sir, the event
	Is yet to name the winner. Fare you well.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	But what from Rome?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	When expect you them?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	This forwardness
	Makes our hopes fair. Command our present numbers
	Be muster'd; bid the captains look to 't. Now, sir,
	What have you dream'd of late of this war's purpose?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	Dream often so,
	And never false. Soft, ho! what trunk is here
	Without his top? The ruin speaks that sometime
	It was a worthy building. How! a page!
	Or dead or sleeping on him? But dead rather,
	For nature doth abhor to make his bed
	With the defunct, or sleep upon the dead.
	Let's see the boy's face.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 2><70%>
	He'll, then, instruct us of this body. Young one,
	Inform us of thy fortunes, for it seems
	They crave to be demanded. Who is this
	Thou mak'st thy bloody pillow? Or who was he
	That, otherwise than noble nature did,
	Hath alter'd that good picture? What's thy interest
	In this sad wrack? How came it? Who is it?
	What art thou?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 4><SCENE 2><71%>
	'Lack, good youth!
	Thou mov'st no less with thy complaining than
	Thy master in bleeding. Say his name, good friend.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 4><SCENE 2><71%>
	Thy name?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 2><71%>
	Thou dost approve thyself the very same;
	Thy name well fits thy faith, thy faith thy name.
	Wilt take thy chance with me? I will not say
	Thou shalt be so well master'd, but be sure
	No less belov'd. The Roman emperor's letters,
	Sent by a consul to me, should not sooner
	Than thine own worth prefer thee. Go with me.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 2><71%>
	Ay, good youth,
	And rather father thee than master thee.
	My friends,
	The boy hath taught us manly duties; let us
	Find out the prettiest daisied plot we can,
	And make him with our pikes and partisans
	A grave; come, arm him. Boy, he is preferr'd
	By thee to us, and he shall be interr'd
	As soldiers can. Be cheerful; wipe thine eyes:
	Some falls are means the happier to arise.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 5><SCENE 2><77%>
	Away, boy, from the troops, and save thyself;
	For friends kill friends, and the disorder's such
	As war were hoodwink'd.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 5><SCENE 2><77%>
	It is a day turn'd strangely: or betimes
	Let's re-inforce, or fly.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 5><SCENE 5><88%>
	Consider, sir, the chance of war: the day
	Was yours by accident; had it gone with us,
	We should not, when the blood was cool, have threaten'd
	Our prisoners with the sword. But since the gods
	Will have it thus, that nothing but our lives
	May be call'd ransom, let it come; sufficeth,
	A Roman with a Roman's heart can suffer;
	Augustus lives to think on 't; and so much
	For my peculiar care. This one thing only
	I will entreat; my boy, a Briton born,
	Let him be ransom'd; never master had
	A page so kind, so duteous, diligent,
	So tender over his occasions, true,
	So feat, so nurse-like. Let his virtue join
	With my request, which I'll make bold your highness
	Cannot deny; he hath done no Briton harm,
	Though he have serv'd a Roman. Save him, sir,
	And spare no blood beside.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 5><SCENE 5><89%>
	I do not bid thee beg my life, good lad;
	And yet I know thou wilt.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 5><SCENE 5><89%>
	The boy disdains me,
	He leaves me, scorns me; briefly die their joys
	That place them on the truth of girls and boys.
	Why stands he so perplex'd?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 5><SCENE 5><98%>
	Happy be you!
<SPEECH 24><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	Philarmonus!
<SPEECH 25><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	Read, and declare the meaning
