<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	Why, knows not Montague, that of itself
	England is safe, if true within itself?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	'Tis better using France than trusting France:
	Let us be back'd with God and with the seas
	Which he hath given for fence impregnable,
	And with their helps only defend ourselves:
	In them and in ourselves our safety lies.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 1><67%>
	And Hastings as he favours Edward's cause!
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 5><73%>
	To Lynn, my lord; and ship from thence to Flanders.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 7><77%>
	My liege, I'll knock once more to summon them.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	Why, Master Mayor, why stand you in a doubt?
	Open the gates; we are King Henry's friends.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 4><SCENE 7><78%>
	The good old man would fain that all were well,
	So 'twere not 'long of him; but being enter'd,
	I doubt not, I, but we shall soon persuade
	Both him and all his brothers unto reason.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	Away with scrupulous wit! now arms must rule.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 7><79%>
	Sound, trumpet! Edward shall be here proclaim'd;
	Come, fellow soldier, make thou proclamation.
