<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><9%>
	Father, you cannot disinherit me:
	If you be king, why should not I succeed?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><10%>
	When I return with victory from the field
	I'll see your Grace: till then, I'll follow her.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	My gracious father, by your kingly leave,
	I'll draw it as apparent to the crown,
	And in that quarrel use it to the death.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 2><29%>
	My royal father, cheer these noble lords,
	And hearten those that fight in your defence:
	Unsheathe your sword, good father: cry, 'Saint George!'
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 2><31%>
	If that be right which Warwick says is right,
	There is no wrong, but everything is right.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 5><39%>
	Fly, father, fly! for all your friends are fled,
	And Warwick rages like a chafed bull.
	Away! for death doth hold us in pursuit.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 3><SCENE 3><56%>
	And why not queen?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	To Edward, but not to the English king.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	Nay, mark how Lewis stamps as he were nettled:
	I hope all's for the best.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 3><SCENE 3><62%>
	Yes, I accept her, for she well deserves it;
	And here, to pledge my vow, I give my hand.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 5><SCENE 4><90%>
	Methinks a woman of this valiant spirit
	Should, if a coward heard her speak these words,
	Infuse his breast with magnanimity,
	And make him, naked, foil a man at arms.
	I speak not this, as doubting any here;
	For did I but suspect a fearful man,
	He should have leave to go away betimes,
	Lest in our need he might infect another,
	And make him of like spirit to himself.
	If any such be here, as God forbid!
	Let him depart before we need his help.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 5><SCENE 4><91%>
	And take his thanks that yet hath nothing else.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 5><SCENE 5><93%>
	Speak like a subject, proud ambitious York!
	Suppose that I am now my father's mouth:
	Resign thy chair, and where I stand kneel thou,
	Whilst I propose the self-same words to thee,
	Which, traitor, thou wouldst have me answer to.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 5><SCENE 5><93%>
	Let Æsop fable in a winter's night;
	His currish riddles sort not with this place.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 5><SCENE 5><93%>
	Nay, take away this scolding crookback rather.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 5><SCENE 5><93%>
	I know my duty; you are all undutiful:
	Lascivious Edward, and thou perjur'd George,
	And thou mis-shapen Dick, I tell ye all,
	I am your better, traitors as ye are;
	And thou usurp'st my father's right and mine.
