<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 1><65%>
	My lords, before it pleas'd his majesty
	To raise my state to title of a queen,
	Do me but right, and you must all-confess
	That I was not ignoble of descent;
	And meaner than myself have had like fortune.
	But as this title honours me and mine,
	So your dislikes, to whom I would be pleasing,
	Do cloud my joys with danger and with sorrow.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Why, brother Rivers, are you yet to learn,
	What late misfortune is befall'n King Edward?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	No, but the loss of his own royal person.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 4><71%>
	Ay, almost slain, for he is taken prisoner;
	Either betray'd by falsehood of his guard
	Or by his foe surpris'd at unawares:
	And, as I further have to understand,
	Is new committed to the Bishop of York,
	Fell Warwick's brother, and by that our foe.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 4><72%>
	Till then fair hope must hinder life's decay.
	And I the rather wean me from despair
	For love of Edward's offspring in my womb:
	This is it that makes me bridle passion,
	And bear with mildness my misfortune's cross;
	Ay, ay, for this I draw in many a tear,
	And stop the rising of blood-sucking sighs,
	Lest with my sighs or tears I blast or drown
	King Edward's fruit, true heir to the English crown.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 4><SCENE 4><72%>
	I am inform'd that he comes towards London,
	To set the crown once more on Henry's head:
	Guess thou the rest; King Edward's friends must down.
	But, to prevent the tyrant's violence,—
	For trust not him that hath once broken faith,—
	I'll hence forthwith unto the sanctuary,
	To save at least the heir of Edward's right:
	There shall I rest secure from force and fraud.
	Come, therefore; let us fly while we may fly:
	If Warwick take us we are sure to die.
