<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	What! shall we suffer this? let's pluck him down:
	My heart for anger burns; I cannot brook it.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	He is both king and Duke of Lancaster;
	And that the Lord of Westmoreland shall maintain.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	Plantagenet, of thee, and these thy sons,
	Thy kinsmen and thy friends, I'll have more lives
	Than drops of blood were in my father's veins.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Base, fearful, and despairing Henry!
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	I cannot stay to hear these articles.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Farewell, faint-hearted and degenerate king,
	In whose cold blood no spark of honour bides.
