<SPEECH 1><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	And if words will not, then our weapons shall.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 5><SCENE 1><94%>
	Oft have I seen a hot o'erweening cur
	Run back and bite, because he was withheld;
	Who, being suffer'd with the bear's fell paw,
	Hath clapp'd his tail between his legs, and cried:
	And such a piece of service will you do,
	If you oppose yourselves to match Lord Warwick.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 5><SCENE 1><96%>
	Fie! charity! for shame! speak not in spite,
	For you shall sup with Jesu Christ to-night.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 5><SCENE 1><96%>
	If not in heaven, you'll surely sup in hell.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	So, lie thou there;
	For underneath an alehouse' paltry sign,
	The Castle in Saint Alban's, Somerset
	Hath made the wizard famous in his death.
	Sword, hold thy temper; heart, be wrathful still:
	Priests pray for enemies, but princes kill.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 5><SCENE 3><99%>
	My noble father,
	Three times to-day I holp him to his horse,
	Three times bestrid him; thrice I led him off,
	Persuaded him from any further act:
	But still, where danger was, still there I met him;
	And like rich hangings in a homely house,
	So was his will in his old feeble body.
	But, noble as he is, look where he comes.
