<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><8%>
	Is it not yours?
	What ever have been thought on in this state,
	That could be brought to bodily act ere Rome
	Had circumvention? 'Tis not four days gone
	Since I heard thence; these are the words: I think
	I have the letter here; yes, here it is.
	They have press'd a power, but it is not known
	Whether for east, or west: the dearth is great;
	The people mutinous; and it is rumour'd,
	Cominius, Marcius, your old enemy,—
	Who is of Rome worse hated than of you,—
	And Titus Lartius, a most valiant Roman,
	These three lead on this preparation
	Whither 'tis bent: most likely 'tis for you:
	Consider of it.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	Nor did you think it folly
	To keep your great pretences veil'd till when
	They needs must show themselves; which in the hatching,
	It seem'd, appear'd to Rome. By the discovery
	We shall be shorten'd in our aim, which was
	To take in many towns ere almost Rome
	Should know we were afoot.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	O! doubt not that;
	I speak from certainties. Nay, more;
	Some parcels of their power are forth already,
	And only hitherward. I leave your honours.
	If we and Caius Marcius chance to meet,
	'Tis sworn between us we shall ever strike
	Till one can do no more.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><9%>
	And keep your honours safe!
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 8><19%>
	We hate alike:
	Not Afric owns a serpent I abhor
	More than thy fame and envy. Fix thy foot.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 8><19%>
	If I fly, Marcius,
	Halloo me like a hare.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 8><20%>
	Wert thou the Hector
	That was the whip of your bragg'd progeny,
	Thou shouldst not 'scape me here.—
	Officious, and not valiant, you have sham'd me
	In your condemned seconds.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE X.— ><23%>
	The town is ta'en!
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE X.— ><23%>
	Condition!
	I would I were a Roman; for I cannot,
	Being a Volsce, be that I am. Condition!
	What good condition can a treaty find
	I' the part that is at mercy? Five times, Marcius,
	I have fought with thee; so often hast thou beat me,
	And wouldst do so, I think, should we encounter
	As often as we eat. By the elements,
	If e'er again I meet him beard to beard,
	He is mine, or I am his: mine emulation
	Hath not that honour in't it had; for where
	I thought to crush him in an equal force—
	True sword to sword—I'll potch at him some way
	Or wrath or craft may get him.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE X.— ><23%>
	Bolder, though not so subtle. My valour's poison'd
	With only suffering stain by him; for him
	Shall fly out of itself. Nor sleep nor sanctuary,
	Being naked, sick, nor fane nor Capitol,
	The prayers of priests, nor times of sacrifice,
	Embarquements all of fury, shall lift up
	Their rotten privilege and custom 'gainst
	My hate to Marcius. Where I find him, were it
	At home, upon my brother's guard, even there
	Against the hospitable canon, would I
	Wash my fierce hand in 's heart. Go you to the city;
	Learn how 'tis held, and what they are that must
	Be hostages for Rome.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE X.— ><24%>
	I am attended at the cypress grove: I pray you—
	'Tis south the city mills—bring me word thither
	How the world goes, that to the pace of it
	I may spur on my journey.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	Where is this fellow?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	Whence com'st thou? what wouldst thou? Thy name?
	Why speak'st not? Speak, man: what's thy name?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	What is thy name?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	Say, what's thy name?
	Thou hast a grim appearance, and thy face
	Bears a command in 't; though thy tackle's torn,
	Thou show'st a noble vessel. What's thy name?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 5><70%>
	I know thee not. Thy name?
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 5><71%>
	O Marcius, Marcius!
	Each word thou hast spoke hath weeded from my heart
	A root of ancient envy. If Jupiter
	Should from yond cloud speak divine things,
	And say, ''Tis true,' I'd not believe them more
	Than thee, all noble Marcius. Let me twine
	Mine arms about that body, where against
	My grained ash a hundred times hath broke,
	And scarr'd the moon with splinters: here I clip
	The anvil of my sword, and do contest
	As hotly and as nobly with thy love
	As ever in ambitious strength I did
	Contend against thy valour. Know thou first,
	I lov'd the maid I married; never man
	Sigh'd truer breath; but that I see thee here,
	Thou noble thing! more dances my rapt heart
	Than when I first my wedded mistress saw
	Bestride my threshold. Why, thou Mars! I tell thee,
	We have a power on foot; and I had purpose
	Once more to hew thy target from thy brawn,
	Or lose mine arm for 't. Thou hast beat me out
	Twelve several times, and I have nightly since
	Dreamt of encounters 'twixt thyself and me;
	We have been down together in my sleep,
	Unbuckling helms, fisting each other's throat,
	And wak'd half dead with nothing. Worthy Marcius,
	Had we no quarrel else to Rome, but that
	Thou art thence banish'd, we would muster all
	From twelve to seventy, and, pouring war
	Into the bowels of ungrateful Rome,
	Like a bold flood o'er-bear. O! come; go in,
	And take our friendly senators by the hands,
	Who now are here, taking their leaves of me,
	Who am prepar'd against your territories,
	Though not for Rome itself.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 5><72%>
	Therefore, most absolute sir, if thou wilt have
	The leading of thine own revenges, take
	The one half of my commission, and set down,
	As best thou art experienc'd, since thou know'st
	Thy country's strength and weakness, thine own ways;
	Whether to knock against the gates of Rome,
	Or rudely visit them in parts remote,
	To fright them, ere destroy. But come in:
	Let me commend thee first to those that shall
	Say yea to thy desires. A thousand welcomes!
	And more a friend than e'er an enemy;
	Yet, Marcius, that was much. Your hand: most welcome!
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 7><80%>
	Do they still fly to the Roman?
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 7><80%>
	I cannot help it now,
	Unless, by using means, I lame the foot
	Of our design. He bears himself more proudlier,
	Even to my person, than I thought he would
	When first I did embrace him; yet his nature
	In that's no changeling, and I must excuse
	What cannot be amended.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 4><SCENE 7><80%>
	I understand thee well; and be thou sure,
	When he shall come to his account, he knows not
	What I can urge against him. Although it seems,
	And so he thinks, and is no less apparent
	To the vulgar eye, that he bears all things fairly,
	And shows good husbandry for the Volscian state,
	Fights dragon-like, and does achieve as soon
	As draw his sword; yet he hath left undone
	That which shall break his neck or hazard mine,
	Whene'er we come to our account.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 7><81%>
	All places yield to him ere he sits down;
	And the nobility of Rome are his:
	The senators and patricians love him too:
	The tribunes are no soldiers; and their people
	Will be as rash in the repeal as hasty
	To expel him thence. I think he'll be to Rome
	As is the osprey to the fish, who takes it
	By sovereignty of nature. First he was
	A noble servant to them, but he could not
	Carry his honours even; whether 'twas pride,
	Which out of daily fortune ever taints
	The happy man; whether defect of judgment,
	To fail in the disposing of those chances
	Which he was lord of; or whether nature,
	Not to be other than one thing, not moving
	From the casque to the cushion, but commanding peace
	Even with the same austerity and garb
	As he controll'd the war; but one of these,
	As he hath spices of them all, not all,
	For I dare so far free him, made him fear'd,
	So hated, and so banish'd: but he has a merit
	To choke it in the utterance. So our virtues
	Lie in the interpretation of the time;
	And power, unto itself most commendable,
	Hath not a tomb so evident as a chair
	To extol what it hath done.
	One fire drives out one fire; one nail, one nail;
	Rights by rights falter, strengths by strengths do fail.
	Come, let's away. When, Caius, Rome is thine,
	Thou art poor'st of all; then shortly art thou mine.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	You keep a constant temper.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 5><SCENE 3><87%>
	Only their ends
	You have respected; stopp'd your ears against
	The general suit of Rome; never admitted
	A private whisper; no, not with such friends
	That thought them sure of you.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 5><SCENE 3><92%>
	I was mov'd withal.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 5><SCENE 3><93%>
	</STAGE DIR> I am glad thou hast set thy mercy and thy honour
	At difference in thee: out of that I'll work
	Myself a former fortune.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 5><SCENE 5><95%>
	Go tell the lords o' the city I am here:
	Deliver them this paper: having read it,
	Bid them repair to the market-place; where I,
	Even in theirs and in the commons' ears,
	Will vouch the truth of it. Him I accuse
	The city ports by this hath enter'd, and
	Intends to appear before the people, hoping
	To purge himself with words: dispatch.
	Most welcome!
<SPEECH 28><ACT 5><SCENE 5><96%>
	Even so
	As with a man by his own alms empoison'd,
	And with his charity slain.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 5><SCENE 5><96%>
	Sir, I cannot tell:
	We must proceed as we do find the people.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 5><SCENE 5><96%>
	I know it;
	And my pretext to strike at him admits
	A good construction. I rais'd him, and I pawn'd
	Mine honour for his truth: who being so heighten'd,
	He water'd his new plants with dews of flattery,
	Seducing so my friends; and, to this end,
	He bow'd his nature, never known before
	But to be rough, unswayable, and free.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 5><SCENE 5><96%>
	That I would have spoke of:
	Being banish'd for't, he came unto my hearth;
	Presented to my knife his throat: I took him;
	Made him joint-servant with me; gave him way
	In all his own desires; nay, let him choose
	Out of my files, his projects to accomplish,
	My best and freshest men; serv'd his designments
	In mine own person; holp to reap the fame
	Which he did end all his; and took some pride
	To do myself this wrong: till, at the last,
	I seem'd his follower, not partner; and
	He wag'd me with his countenance, as if
	I had been mercenary.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	There was it;
	For which my sinews shall be stretch'd upon him.
	At a few drops of women's rheum, which are
	As cheap as lies, he sold the blood and labour
	Of our great action: therefore shall he die,
	And I'll renew me in his fall. But, hark!
<SPEECH 33><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	Say no more:
	Here come the lords.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	I have not deserv'd it.
	But, worthy lords, have you with heed perus'd
	What I have written to you?
<SPEECH 35><ACT 5><SCENE 5><97%>
	He approaches: you shall hear him.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 5><SCENE 5><98%>
	Read it not, noble lords;
	But tell the traitor in the highest degree
	He hath abus'd your powers.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 5><SCENE 5><98%>
	Ay, traitor, Marcius.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 5><SCENE 5><98%>
	Ay, Marcius, Caius Marcius. Dost thou think
	I'll grace thee with that robbery, thy stol'n name
	Coriolanus in Corioli?
	You lords and heads of the state, perfidiously
	He has betray'd your business, and given up,
	For certain drops of salt, your city Rome,
	I say 'your city,' to his wife and mother;
	Breaking his oath and resolution like
	A twist of rotten silk, never admitting
	Counsel o' the war, but at his nurse's tears
	He whin'd and roar'd away your victory,
	That pages blush'd at him, and men of heart
	Look'd wondering each at other.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 5><SCENE 5><98%>
	Name not the god, thou boy of tears.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 5><SCENE 5><98%>
	No more.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	Why, noble lords,
	Will you be put in mind of his blind fortune,
	Which was your shame, by this unholy braggart,
	'Fore your own eyes and ears?
<SPEECH 42><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	Insolent villain!
<SPEECH 43><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	My noble masters, hear me speak.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 5><SCENE 5><99%>
	My lords, when you shall know,—as in this rage,
	Provok'd by him, you cannot,—the great danger
	Which this man's life did owe you, you'll rejoice
	That he is thus cut off. Please it your honours
	To call me to your senate, I'll deliver
	Myself your loyal servant, or endure
	Your heaviest censure.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 5><SCENE 5><100%>
	My rage is gone,
	And I am struck with sorrow. Take him up:
	Help, three o' the chiefest soldiers; I'll be one.
	Beat thou the drum, that it speak mournfully;
	Trail your steel pikes. Though in this city he
	Hath widow'd and unchilded many a one,
	Which to this hour bewail the injury,
	Yet he shall have a noble memory.
	Assist.
