<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	He has no equal.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	Mark'd you his lip and eyes?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	Being mov'd, he will not spare to gird the gods.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	The present wars devour him; he is grown
	Too proud to be so valiant.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	Fame, at the which he aims,
	In whom already he is well grac'd, cannot
	Better be held nor more attain'd than by
	A place below the first; for what miscarries
	Shall be the general's fault, though he perform
	To the utmost of a man; and giddy censure
	Will then cry out of Marcius 'O! if he
	Had borne the business.'
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	Come:
	Half all Cominius' honours are to Marcius,
	Though Marcius earn'd them not; and all his faults
	To Marcius shall be honours, though indeed
	In aught he merit not.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><8%>
	Let's along.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Good or bad?
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	He's a lamb indeed, that baes like a bear.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	Well, sir.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	He's poor in no one fault, but stored with all.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	And topping all others in boasting.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	We do it not alone, sir.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	What then, sir?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><25%>
	Come, sir, come, we know you well enough.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Come, come, you are well understood to be a perfecter giber for the table than a necessary bencher in the Capitol.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	All tongues speak of him, and the bleared sights
	Are spectacled to see him: your prattling nurse
	Into a rapture lets her baby cry
	While she chats him: the kitchen malkin pins
	Her richest lockram 'bout her reechy neck,
	Clambering the walls to eye him: stalls, bulks, windows,
	Are smother'd up, leads fill'd, and ridges hors'd
	With variable complexions, all agreeing
	In earnestness to see him: seld-shown flamens
	Do press among the popular throngs, and puff
	To win a vulgar station: our veil'd dames
	Commit the war of white and damask in
	Their nicely-gawded cheeks to the wanton spoil
	Of Phœbus' burning kisses: such a pother
	As if that whatsoever god who leads him
	Were slily crept into his human powers,
	And gave him graceful posture.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	Then our office may,
	During his power, go sleep.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	In that there's comfort.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	I heard him swear,
	Were he to stand for consul, never would he
	Appear i' the market-place, nor on him put
	The napless vesture of humility;
	Nor, showing, as the manner is, his wounds
	To the people, beg their stinking breaths.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 1><30%>
	It was his word. O! he would miss it rather
	Than carry it but by the suit o' the gentry to him
	And the desire of the nobles.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	'Tis most like he will.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	So it must fall out
	To him or our authorities. For an end,
	We must suggest the people in what hatred
	He still hath held them; that to his power he would
	Have made them mules, silenc'd their pleaders, and
	Dispropertied their freedoms; holding them,
	In human action and capacity,
	Of no more soul nor fitness for the world
	Than camels in the war; who have their provand
	Only for bearing burdens, and sore blows
	For sinking under them.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	What's the matter?
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 1><31%>
	Let's to the Capitol;
	And carry with us ears and eyes for the time,
	But hearts for the event.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Which the rather
	We shall be bless'd to do, if he remember
	A kinder value of the people than
	He hath hereto priz'd them at.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Most willingly;
	But yet my caution was more pertinent
	Than the rebuke you give it.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	Sir, I hope
	My words disbench'd you not.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	</STAGE DIR> Mark you that?
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	You see how he intends to use the people.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 2><36%>
	Come; we'll inform them
	Of our proceedings here: on the market-place
	I know they do attend us.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 3><41%>
	We stay here for the people.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 3><41%>
	With a proud heart he wore
	His humble weeds. Will you dismiss the people?
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 3><41%>
	We pray the gods he may deserve your love.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 3><41%>
	Could you not have told him
	As you were lesson'd, when he had no power,
	But was a petty servant to the state,
	He was your enemy, ever spake against
	Your liberties and the charters that you bear
	I' the body of the weal; and now, arriving
	A place of potency and sway o' the state,
	If he should still malignantly remain
	Fast foe to the plebeii, your voices might
	Be curses to yourselves? You should have said
	That as his worthy deeds did claim no less
	Than what he stood for, so his gracious nature
	Would think upon you for your voices and
	Translate his malice towards you into love,
	Standing your friendly lord.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 3><42%>
	Did you perceive
	He did solicit you in free contempt
	When he did need your loves, and do you think
	That his contempt shall not be bruising to you
	When he hath power to crush? Why, had your bodies
	No heart among you? or had you tongues to cry
	Against the rectorship of judgment?
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 3><42%>
	Get you hence instantly, and tell those friends,
	They have chose a consul that will from them take
	Their liberties; make them of no more voice
	Than dogs that are as often beat for barking
	As therefore kept to do so.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 3><43%>
	Lay
	A fault on us, your tribunes; that we labour'd,—
	No impediment between,—but that you must
	Cast your election on him.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 3><43%>
	Ay, spare us not. Say we read lectures to you,
	How youngly he began to serve his country,
	How long continu'd, and what stock he springs of,
	The noble house o' the Marcians, from whence came
	That Ancus Marcius, Numa's daughter's son,
	Who, after great Hostilius, here was king;
	Of the same house Publius and Quintus were,
	That our best water brought by conduits hither;
	And Censorinus, that was so surnam'd,—
	And nobly nam'd so, twice being censor,—
	Was his great ancestor.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 3><44%>
	Say you ne'er had done 't—
	Harp on that still—but by our putting on;
	And presently, when you have drawn your number,
	Repair to the Capitol.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 3><44%>
	Let them go on;
	This mutiny were better put in hazard
	Than stay, past doubt, for greater.
	If, as his nature is, he fall in rage
	With their refusal, both observe and answer
	The vantage of his anger.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	It will be dangerous to go on: no further.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Cominius, no.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	The people are incens'd against him.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Call't not a plot:
	The people cry you mock'd them, and of late,
	When corn was given them gratis, you repin'd;
	Scandall'd the suppliants for the people, call'd them
	Time-pleasers, flatterers, foes to nobleness.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Not to them all.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	How! I inform them!
<SPEECH 48><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Not unlike,
	Each way, to better yours.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	You speak o' the people,
	As if you were a god to punish, not
	A man of their infirmity.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Why, shall the people give
	One that speaks thus their voice?
<SPEECH 51><ACT 3><SCENE 1><48%>
	Enough, with over-measure.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	He has said enough.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Manifest treason!
<SPEECH 54><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	The ædiles, ho! Let him be apprehended.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Seize him, ædiles!
<SPEECH 56><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	By the consent of all, we were establish'd
	The people's magistrates.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	Or let us stand to our authority,
	Or let us lose it. We do here pronounce,
	Upon the part o' the people, in whose power
	We were elected theirs, Marcius is worthy
	Of present death.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	Ædiles, seize him!
<SPEECH 59><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	Sir, those cold ways,
	That seem like prudent helps, are very poisonous
	Where the disease is violent. Lay hands upon him,
	And bear him to the rock.
<SPEECH 60><ACT 3><SCENE 1><51%>
	Lay hands upon him.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 3><SCENE 1><52%>
	He consul!
<SPEECH 62><ACT 3><SCENE 1><53%>
	Merely awry: when he did love his country
	It honour'd him.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 3><SCENE 1><53%>
	We'll hear no more.
	Pursue him to his house, and pluck him thence,
	Lest his infection, being of catching nature,
	Spread further.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 3><SCENE 1><53%>
	If 'twere so,—
<SPEECH 65><ACT 3><SCENE 1><54%>
	Go not home.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	In this point charge him home, that he affects
	Tyrannical power: if he evade us there,
	Enforce him with his envy to the people,
	And that the spoil got on the Antiates
	Was ne'er distributed.—
	What, will he come?
<SPEECH 67><ACT 3><SCENE 3><58%>
	How accompanied?
<SPEECH 68><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	And when such time they have begun to cry,
	Let them not cease, but with a din confus'd
	Enforce the present execution
	Of what we chance to sentence.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 3><SCENE 3><59%>
	Go about it.
	Put him to choler straight. He hath been us'd
	Ever to conquer, and to have his worth
	Of contradiction: being once chaf'd, he cannot
	Be rein'd again to temperance; then he speaks
	What's in his heart; and that is there which looks
	With us to break his neck.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 3><SCENE 3><61%>
	But since he hath
	Serv'd well for Rome,—
<SPEECH 71><ACT 3><SCENE 3><61%>
	I talk of that, that know it.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 3><SCENE 3><62%>
	There's no more to be said, but he is banish'd,
	As enemy to the people and his country:
	It shall be so.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	Now we have shown our power,
	Let us seem humbler after it is done
	Than when it was a-doing.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	Dismiss them home.
	Here comes his mother.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 4><SCENE 2><65%>
	Why?
<SPEECH 76><ACT 4><SCENE 2><65%>
	They have ta'en note of us: keep on your way.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 4><SCENE 2><65%>
	I would he had.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 4><SCENE 2><65%>
	Pray, let us go.
<SPEECH 79><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	Well, well, we'll leave you.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 4><SCENE 6><75%>
	We stood to 't in good time. Is this Menenius?
<SPEECH 81><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	Good den to you all, good den to you all.
<SPEECH 82><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	Farewell, kind neighbours: we wish'd Coriolanus
	Had lov'd you as we did.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	Farewell, farewell.
<SPEECH 84><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	Caius Marcius was
	A worthy officer i' the war; but insolent,
	O'ercome with pride, ambitious past all thinking,
	Self-loving,—
<SPEECH 85><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	The gods have well prevented it, and Rome
	Sits safe and still without him.
<SPEECH 86><ACT 4><SCENE 6><77%>
	Go see this rumourer whipp'd. It cannot be
	The Volsces dare break with us.
<SPEECH 87><ACT 4><SCENE 6><77%>
	Not possible.
<SPEECH 88><ACT 4><SCENE 6><77%>
	Rais'd only, that the weaker sort may wish
	Good Marcius home again.
<SPEECH 89><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	But is this true, sir?
<SPEECH 90><ACT 4><SCENE 6><79%>
	Say not we brought it.
<SPEECH 91><ACT 4><SCENE 6><80%>
	I do not like this news.
<SPEECH 92><ACT 4><SCENE 6><80%>
	Let's to the Capitol. Would half my wealth
	Would buy this for a lie!
<SPEECH 93><ACT 5><SCENE 1><83%>
	Only make trial what your love can do
	For Rome, towards Marcius.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 5><SCENE 1><83%>
	You know the very road into his kindness,
	And cannot lose your way.
