<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	You have fought together.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	It is your former promise.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Noble Marcius!
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 6><16%>
	Breathe you, my friends: well fought; we are come off
	Like Romans, neither foolish in our stands,
	Nor cowardly in retire: believe me, sirs,
	We shall be charg'd again. Whiles we have struck,
	By interims and conveying gusts we have heard
	The charges of our friends. Ye Roman gods!
	Lead their successes as we wish our own,
	That both our powers, with smiling fronts encountering,
	May give you thankful sacrifice.
	Thy news?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	Though thou speak'st truth,
	Methinks thou speak'st not well. How long is't since?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	'Tis not a mile; briefly we heard their drums:
	How couldst thou in a mile confound an hour,
	And bring thy news so late?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	Who's yonder,
	That does appear as he were flay'd? O gods!
	He has the stamp of Marcius; and I have
	Before-time seen him thus.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	The shepherd knows not thunder from a tabor,
	More than I know the sound of Marcius' tongue
	From every meaner man.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	Ay, if you come not in the blood of others,
	But mantled in your own.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	Flower of warriors.
	How is't with Titus Lartius?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	Where is that slave
	Which told me they had beat you to your trenches?
	Where is he? Call him hither.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	But how prevail'd you?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	Marcius, we have at disadvantage fought,
	And did retire to win our purpose.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	As I guess, Marcius,
	Their bands i' the vaward are the Antiates,
	Of their best trust; o'er them Aufidius,
	Their very heart of hope.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	Though I could wish
	You were conducted to a gentle bath,
	And balms applied to you, yet dare I never
	Deny your asking: take your choice of those
	That best can aid your action.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 6><19%>
	March on, my fellows:
	Make good this ostentation, and you shall
	Divide in all with us.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 1><20%>
	If I should tell thee o'er this thy day's work,
	Thou'lt not believe thy deeds: but I'll report it
	Where senators shall mingle tears with smiles,
	Where great patricians shall attend and shrug,
	I' the end, admire; where ladies shall be frighted,
	And, gladly quak'd, hear more; where the dull Tribunes,
	That, with the fusty plebeians, hate thine honours,
	Shall say, against their hearts,
	'We thank the gods our Rome hath such a soldier!'
	Yet cam'st thou to a morsel of this feast,
	Having fully din'd before.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 1><21%>
	You shall not be
	The grave of your deserving; Rome must know
	The value of her own: 'twere a concealment
	Worse than a theft, no less than a traducement,
	To hide your doings; and to silence that,
	Which, to the spire and top of praises vouch'd,
	Would seem but modest. Therefore, I beseech you,—
	In sign of what you are, not to reward
	What you have done,—before our army hear me.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 1><21%>
	Should they not.
	Well might they fester 'gainst ingratitude,
	And tent themselves with death. Of all the horses,
	Whereof we have ta'en good, and good store, of all
	The treasure, in this field achiev'd and city,
	We render you the tenth; to be ta'en forth,
	Before the common distribution,
	At your only choice.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 1><21%>
	Too modest are you;
	More cruel to your good report than grateful
	To us that give you truly. By your patience,
	If 'gainst yourself you be incens'd, we'll put you,
	Like one that means his proper harm, in manacles,
	Then reason safely with you. Therefore, be it known,
	As to us, to all the world, that Caius Marcius
	Wears this war's garland; in token of the which,
	My noble steed, known to the camp, I give him,
	With all his trim belonging; and from this time,
	For what he did before Corioli, call him,
	With all the applause and clamour of the host,
	<CAIUS MARCIUS CORIOLANUS! BEAR>The addition nobly ever!
<SPEECH 21><ACT 1><SCENE 1><22%>
	So, to our tent;
	Where, ere we do repose us, we will write
	To Rome of our success. You, Titus Lartius,
	Must to Corioli back: send us to Rome
	The best, with whom we may articulate,
	For their own good and ours.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 1><SCENE 1><22%>
	Take it; 'tis yours. What is't?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 1><SCENE 1><22%>
	O! well begg'd!
	Were he the butcher of my son, he should
	Be free as is the wind. Deliver him, Titus.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 1><SCENE 1><23%>
	Go we to our tent:
	The blood upon your visage dries; 'tis time
	It should be look'd to: come.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 1><28%>
	Look, sir, your mother!
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 1><29%>
	Ever right.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 1><29%>
	On, to the Capitol!
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	I shall lack voice: the deeds of Coriolanus
	Should not be utter'd feebly. It is held
	That valour is the chiefest virtue, and
	Most dignifies the haver: if it be,
	The man I speak of cannot in the world
	Be singly counterpois'd. At sixteen years,
	When Tarquin made a head for Rome, he fought
	Beyond the mark of others; our then dictator,
	Whom with all praise I point at, saw him fight,
	When with his Amazonian chin he drove
	The bristled lips before him. He bestrid
	An o'er-press'd Roman, and i' the consul's view
	Slew three opposers: Tarquin's self he met,
	And struck him on his knee: in that day's feats,
	When he might act the woman in the scene,
	He prov'd best man i' the field, and for his meed
	Was brow-bound with the oak. His pupil age
	Man-enter'd thus, he waxed like a sea,
	And in the brunt of seventeen battles since
	He lurch'd all swords of the garland. For this last,
	Before and in Corioli, let me say,
	I cannot speak him home: he stopp'd the fliers,
	And by his rare example made the coward
	Turn terror into sport: as weeds before
	A vessel under sail, so men obey'd,
	And fell below his stem: his sword, death's stamp,
	Where it did mark, it took; from face to foot
	He was a thing of blood, whose every motion
	Was tim'd with dying cries: alone he enter'd
	The mortal gate of the city, which he painted
	With shunless destiny; aidless came off,
	And with a sudden re-enforcement struck
	Corioli like a planet. Now all's his:
	When by and by the din of war 'gan pierce
	His ready sense; then straight his doubled spirit
	Re-quicken'd what in flesh was fatigate,
	And to the battle came he; where he did
	Run reeking o'er the lives of men, as if
	'Twere a perpetual spoil; and till we call'd
	Both field and city ours, he never stood
	To ease his breast with panting.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 2><35%>
	Our spoils he kick'd at,
	And look'd upon things precious as they were
	The common muck o' the world: he covets less
	Than misery itself would give; rewards
	His deeds with doing them, and is content
	To spend the time to end it.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	They are worn, lord consul, so,
	That we shall hardly in our ages see
	Their banners wave again.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Hath he not pass'd the noble and the common?
<SPEECH 32><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	The people are abus'd; set on. This paltering
	Becomes not Rome, nor has Coriolanus
	Deserv'd this so dishonour'd rub, laid falsely
	I' the plain way of his merit.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	'Twas from the canon.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	Well, on to the market-place.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 3><SCENE 1><49%>
	Aged sir, hands off.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 3><SCENE 1><50%>
	That is the way to lay the city flat;
	To bring the roof to the foundation,
	And bury all, which yet distinctly ranges,
	In heaps and piles of ruin.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 3><SCENE 1><51%>
	Come, sir, along with us.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 3><SCENE 1><51%>
	But now 'tis odds beyond arithmetic;
	And manhood is call'd foolery when it stands
	Against a falling fabric. Will you hence,
	Before the tag return? whose rage doth rend
	Like interrupted waters and o'erbear
	What they are us'd to bear.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 3><SCENE 1><51%>
	Nay, come away.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	I have been i' the market-place; and, sir, 'tis fit
	You make strong party, or defend yourself
	By calmness or by absence: all's in anger.
<SPEECH 41><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	I think 'twill serve if he
	Can thereto frame his spirit.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 3><SCENE 2><57%>
	Come, come, we'll prompt you.
<SPEECH 43><ACT 3><SCENE 2><58%>
	Away! the tribunes do attend you: arm yourself
	To answer mildly; for they are prepar'd
	With accusations, as I hear, more strong
	Than are upon you yet.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 3><SCENE 3><60%>
	Well, well; no more.
<SPEECH 45><ACT 3><SCENE 3><61%>
	Know, I pray you,—
<SPEECH 46><ACT 3><SCENE 3><61%>
	Hear me, my masters, and my common friends,—
<SPEECH 47><ACT 3><SCENE 3><61%>
	Let me speak:
	I have been consul, and can show for Rome
	Her enemies' marks upon me. I do love
	My country's good with a respect more tender,
	More holy, and profound, than mine own life,
	My dear wife's estimate, her womb's increase,
	And treasure of my loins; then if I would
	Speak that—
<SPEECH 48><ACT 4><SCENE 1><64%>
	I'll follow thee a month, devise with thee
	Where thou shalt rest, that thou mayst hear of us,
	And we of thee: so, if the time thrust forth
	A cause for thy repeal, we shall not send
	O'er the vast world to seek a single man,
	And lose advantage, which doth ever cool
	I' the absence of the needer.
<SPEECH 49><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	O! you have made good work!
<SPEECH 50><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	You have holp to ravish your own daughters; and
	To melt the city leads upon your pates.
	To see your wives dishonour'd to your noses,—
<SPEECH 51><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	Your temples burned in their cement, and
	Your franchises, whereon you stood, confin'd
	Into an auger's bore.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	If!
	He is their god: he leads them like a thing
	Made by some other deity than Nature,
	That shapes man better; and they follow him,
	Against us brats, with no less confidence
	Than boys pursuing summer butterflies,
	Or butchers killing flies.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	He will shake
	Your Rome about your ears.
<SPEECH 54><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	Ay; and you'll look pale
	Before you find it other. All the regions
	Do smilingly revolt; and who resist
	Are mock'd for valiant ignorance,
	And perish constant fools. Who is't can blame him?
	Your enemies, and his, find something in him.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	Who shall ask it?
	The tribunes cannot do't for shame; the people
	Deserve such pity of him as the wolf
	Does of the shepherds: for his best friends, if they
	Should say, 'Be good to Rome,' they charg'd him even
	As those should do that had deserv'd his hate,
	And therein show'd like enemies.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 4><SCENE 6><79%>
	You have brought
	A trembling upon Rome, such as was never
	So incapable of help.
<SPEECH 57><ACT 4><SCENE 6><79%>
	But I fear
	They'll roar him in again. Tullus Aufidius,
	The second name of men, obeys his points
	As if he were his officer: desperation
	Is all the policy, strength, and defence,
	That Rome can make against them.
<SPEECH 58><ACT 4><SCENE 6><80%>
	You're goodly things, you voices!
<SPEECH 59><ACT 4><SCENE 6><80%>
	O! ay; what else?
<SPEECH 60><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	He would not seem to know me.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	Yet one time he did call me by my name.
	I urg'd our old acquaintance, and the drops
	That we have bled together. Coriolanus
	He would not answer to; forbad all names;
	He was a kind of nothing, titleless,
	Till he had forg'd himself a name o' the fire
	Of burning Rome.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	I minded him how royal 'twas to pardon
	When it was less expected: he replied,
	It was a bare petition of a state
	To one whom they had punish'd.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 5><SCENE 1><82%>
	I offer'd to awaken his regard
	For's private friends: his answer to me was,
	He could not stay to pick them in a pile
	Of noisome musty chaff: he said 'twas folly,
	For one poor grain or two, to leave unburnt,
	And still to nose the offence.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 5><SCENE 1><83%>
	He'll never hear him.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 5><SCENE 1><83%>
	I tell you he does sit in gold, his eye
	Red as 'twould burn Rome, and his injury
	The gaoler to his pity. I kneel'd before him;
	'Twas very faintly he said 'Rise;' dismiss'd me
	Thus, with his speechless hand: what he would do
	He sent in writing after me; what he would not,
	Bound with an oath to yield to his conditions:
	So that all hope is vain
	Unless his noble mother and his wife,
	Who, as I hear, mean to solicit him
	For mercy to his country. Therefore let's hence,
	And with our fair entreaties haste them on.
