<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	Thanks.—What's the matter, you dissentious rogues,
	That, rubbing the poor itch of your opinion,
	Make yourselves scabs?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	He that will give good words to thee will flatter
	Beneath abhorring. What would you have, you curs,
	That like nor peace nor war? the one affrights you,
	The other makes you proud. He that trusts to you,
	Where he should find you lions, finds you hares;
	Where foxes, geese: you are no surer, no,
	Than is the coal of fire upon the ice,
	Or hailstone in the sun. Your virtue is,
	To make him worthy whose offence subdues him,
	And curse that justice did it. Who deserves greatness
	Deserves your hate; and your affections are
	A sick man's appetite, who desires most that
	Which would increase his evil. He that depends
	Upon your favours swims with fins of lead
	And hews down oaks with rushes. Hang ye! Trust ye?
	With every minute you do change a mind,
	And call him noble that was now your hate,
	Him vile that was your garland. What's the matter,
	That in these several places of the city
	You cry against the noble senate, who,
	Under the gods, keep you in awe, which else
	Would feed on one another? What's their seeking?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	Hang 'em! They say!
	They'll sit by the fire, and presume to know
	What's done i' the Capitol; who's like to rise,
	Who thrives, and who declines; side factions, and give out
	Conjectural marriages; making parties strong,
	And feebling such as stand not in their liking,
	Below their cobbled shoes. They say there's grain enough!
	Would the nobility lay aside their ruth,
	And let me use my sword, I'd make a quarry
	With thousands of these quarter'd slaves, as high
	As I could pick my lance.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	They are dissolv'd: hang 'em!
	They said they were an-hungry; sigh'd forth proverbs:
	That hunger broke stone walls; that dogs must eat;
	That meat was made for mouths; that the gods sent not
	Corn for the rich men only. With these shreds
	They vented their complainings; which being answer'd,
	And a petition granted them, a strange one,—
	To break the heart of generosity,
	And make bold power look pale,—they threw their caps
	As they would hang them on the horns o' the moon,
	Shouting their emulation.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Five tribunes to defend their vulgar wisdoms,
	Of their own choice: one's Junius Brutus,
	Sicinius Velutus, and I know not—'Sdeath!
	The rabble should have first unroof'd the city,
	Ere so prevail'd with me; it will in time
	Win upon power, and throw forth greater themes
	For insurrection's arguing.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Go; get you home, you fragments!
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Here: what's the matter?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	I am glad on't; then we shall ha' means to vent
	Our musty superfluity. See, our best elders.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	They have a leader,
	Tullus Aufidius, that will put you to't.
	I sin in envying his nobility,
	And were I anything but what I am,
	I would wish me only he.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Were half to half the world by the ears, and he
	Upon my party, I'd revolt, to make
	Only my wars with him: he is a lion
	That I am proud to hunt.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Sir, it is;
	And I am constant. Titus Lartius, thou
	Shalt see me once more strike at Tullus' face.
	What! art thou stiff? stand'st out?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	Nay, let them follow:
	The Volsces have much corn; take these rats thither
	To gnaw their garners. Worshipful mutiners,
	Your valour puts well forth; pray, follow.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	Yonder comes news: a wager they have met.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	'Tis done.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	Say, has our general met the enemy?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	I'll buy him of you.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	How far off lie these armies?
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 4><13%>
	Then shall we hear their 'larum, and they ours.
	Now, Mars, I prithee, make us quick in work,
	That we with smoking swords may march from hence,
	To help our fielded friends! Come, blow thy blast.
	Tullus Aufidius, is he within your walls?
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 4><14%>
	O! they are at it!
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 4><14%>
	They fear us not, but issue forth their city.
	Now put your shields before your hearts, and fight
	With hearts more proof than shields. Advance, brave Titus:
	They do disdain us much beyond our thoughts,
	Which makes me sweat with wrath. Come on, my fellows:
	He that retires, I'll take him for a Volsce,
	And he shall feel mine edge.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 1><SCENE 4><14%>
	All the contagion of the south light on you,
	You shames of Rome! you herd of—Boils and plagues
	Plaster you o'er, that you may be abhorr'd
	Further than seen, and one infect another
	Against the wind a mile! You souls of geese,
	That bear the shapes of men, how have you run
	From slaves that apes would beat! Pluto and hell!
	All hurt behind; backs red, and faces pale
	With flight and agu'd fear! Mend and charge home,
	Or, by the fires of heaven, I'll leave the foe
	And make my wars on you; look to 't: come on;
	If you'll stand fast, we'll beat them to their wives,
	As they us to our trenches follow'd.
	So, now the gates are ope: now prove good seconds:
	'Tis for the followers Fortune widens them,
	Not for the fliers: mark me, and do the like.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 1><SCENE 5><15%>
	See here these movers that do prize their hours
	At a crack'd drachme! Cushions, leaden spoons,
	Irons of a doit, doublets that hangmen would
	Bury with those that wore them, these base slaves,
	Ere yet the fight be done, pack up. Down with them!
	And hark, what noise the general makes! To him!
	There is the man of my soul's hate, Aufidius,
	Piercing our Romans: then, valiant Titus, take
	Convenient numbers to make good the city,
	Whilst I, with those that have the spirit, will haste
	To help Cominius.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 1><SCENE 5><16%>
	Sir, praise me not;
	My work hath yet not warm'd me: fare you well:
	The blood I drop is rather physical
	Than dangerous to me: to Aufidius thus
	I will appear, and fight.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 1><SCENE 5><16%>
	Thy friend no less
	Than those she places highest! So, farewell.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	</STAGE DIR> Come I too late?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	Come I too late?
<SPEECH 27><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	O! let me clip ye
	In arms as sound as when I woo'd, in heart
	As merry as when our nuptial day was done,
	And tapers burn'd to bedward.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	As with a man busied about decrees:
	Condemning some to death, and some to exile;
	Ransoming him, or pitying, threat'ning the other;
	Holding Corioli in the name of Rome,
	Even like a fawning greyhound in the leash,
	To let him slip at will.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 1><SCENE 6><17%>
	Let him alone;
	He did inform the truth: but for our gentlemen,
	The common file—a plague! tribunes for them!—
	The mouse ne'er shunn'd the cat as they did budge
	From rascals worse than they.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	Will the time serve to tell? I do not think.
	Where is the enemy? Are you lords o' the field?
	If not, why cease you till you are so?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	How lies their battle? Know you on which side
	They have plac'd their men of trust?
<SPEECH 32><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	I do beseech you,
	By all the battles wherein we have fought,
	By the blood we have shed together, by the vows
	We have made to endure friends, that you directly
	Set me against Aufidius and his Antiates;
	And that you not delay the present, but,
	Filling the air with swords advanc'd and darts,
	We prove this very hour.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 1><SCENE 6><18%>
	Those are they
	That most are willing. If any such be here—
	As it were sin to doubt—that love this painting
	Wherein you see me smear'd; if any fear
	Lesser his person than an ill report;
	If any think brave death outweighs bad life,
	And that his country's dearer than himself;
	Let him, alone, or so many so minded,
	Wave thus, to express his disposition,
	And follow Marcius.
	O! me alone? Make you a sword of me?
	If these shows be not outward, which of you
	But is four Volsces? None of you but is
	Able to bear against the great Aufidius
	A shield as hard as his. A certain number,
	Though thanks to all, must I select from all: the rest
	Shall bear the business in some other fight,
	As cause will be obey'd. Please you to march;
	And four shall quickly draw out my command,
	Which men are best inclin'd.
<SPEECH 34><ACT 1><SCENE 8><19%>
	I'll fight with none but thee; for I do hate thee
	Worse than a promise-breaker.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 1><SCENE 8><19%>
	Let the first budger die the other's slave,
	And the gods doom him after!
<SPEECH 36><ACT 1><SCENE 8><19%>
	Within these three hours, Tullus,
	Alone I fought in your Corioli walls,
	And made what work I pleas'd; 'tis not my blood
	Wherein thou seest me mask'd; for thy revenge
	Wrench up thy power to the highest.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 1><SCENE 1><20%>
	Pray now, no more: my mother,
	Who has a charter to extol her blood,
	When she does praise me grieves me. I have done
	As you have done; that's what I can; induc'd
	As you have been; that's for my country:
	He that has but effected his good will
	Hath overta'en mine act.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 1><SCENE 1><21%>
	I have some wounds upon me, and they smart
	To hear themselves remember'd.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 1><SCENE 1><21%>
	I thank you, general;
	But cannot make my heart consent to take
	A bribe to pay my sword: I do refuse it;
	And stand upon my common part with those
	That have beheld the doing.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 1><SCENE 1><21%>
	May these same instruments, which you profane,
	Never sound more! When drums and trumpets shall
	I' the field prove flatterers, let courts and cities be
	Made all of false-fac'd soothing!
	When steel grows soft as is the parasite's silk,
	Let him be made a coverture for the wars!
	No more, I say! For that I have not wash'd
	My nose that bled, or foil'd some debile wretch,
	Which, without note, here's many else have done,
	You shout me forth
	In acclamations hyperbolical;
	As if I lov'd my little should be dieted
	In praises sauc'd with lies.
