<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><1%>
	A strange beginning; 'borrow'd majesty!'
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	What now, my son! have I not ever said
	How that ambitious Constance would not cease
	Till she had kindled France and all the world
	Upon the right and party of her son?
	This might have been prevented and made whole
	With very easy arguments of love,
	Which now the manage of two kingdoms must
	With fearful bloody issue arbitrate.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><2%>
	Your strong possession much more than your right,
	Or else it must go wrong, with you and me:
	So much my conscience whispers in your ear,
	Which none but heaven and you and I shall hear.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	Out on thee, rude man! thou dost shame thy mother
	And wound her honour with this diffidence.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	He hath a trick of Cœur-de-Lion's face;
	The accent of his tongue affecteth him.
	Do you not read some tokens of my son
	In the large composition of this man?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Whe'r hadst thou rather be a Faulconbridge
	And like thy brother, to enjoy thy land,
	Or the reputed son of Cœur-de-Lion,
	Lord of thy presence and no land beside?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	I like thee well: wilt thou forsake thy fortune,
	Bequeath thy land to him, and follow me?
	I am a soldier and now bound to France.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 1><6%>
	Nay, I would have you go before me thither.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 1><7%>
	The very spirit of Plantagenet!
	I am thy grandam, Richard: call me so.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	Who is it thou dost call usurper, France?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	Out, insolent! thy bastard shall be king,
	That thou mayst be a queen, and check the world!
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><16%>
	There's a good mother, boy, that blots thy father.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	Come to thy grandam, child.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><17%>
	His mother shames him so, poor boy, he weeps.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	Thou monstrous slanderer of heaven and earth!
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><18%>
	Thou unadvised scold, I can produce
	A will that bars the title of thy son.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><29%>
	</STAGE DIR> Son, list to this conjunction, make this match;
	Give with our niece a dowry large enough;
	For by this knot thou shalt so surely tie
	Thy now unsur'd assurance to the crown,
	That yon green boy shall have no sun to ripe
	The bloom that promiseth a mighty fruit.
	I see a yielding in the looks of France;
	Mark how they whisper: urge them while their souls
	Are capable of this ambition,
	Lest zeal, now melted by the windy breath
	Of soft petitions, pity and remorse,
	Cool and congeal again to what it was.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 1><41%>
	Look'st thou pale, France? do not let go thy hand.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	O foul revolt of French inconstancy!
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 3><48%>
	Farewell, gentle cousin.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 3><48%>
	Come hither, little kinsman; hark, a word.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 3><SCENE 3><50%>
	My blessing go with thee!
