<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 2><63%>
	This 'once again,' but that your highness pleas'd,
	Was once superfluous: you were crown'd before,
	And that high royalty was ne'er pluck'd off,
	The faiths of men ne'er stained with revolt;
	Fresh expectation troubled not the land
	With any long'd-for change or better state.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	But that your royal pleasure must be done,
	This act is as an ancient tale new told,
	And in the last repeating troublesome,
	Being urged at a time unseasonable.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 2><64%>
	When workmen strive to do better than well
	They do confound their skill in covetousness;
	And oftentimes excusing of a fault
	Doth make the fault the worse by the excuse:
	As patches set upon a little breach
	Discredit more in hiding of the fault
	Than did the fault before it was so patch'd.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 2><65%>
	Then I,—as one that am the tongue of these
	To sound the purposes of all their hearts,—
	Both for myself and them,—but, chief of all,
	Your safety, for the which myself and them
	Bend their best studies,—heartily request
	The enfranchisement of Arthur; whose restraint
	Doth move the murmuring lips of discontent
	To break into this dangerous argument:
	If what in rest you have in right you hold,
	Why then your fears,—which, as they say, attend
	The steps of wrong,—should move you to mew up
	Your tender kinsman, and to choke his days
	With barbarous ignorance, and deny his youth
	The rich advantage of good exercise?
	That the time's enemies may not have this
	To grace occasions, let it be our suit
	That you have bid us ask, his liberty;
	Which for our goods we do no further ask
	Than whereupon our weal, on you depending,
	Counts it your weal he have his liberty.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	This is the man should do the bloody deed;
	He show'd his warrant to a friend of mine:
	The image of a wicked hemous fault
	Lives in his eye; that close aspect of his
	Does show the mood of a much troubled breast;
	And I do fearfully believe 'tis done,
	What we so fear'd he had a charge to do.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	And when it breaks, I fear will issue thence
	The foul corruption of a sweet child's death.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 4><SCENE 2><66%>
	Indeed we heard how near his death he was
	Before the child himself felt he was sick:
	This must be answer'd, either here or hence.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 4><SCENE 2><67%>
	Stay yet, Lord Salisbury; I'll go with thee,
	And find the inheritance of this poor child,
	His little kingdom of a forced grave.
	That blood which ow'd the breadth of all this isle,
	Three foot of it doth hold: bad world the while!
	This must not be thus borne: this will break out
	To all our sorrows, and ere long I doubt.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 3><74%>
	Who brought that letter from the cardinal?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	Sir, sir, impatience hath his privilege.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	O death, made proud with pure and princely beauty!
	The earth had not a hole to hide this deed.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 3><75%>
	All murders past do stand excus'd in this:
	And this, so sole and so unmatchable,
	Shall give a holiness, a purity,
	To the yet unbegotten sin of times;
	And prove a deadly bloodshed but a jest,
	Exampled by this heinous spectacle.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 3><76%>
	Our souls religiously confirm thy words.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 4><SCENE 3><77%>
	Cut him to pieces.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 4><SCENE 3><78%>
	There tell the king he may inquire us out.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 5><SCENE 4><90%>
	Up once again; put spirit in the French:
	If they miscarry we miscarry too.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 5><SCENE 4><90%>
	They say King John, sore sick, hath left the field.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 5><SCENE 4><91%>
	It is the Count Melun.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 5><SCENE 7><96%>
	His highness yet doth speak; and holds belief
	That, being brought into the open air,
	It would allay the burning quality
	Of that fell poison which assaileth him.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 5><SCENE 7><96%>
	He is more patient
	Than when you left him: even now he sung.
