<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 1><3%>
	The son and heir to that same Faulconbridge.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	My gracious liege, when that my father liv'd,
	Your brother did employ my father much,—
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 1><4%>
	And once dispatch'd him in an embassy
	To Germany, there with the emperor
	To treat of high affairs touching that time.
	The advantage of his absence took the king,
	And in the mean time sojourn'd at my father's;
	Where how he did prevail I shame to speak,
	But truth is truth: large lengths of seas and shores
	Between my father and my mother lay,—
	As I have heard my father speak himself,—
	When this same lusty gentleman was got.
	Upon his death-bed he by will bequeath'd
	His lands to me, and took it on his death
	That this my mother's son was none of his;
	An if he were, he came into the world
	Full fourteen weeks before the course of time.
	Then, good my liege, let me have what is mine,
	My father's land, as was my father's will.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 1><5%>
	Shall then my father's will be of no force
	To dispossess that child which is not his?
