<SPEECH 1><ACT 5><SCENE 1><94%>
	My temple stands in Ephesus; hie thee thither,
	And do upon mine altar sacrifice.
	There, when my maiden priests are met together,
	Before the people all,
	Reveal how thou at sea didst lose thy wife;
	To mourn thy crosses, with thy daughter's, call
	And give them repetition to the life.
	Perform my bidding, or thou liv'st in woe;
	Do it, and happy; by my silver bow!
	Awake, and tell thy dream!
