<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 6><75%>
	How now! How a dozen of virginities?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 6><75%>
	You may so; 'tis the better for you that your resorters stand upon sound legs. How now! wholesome iniquity, have you that a man may deal withal, and defy the surgeon?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	If she'd do the deed of darkness, thou wouldst say.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	Well; call forth, call forth.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	What, prithee?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	That dignifies the renown of a bawd no less than it gives a good report to a number to be chaste.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	Faith, she would serve after a long voyage at sea. Well, there's for you; leave us.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 4><SCENE 6><76%>
	I beseech you do.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 6><77%>
	Ha' you done?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 6><77%>
	Go thy ways. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> Now, pretty one, how long have you been at this trade?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 6><77%>
	Why, I cannot name 't but I shall offend.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 6><77%>
	How long have you been of this profession?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 6><77%>
	Did you go to 't so young? Were you a gamester at five or at seven?
<SPEECH 14><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	Why, the house you dwell in proclaims you to be a creature of sale.
<SPEECH 15><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	Why, hath your principal made known unto you who I am?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	Why, your herb-woman; she that sets seeds and roots of shame and iniquity. O! you have heard something of my power, and so stand aloof for more serious wooing. But I protest to thee, pretty one, my authority shall not see thee, or else look friendly upon thee. Come, bring me to some private place; come, come.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 6><78%>
	How's this? how's this? Some more; be sage.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 6><79%>
	I did not think
	Thou couldst have spoke so well; ne'er dream'd thou couldst.
	Had I brought hither a corrupted mind,
	Thy speech had alter'd it. Hold, here's gold for thee;
	Persever in that clear way thou goest,
	And the gods strengthen thee!
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 6><79%>
	For me, be you thoughten
	That I came with no ill intent, for to me
	The very doors and windows savour vilely.
	Farewell. Thou art a piece of virtue, and
	I doubt not but thy training hath been noble.
	Hold, here's more gold for thee.
	A curse upon him, die he like a thief,
	That robs thee of thy goodness! If thou dost
	Hear from me, it shall be for thy good.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 4><SCENE 6><79%>
	Avaunt! thou damned door-keeper. Your house,
	But for this virgin that doth prop it, would
	Sink and overwhelm you. Away!
<SPEECH 21><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	Hail, reverend sir! The gods preserve you!
<SPEECH 22><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	You wish me well.
	Being on shore, honouring of Neptune's triumphs,
	Seeing this goodly vessel ride before us,
	I made to it to know of whence you are.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	I am the governor of this place you lie before.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	Upon what ground is his distemperature?
<SPEECH 25><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	May we not see him?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	Yet let me obtain my wish.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	Sir king, all hail! the gods preserve you!
	Hall, royal sir!
<SPEECH 28><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	'Tis well bethought.
	She questionless with her sweet harmony
	And other chosen attractions, would allure,
	And make a battery through his deafen'd ports
	Which now are midway stopp'd:
	She is all happy as the fair'st of all,
	And with her fellow maids is now upon
	The leafy shelter that abuts against
	The island's side.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	O! sir, a courtesy,
	Which if we should deny, the most just gods
	For every graff would send a caterpillar,
	And so afflict our province. Yet once more
	Let me entreat to know at large the cause
	Of your king's sorrow.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	O! here is
	The lady that I sent for. Welcome, fair one!
	Is't not a goodly presence?
<SPEECH 31><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	She's such a one, that were I well assur'd
	Came of a gentle kind and noble stock,
	I'd wish no better choice, and think me rarely wed.
	Fair one, all goodness that consists in bounty
	Expect even here, where is a kingly patient:
	If that thy prosperous and artificial feat
	Can draw him but to answer thee in aught,
	Thy sacred physic shall receive such pay
	As thy desires can wish.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Come, let us leave her;
	And the gods make her prosperous!
<SPEECH 33><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	Mark'd he your music?
<SPEECH 34><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	See, she will speak to him.
<SPEECH 35><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	She never would tell
	Her parentage; being demanded that,
	She would sit still and weep.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	It is not good to cross him; give him way.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	My lord, I hear.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	A pillow for his head.
	So, leave him all. Well, my companion friends,
	If this but answer to my just belief,
	I'll well remember you.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 5><SCENE 1><95%>
	Sir,
	With all my heart; and when you come ashore,
	I have another suit.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 5><SCENE 1><95%>
	Sir, lend me your arm.
