<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 2><32%>
	Good grandam, tell us, is our father dead?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Why do you look on us, and shake your head,
	And call us orphans, wretches, castaways,
	If that our noble father be alive?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Then, grandam, you conclude that he is dead.
	The king mine uncle is to blame for it:
	God will revenge it; whom I will importune
	With earnest prayers all to that effect.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Grandam, we can; for my good uncle Gloucester
	Told me, the king, provok'd to't by the queen,
	Devis'd impeachments to imprison him:
	And when my uncle told me so, he wept,
	And pitied me, and kindly kiss'd my cheek;
	Bade me rely on him, as on my father,
	And he would love me dearly as his child.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	Think you my uncle did dissemble, grandam?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 2><33%>
	I cannot think it. Hark! what noise is this?
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 2><34%>
	Ah, aunt, you wept not for our father's death;
	How can we aid you with our kindred tears?
