<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 5><86%>
	At Pembroke, or at Ha'rford-west, in Wales.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 5><86%>
	Sir Walter Herbert, a renowned soldier,
	Sir Gilbert Talbot, Sir William Stanley,
	Oxford, redoubted Pembroke, Sir James Blunt,
	And Rice ap Thomas, with a valiant crew;
	And many other of great name and worth:
	And towards London do they bend their power,
	If by the way they be not fought withal.
