<SPEECH 1><ACT 2><SCENE 3><37%>
	Neighbours, God speed!
<SPEECH 2><ACT 2><SCENE 3><37%>
	Doth the news hold of good King Edward's death?
<SPEECH 3><ACT 2><SCENE 3><37%>
	Then, masters, look to see a troublous world.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 2><SCENE 3><37%>
	Woe to that land that's govern'd by a child!
<SPEECH 5><ACT 2><SCENE 3><37%>
	Stood the state so? no, no, good friends, God wot;
	For then this land was famously enrich'd
	With politic grave counsel; then the king
	Had virtuous uncles to protect his Grace.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 2><SCENE 3><37%>
	Better it were they all came by his father,
	Or by his father there were none at all;
	For emulation, who shall now be nearest,
	Will touch us all too near, if God prevent not.
	O! full of danger is the Duke of Gloucester!
	And the queen's sons and brothers haught and proud;
	And were they to be rul'd, and not to rule,
	This sickly land might solace as before.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 3><37%>
	When clouds are seen, wise men put on their cloaks;
	When great leaves fall, then winter is at hand;
	When the sun sets, who doth not look for night?
	Untimely storms make men expect a dearth.
	All may be well; but, if God sort it so,
	'Tis more than we deserve, or I expect.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 3><38%>
	Before the days of change, still is it so:
	By a divine instinct men's minds mistrust
	Ensuing danger; as, by proof, we see
	The waters swell before a boisterous storm.
	But leave it all to God. Whither away?
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 3><38%>
	And so was I: I'll bear you company.
