<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><23%>
	Where should this music be? i' th' air, or th' earth?
	It sounds no more;—and sure, it waits upon
	Some god o' th' island. Sitting on a bank,
	Weeping again the king my father's wrack,
	This music crept by me upon the waters,
	Allaying both their fury, and my passion,
	With its sweet air: thence I have follow'd it,—
	Or it hath drawn me rather,—but 'tis gone.
	No, it begins again.
	<ARIEL SINGS.>Full fathom five thy father lies;
	Of his bones are coral made
	Those are pearls that were his eyes:
	Nothing of him that doth fade,
	But doth suffer a sea-change
	Into something rich and strange.
	Sea-nymphs hourly ring his knell:
	Hark! now I hear them,—ding-dong, bell.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><23%>
	The ditty does remember my drown'd father.
	This is no mortal business, nor no sound
	That the earth owes:—I hear it now above me.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><24%>
	Most sure, the goddess
	On whom these airs attend!—Vouchsafe, my prayer
	May know if you remain upon this island;
	And that you will some good instruction give
	How I may bear me here: my prime request,
	Which I do last pronounce, is,—O you wonder!—
	If you be maid or no?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><24%>
	My language! heavens!—
	I am the best of them that speak this speech,
	Were I but where 'tis spoken.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><25%>
	A single thing, as I am now, that wonders
	To hear thee speak of Naples. He does hear me;
	And, that he does, I weep: myself am Naples,
	Who with mine eyes,—ne'er since at ebb,—beheld
	The king, my father wrack'd.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><25%>
	Yes, faith, and all his lords; the Duke of Milan,
	And his brave son being twain.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 2><26%>
	</STAGE DIR> O! if a virgin,
	And your affection not gone forth, I'll make you
	The Queen of Naples.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 2><26%>
	No, as I am a man.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 2><27%>
	No;
	I will resist such entertainment till
	Mine enemy has more power.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 2><28%>
	So they are:
	My spirits, as in a dream, are all bound up.
	My father's loss, the weakness which I feel,
	The wrack of all my friends, or this man's threats,
	To whom I am subdued, are but light to me,
	Might I but through my prison once a day
	Behold this maid: all corners else o' th' earth
	Let liberty make use of; space enough
	Have I in such a prison.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 3><SCENE 1><52%>
	There be some sports are painful, and their labour
	Delight in them sets off: some kinds of baseness
	Are nobly undergone, and most poor matters
	Point to rich ends. This my mean task
	Would be as heavy to me as odious; but
	The mistress which I serve quickens what's dead
	And makes my labours pleasures: O! she is
	Ten times more gentle than her father's crabbed,
	And he's compos'd of harshness. I must remove
	Some thousands of these logs and pile them up,
	Upon a sore injunction: my sweet mistress
	Weeps when she sees me work, and says such baseness
	Had never like executor. I forget:
	But these sweet thoughts do even refresh my labours,
	Most busiest when I do it.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 3><SCENE 1><53%>
	O most dear mistress,
	The sun will set, before I shall discharge
	What I must strive to do.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 3><SCENE 1><54%>
	No, precious creature:
	I had rather crack my sinews, break my back,
	Than you should such dishonour undergo,
	While I sit lazy by.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 3><SCENE 1><54%>
	No, noble mistress; 'tis fresh morning with me
	When you are by at night. I do beseech you—
	Chiefly that I might set it in my prayers—
	What is your name?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 3><SCENE 1><54%>
	Admir'd Miranda!
	Indeed, the top of admiration; worth
	What's dearest to the world! Full many a lady
	I have ey'd with best regard, and many a time
	The harmony of their tongues hath into bondage
	Brought my too diligent ear: for several virtues
	Have I lik'd several women; never any
	With so full soul but some defect in her
	Did quarrel with the noblest grace she ow'd,
	And put it to the foil: but you, O you!
	So perfect and so peerless, are created
	Of every creature's best.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 3><SCENE 1><55%>
	I am in my condition
	A prince, Miranda; I do think, a king;—
	I would not so!—and would no more endure
	This wooden slavery than to suffer
	The flesh-fly blow my mouth.—Hear my soul speak:—
	The very instant that I saw you did
	My heart fly to your service; there resides,
	To make me slave to it; and for your sake
	Am I this patient log-man.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 3><SCENE 1><56%>
	O heaven! O earth! bear witness to this sound,
	And crown what I profess with kind event
	If I speak true: if hollowly, invert
	What best is boded me to mischief! I,
	Beyond all limit of what else i' the world,
	Do love, prize, honour you.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 3><SCENE 1><56%>
	Wherefore weep you?
<SPEECH 19><ACT 3><SCENE 1><56%>
	My mistress, dearest;
	And I thus humble ever.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 3><SCENE 1><56%>
	Ay, with a heart as willing
	As bondage e'er of freedom: here's my hand.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 3><SCENE 1><57%>
	A thousand thousand!
<SPEECH 22><ACT 4><SCENE 1><71%>
	I do believe it
	Against an oracle.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 4><SCENE 1><71%>
	As I hope
	For quiet days, fair issue and long life,
	With such love as 'tis now, the murkiest den,
	The most opportune place, the strong'st sug gestion
	Our worser genius can, shall never melt
	Mine honour into lust, to take away
	The edge of that day's celebration
	When I shall think, or Phœbus' steeds are founder'd,
	Or Night kept chain'd below.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 4><SCENE 1><73%>
	I warrant you, sir;
	The white-cold virgin snow upon my heart
	Abates the ardour of my liver.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 4><SCENE 1><76%>
	This is a most majestic vision, and
	Harmonious charmingly: May I be bold
	To think these spirits?
<SPEECH 26><ACT 4><SCENE 1><76%>
	Let me live here ever:
	So rare a wonder'd father and a wise,
	Makes this place Paradise.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 4><SCENE 1><77%>
	This is strange: your father's in some passion
	That works him strongly.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	No, my dearest love,
	I would not for the world.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 5><SCENE 1><92%>
	Though the seas threaten, they are merciful:
	I have curs'd them without cause.
<SPEECH 30><ACT 5><SCENE 1><93%>
	Sir, she is mortal;
	But by immortal Providence she's mine;
	I chose her when I could not ask my father
	For his advice, nor thought I had one. She
	Is daughter to this famous Duke of Milan,
	Of whom so often I have heard renown,
	But never saw before; of whom I have
	Receiv'd a second life; and second father
	This lady makes him to me.
