<SPEECH 1><ACT 4><SCENE 4><73%>
	What would my lord and father?
<SPEECH 2><ACT 4><SCENE 4><73%>
	I shall observe him with all care and love.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 4><SCENE 4><73%>
	He is not there to-day; he dines in London.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 4><SCENE 4><73%>
	With Poins and other his continual followers.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 4><SCENE 4><75%>
	O my royal father!
<SPEECH 6><ACT 4><SCENE 4><75%>
	No, no; he cannot long hold out these pangs:
	The incessant care and labour of his mind
	Hath wrought the mure that should confine it in
	So thin, that life looks through and will break out.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 4><SCENE 4><76%>
	The river hath thrice flow'd, no ebb between;
	And the old folk, time's doting chronicles,
	Say it did so a little time before
	That our great-grandsire, Edward, sick'd and died.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 4><SCENE 5><76%>
	His eye is hollow, and he changes much.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 5><76%>
	I am here, brother, full of heaviness.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 5><77%>
	Let us withdraw into the other room.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 5><78%>
	Doth the king call?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 5><78%>
	We left the prince my brother here, my liege,
	Who undertook to sit and watch by you.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 5><SCENE 2><87%>
	Good morrow, cousin.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 5><SCENE 2><87%>
	Well, you must now speak Sir John Falstaff fair,
	Which swims against your stream of quality.
