<SPEECH 1><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	Many good morrows to your majesty!
<SPEECH 2><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	'Tis one o'clock, and past.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	We have, my liege.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 3><SCENE 1><45%>
	It is but as a body, yet, distemper'd,
	Which to his former strength may be restor'd
	With good advice and little medicine:
	My Lord Northumberland will soon be cool'd.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 3><SCENE 1><46%>
	There is a history in all men's lives,
	Figuring the nature of the times deceas'd;
	The which observ'd, a man may prophesy,
	With a near aim, of the main chance of things
	As yet not come to life, which in their seeds
	And weak leginnings lie intreasured.
	Such things become the hatch and brood of time;
	And by the necessary form of this
	King Richard might create a perfect guess
	That great Northumberland, then false to him,
	Would of that seed grow to a greater falseness,
	Which should not find a ground to root upon,
	Unless on you.
<SPEECH 6><ACT 3><SCENE 1><47%>
	It cannot be, my lord!
	Rumour doth double, like the voice and echo,
	The numbers of the fear'd. Please it your Grace
	To go to bed: upon my soul, my lord,
	The powers that you already have sent forth
	Shall bring this prize in very easily.
	To comfort you the more, I have receiv'd
	A certain instance that Glendower is dead.
	Your majesty hath been this fortnight ill,
	And these unseason'd hours perforce must add
	Unto your sickness.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 4><SCENE 4><72%>
	Both which we doubt not but your majesty
	Shall soon enjoy.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 4><SCENE 4><74%>
	My gracious lord, you look beyond him quite:
	The prince but studies his companions
	Like a strange tongue, wherein, to gain the language,
	'Tis needful that the most immodest word
	Be look'd upon, and learn'd; which once attain'd,
	Your highness knows, comes to no further use
	But to be known and hated. So, like gross terms,
	The prince will in the perfectness of time
	Cast off his followers; and their memory
	Shall as a pattern or a measure live,
	By which his Grace must mete the lives of others,
	Turning past evils to advantages.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 4><SCENE 4><75%>
	Be patient, princes: you do know these fits
	Are with his highness very ordinary:
	Stand from him, give him air; he'll straight be well.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 4><SCENE 4><76%>
	Speak lower, princes, for the king recovers.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 4><SCENE 5><76%>
	Call for the music in the other room.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 4><SCENE 5><76%>
	Less noise, less noise!
<SPEECH 13><ACT 4><SCENE 5><76%>
	Not so much noise, my lords. Sweet prince, speak low;
	The king your father is dispos'd to sleep.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 4><SCENE 5><77%>
	Will't please your Grace to go along with us?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 4><SCENE 5><78%>
	What would your majesty? How fares your Grace?
<SPEECH 16><ACT 4><SCENE 5><78%>
	This door is open; he is gone this way.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 4><SCENE 5><78%>
	When we withdrew, my liege, we left it here.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 4><SCENE 5><79%>
	My lord, I found the prince in the next room,
	Washing with kindly tears his gentle cheeks,
	With such a deep demeanour in great sorrow
	That tyranny, which never quaff'd but blood,
	Would, by beholding him, have wash'd his knife
	With gentle eye-drops. He is coming hither.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 4><SCENE 5><83%>
	'Tis call'd Jerusalem, my noble lord.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	How now, my Lord Chief Justice! whither away?
<SPEECH 21><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	Exceeding well: his cares are now all ended.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	He's walk'd the way of nature;
	And to our purposes he lives no more.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 5><SCENE 2><86%>
	Indeed I think the young king loves you not.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 5><SCENE 2><87%>
	Here come the heavy issue of dead Harry:
	O! that the living Harry had the temper
	Of him, the worst of these three gentlemen.
	How many nobles then should hold their places,
	That must strike sail to spirits of vile sort!
<SPEECH 25><ACT 5><SCENE 2><87%>
	We do remember; but our argument
	Is all too heavy to admit much talk.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 5><SCENE 2><87%>
	Here comes the prince.
