<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	The duke does greet you, general,
	And he requires your haste-post-haste appearance,
	Even on the instant.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	Something from Cyprus, as I may divine.
	It is a business of some heat; the galleys
	Have sent a dozen sequent messengers
	This very night at one another's heels,
	And many of the consuls, rais'd and met,
	Are at the duke's already. You have been hotly call'd for;
	When, being not at your lodging to be found,
	The senate hath sent about three several quests
	To search you out.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	Ancient, what makes he here?
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	I do not understand.
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	To who?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 2><7%>
	Here comes another troop to seek for you.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	Thanks, you the valiant of this war-like isle,
	That so approve the Moor. O! let the heavens
	Give him defence against the elements,
	For I have lost him on a dangerous sea.
<SPEECH 8><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	His bark is stoutly timber'd, and his pilot
	Of very expert and approv'd allowance;
	Therefore my hopes, not surfeited to death,
	Stand in bold cure.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 2><SCENE 1><22%>
	What noise?
<SPEECH 10><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	My hopes do shape him for the governor.
<SPEECH 11><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	I pray you, sir, go forth,
	And give us truth who 'tis that is arriv'd.
<SPEECH 12><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	Most fortunately: he hath achiev'd a maid
	That paragons description and wild fame;
	One that excels the quirks of blazoning pens,
	And in th' essential vesture of creation
	Does tire the ingener.
	How now! who has put in?
<SPEECH 13><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	He has had most favourable and happy speed:
	Tempests themselves, high seas, and howling winds,
	The gutter'd rocks, and congregated sands,
	Traitors ensteep'd to clog the guiltless keel,
	As having sense of beauty, do omit
	Their mortal natures, letting go safely by
	The divine Desdemona.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 2><SCENE 1><23%>
	She that I spake of, our great captain's captain,
	Left in the conduct of the bold Iago,
	Whose footing here anticipates our thoughts
	A se'nnight's speed. Great Jove, Othello guard,
	And swell his sail with thine own powerful breath,
	That he may bless this bay with his tall ship,
	Make love's quick pants in Desdemona's arms,
	Give renew'd fire to our extinc'ed spirits,
	And bring all Cyprus comfort!
	O! behold,
	The riches of the ship is come on shore.
	Ye men of Cyprus, let her have your knees.
	Hail to thee, lady! and the grace of heaven,
	Before, behind thee, and on every hand,
	Enwheel thee round!
<SPEECH 15><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	He is not yet arriv'd; nor know I aught
	But that he's well, and will be shortly here.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	The great contention of the sea and skies
	Parted our fellowship. But hark! a sail.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 2><SCENE 1><24%>
	See for the news!
	Good ancient, you are welcome:—<STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> welcome, mistress.
	Let it not gall your patience, good Iago,
	That I extend my manners; 'tis my breeding
	That gives me this bold show of courtesy.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	He speaks home, madam; you may relish him more in the soldier than in the scholar.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	'Tis truly so.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 2><SCENE 1><26%>
	Lo! where he comes.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 2><SCENE 3><31%>
	Iago hath direction what to do;
	But, notwithstanding, with my personal eye
	Will I look to 't.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 2><SCENE 3><31%>
	Welcome, Iago; we must to the watch.
<SPEECH 23><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	She's a most exquisite lady.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	Indeed, she is a most fresh and delicate creature.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	An inviting eye; and yet methinks right modest.
<SPEECH 26><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	She is indeed perfection.
<SPEECH 27><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	Not to-night, good Iago: I have very poor and unhappy brains for drinking: I could well wish courtesy would invent some other custom of entertainment.
<SPEECH 28><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	I have drunk but one cup to-night, and that was craftily qualified too, and, behold, what innovation it makes here: I am unfortunate in the infirmity, and dare not task my weakness with any more.
<SPEECH 29><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	Where are they?
<SPEECH 30><ACT 2><SCENE 3><32%>
	I'll do 't; but it dislikes me.
<SPEECH 31><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	'Fore God, they have given me a rouse already.
<SPEECH 32><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	'Fore God, an excellent song.
<SPEECH 33><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	Is your Englishman so expert in his drinking?
<SPEECH 34><ACT 2><SCENE 3><33%>
	To the health of our general!
<SPEECH 35><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	Why, this is a more exquisite song than the other.
<SPEECH 36><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	No; for I hold him to be unworthy of his place that does those things. Well, God's above all; and there be souls must be saved, and there be souls must not be saved.
<SPEECH 37><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	For mine own part,—no offence to the general, nor any man of quality,—I hope to be saved.
<SPEECH 38><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	Ay; but, by your leave, not before me; the lieutenant is to be saved before the ancient. Let's have no more of this; let's to our affairs. God forgive us our sins! Gentlemen, let's look to our business. Do not think, gentlemen, I am drunk: this is my ancient; this is my right hand, and this is my left hand. I am not drunk now; I can stand well enough, and speak well enough.
<SPEECH 39><ACT 2><SCENE 3><34%>
	Why, very well, then; you must not think then that I am drunk.
<SPEECH 40><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	You rogue! you rascal!
<SPEECH 41><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	A knave teach me my duty!
	I'll beat the knave into a twiggen bottle.
<SPEECH 42><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Dost thou prate, rogue?
<SPEECH 43><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Let me go, sir,
	Or I'll knock you o'er the mazzard.
<SPEECH 44><ACT 2><SCENE 3><35%>
	Drunk!
<SPEECH 45><ACT 2><SCENE 3><36%>
	I pray you, pardon me; I cannot speak.
<SPEECH 46><ACT 2><SCENE 3><39%>
	Ay; past all surgery.
<SPEECH 47><ACT 2><SCENE 3><39%>
	Reputation, reputation, reputation! O! I have lost my reputation. I have lost the immortal part of myself, and what remains is bestial. My reputation, Iago, my reputation!
<SPEECH 48><ACT 2><SCENE 3><39%>
	I will rather sue to be despised than to deceive so good a commander with so slight, so drunken, and so indiscreet an officer. Drunk! and speak parrot! and squabble, swagger, swear, and discourse fustian with one's own shadow! O thou invisible spirit of wine! if thou hast no name to be known by, let us call thee devil!
<SPEECH 49><ACT 2><SCENE 3><39%>
	I know not.
<SPEECH 50><ACT 2><SCENE 3><39%>
	I remember a mass of things, but nothing distinctly; a quarrel, but nothing wherefore. O God! that men should put an enemy in their mouths to steal away their brains; that we should, with joy, pleasance, revel, and applause, transform ourselves into beasts.
<SPEECH 51><ACT 2><SCENE 3><40%>
	It hath pleased the devil drunkenness to give place to the devil wrath; one unperfectness shows me another, to make me frankly despise myself.
<SPEECH 52><ACT 2><SCENE 3><40%>
	I will ask him for my place again; he shall tell me I am a drunkard! Had I as many mouths as Hydra, such an answer would stop them all. To be now a sensible man, by and by a fool, and presently a beast! O strange! Every inordinate cup is unblessed and the ingredient is a devil.
<SPEECH 53><ACT 2><SCENE 3><40%>
	I have well approved it, sir. I drunk!
<SPEECH 54><ACT 2><SCENE 3><40%>
	You advise me well.
<SPEECH 55><ACT 2><SCENE 3><41%>
	I think it freely; and betimes in the morning I will beseech the virtuous Desdemona to undertake for me. I am desperate of my fortunes if they check me here.
<SPEECH 56><ACT 2><SCENE 3><41%>
	Good night, honest Iago!
<SPEECH 57><ACT 3><SCENE 1><42%>
	Masters, play here, I will content your pains;
	Something that's brief; and bid 'Good morrow, general.'
<SPEECH 58><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	Dost thou hear, mine honest friend?
<SPEECH 59><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	Prithee, keep up thy quillets. There's a poor piece of gold for thee. If the gentlewoman that attends the general's wife be stirring, tell her there's one Cassio entreats her a little favour of speech: wilt thou do this?
<SPEECH 60><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	Do, good my friend.
	In happy time, Iago.
<SPEECH 61><ACT 3><SCENE 1><43%>
	Why, no; the day had broke
	Before we parted. I have made bold, Iago,
	To send in to your wife; my suit to her
	Is, that she will to virtuous Desdemona
	Procure me some access.
<SPEECH 62><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	I humbly thank you for 't.
	I never knew
	A Florentine more kind and honest.
<SPEECH 63><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	Yet, I beseech you,
	If you think fit, or that it may be done,
	Give me advantage of some brief discourse
	With Desdemona alone.
<SPEECH 64><ACT 3><SCENE 1><44%>
	I am much bound to you.
<SPEECH 65><ACT 3><SCENE 3><45%>
	Bounteous madam,
	Whatever shall become of Michael Cassio,
	He's never anything but your true servant.
<SPEECH 66><ACT 3><SCENE 3><45%>
	Ay, but, lady,
	That policy may either last so long,
	Or feed upon such nice and waterish diet,
	Or breed itself so out of circumstance,
	That, I being absent and my place supplied,
	My general will forget my love and service.
<SPEECH 67><ACT 3><SCENE 3><45%>
	Madam, I'll take my leave.
<SPEECH 68><ACT 3><SCENE 3><45%>
	Madam, not now; I am very ill at ease,
	Unfit for mine own purposes.
<SPEECH 69><ACT 3><SCENE 4><62%>
	Madam, my former suit: I do beseech you
	That by your virtuous means I may again
	Exist, and be a member of his love
	Whom I with all the office of my heart
	Entirely honour; I would not be delay'd.
	If my offence be of such mortal kind
	That nor my service past, nor present sorrows,
	Nor purpos'd merit in futurity,
	Can ransom me into his love again,
	But to know so must be my benefit;
	So shall I clothe me in a forc'd content,
	And shut myself up in some other course
	To fortune's alms.
<SPEECH 70><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	I humbly thank your ladyship.
<SPEECH 71><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	What make you from home?
	How is it with you, my most fair Bianca?
	I' faith, sweet love, I was coming to your house.
<SPEECH 72><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	Pardon me, Bianca,
	I have this while with leaden thoughts been press'd,
	But I shall, in a more continuate time,
	Strike off this score of absence. Sweet Bianca.
	Take me this work out.
<SPEECH 73><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	Go to, woman!
	Throw your vile guesses in the devil's teeth,
	From whence you have them. You are jealous now
	That this is from some mistress, some remembrance:
	No, in good troth, Bianca.
<SPEECH 74><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	I know not, sweet; I found it in my chamber.
	I like the work well; ere it be demanded,—
	As like enough it will,—I'd have it copied;
	Take it and do 't; and leave me for this time.
<SPEECH 75><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	I do attend here on the general,
	And think it no addition nor my wish
	To have him see me woman'd.
<SPEECH 76><ACT 3><SCENE 4><64%>
	Not that I love you not.
<SPEECH 77><ACT 3><SCENE 4><65%>
	'Tis but a little way that I can bring you,
	For I attend here; but I'll see you soon.
<SPEECH 78><ACT 4><SCENE 1><66%>
	What's the matter?
<SPEECH 79><ACT 4><SCENE 1><66%>
	Rub him about the temples.
<SPEECH 80><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	The worser that you give me the addition
	Whose want even kills me.
<SPEECH 81><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	Alas! poor caitiff!
<SPEECH 82><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	Alas! poor rogue, I think, i' faith, she loves me.
<SPEECH 83><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	Ha, ha, ha!
<SPEECH 84><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	I marry her! what? a customer? I prithee, bear some charity to my wit; do not think it so unwholesome. Ha, ha, ha!
<SPEECH 85><ACT 4><SCENE 1><68%>
	Prithee, say true.
<SPEECH 86><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	This is the monkey's own giving out: she is persuaded I will marry her, out of her own love and flattery, not out of my promise.
<SPEECH 87><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	She was here even now; she haunts me in every place. I was the other day talking on the sea bank with certain Venetians, and thither come this bauble, and, by this hand, she falls me thus about my neck;—
<SPEECH 88><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	So hangs and lolls and weeps upon me; so hales and pulls me; ha, ha, ha!
<SPEECH 89><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	Well, I must leave her company.
<SPEECH 90><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	'Tis such another fitchew! marry, a perfumed one.
	What do you mean by this haunting of me?
<SPEECH 91><ACT 4><SCENE 1><69%>
	How now, my sweet Bianca! how now, how now!
<SPEECH 92><ACT 4><SCENE 1><70%>
	Faith, I must; she'll rail in the street else.
<SPEECH 93><ACT 4><SCENE 1><70%>
	Faith, I intend so.
<SPEECH 94><ACT 4><SCENE 1><70%>
	Prithee, come; will you?
<SPEECH 95><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	That thrust had been mine enemy indeed
	But that my coat is better than thou know'st;
	I will make proof of thine.
<SPEECH 96><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	I am maim'd for ever. Help, ho! murder! murder!
<SPEECH 97><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	O, help, ho! light! a surgeon!
<SPEECH 98><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	What ho! no watch? no passage? murder! murder!
<SPEECH 99><ACT 5><SCENE 1><85%>
	O, help!
<SPEECH 100><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Here, here! for heaven's sake, help me.
<SPEECH 101><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	Iago? O! I am spoil'd, undone by villains!
	Give me some help.
<SPEECH 102><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	I think that one of them is hereabout,
	And cannot make away.
<SPEECH 103><ACT 5><SCENE 1><86%>
	That's one of them.
<SPEECH 104><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	My leg is cut in two.
<SPEECH 105><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	No.
<SPEECH 106><ACT 5><SCENE 1><87%>
	None in the world; nor do I know the man.
<SPEECH 107><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	Dear general, I never gave you cause.
<SPEECH 108><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	Most heathenish and most gross!
<SPEECH 109><ACT 5><SCENE 2><98%>
	I found it in my chamber;
	And he himself confess'd but even now
	That there he dropp'd it for a special purpose
	Which wrought to his desire.
<SPEECH 110><ACT 5><SCENE 2><99%>
	There is besides in Roderigo's letter
	How he upbraids Iago that he made him
	Brave me upon the watch; whereon it came
	That I was cast: and even but now he spake,
	After long seeming dead, Iago hurt him,
	Iago set him on.
<SPEECH 111><ACT 5><SCENE 2><100%>
	This did I fear, but thought he had no weapon;
	For he was great of heart.
