<SPEECH 1><ACT 1><SCENE 3><9%>
	There is no composition in these news
	That gives them credit.
<SPEECH 2><ACT 1><SCENE 3><9%>
	And mine, a hundred and forty.
<SPEECH 3><ACT 1><SCENE 3><9%>
	Nay, it is possible enough to judgment:
	I do not so secure me in the error,
	But the main article I do approve
	In fearful sense.
<SPEECH 4><ACT 1><SCENE 3><9%>
	Now, what's the business?
<SPEECH 5><ACT 1><SCENE 3><10%>
	How say you by this change?
<SPEECH 6><ACT 1><SCENE 3><10%>
	Nay, in all confidence, he's not for Rhodes.
<SPEECH 7><ACT 1><SCENE 3><10%>
	'Tis certain then, for Cyprus.
	Marcus Luccicos, is not he in town?
<SPEECH 8><ACT 1><SCENE 3><10%>
	Write from us to him; post-post-haste dispatch.
<SPEECH 9><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	Valiant Othello, we must straight employ you
	Against the general enemy Ottoman.
	</STAGE DIR> I did not see you; welcome, gentle signior;
	We lack'd your counsel and your help to-night.
<SPEECH 10><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	Why, what's the matter?
<SPEECH 11><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	Dead?
<SPEECH 12><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	Whoe'er he be that in this foul proceeding
	Hath thus beguil'd your daughter of herself
	And you of her, the bloody book of law
	You shall yourself read in the bitter letter
	After your own sense; yea, though our proper son
	Stood in your action.
<SPEECH 13><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	We are very sorry for it.
<SPEECH 14><ACT 1><SCENE 3><11%>
	</STAGE DIR> What, in your own part, can you say to this?
<SPEECH 15><ACT 1><SCENE 3><12%>
	To vouch this, is no proof,
	Without more certain and more overt test
	Than these thin habits and poor likelihoods
	Of modern seeming do prefer against him.
<SPEECH 16><ACT 1><SCENE 3><13%>
	Fetch Desdemona hither.
<SPEECH 17><ACT 1><SCENE 3><13%>
	Say it, Othello.
<SPEECH 18><ACT 1><SCENE 3><14%>
	I think this tale would win my daughter too.
	Good Brabantio,
	Take up this mangled matter at the best;
	Men do their broken weapons rather use
	Than their bare hands.
<SPEECH 19><ACT 1><SCENE 3><15%>
	Let me speak like yourself and lay a sentence,
	Which as a grize or step, may help these lovers
	Into your favour.
	When remedies are past, the griefs are ended
	By seeing the worst, which late on hopes depended.
	To mourn a mischief that is past and gone
	Is the next way to draw new mischief on.
	What cannot be preserv'd when Fortune takes,
	Patience her injury a mockery makes.
	The robb'd that smiles steals something from the thief;
	He robs himself that spends a bootless grief.
<SPEECH 20><ACT 1><SCENE 3><16%>
	The Turk with a most mighty preparation makes for Cyprus. Othello, the fortitude of the place is best known to you; and though we have there a substitute of most allowed sufficiency, yet opinion, a sovereign mistress of effects, throws a more safer voice on you: you must therefore be content to slubber the gloss of your new fortunes with this more stubborn and boisterous expedition.
<SPEECH 21><ACT 1><SCENE 3><16%>
	If you please,
	Be 't at her father's.
<SPEECH 22><ACT 1><SCENE 3><16%>
	What would you, Desdemona?
<SPEECH 23><ACT 1><SCENE 3><17%>
	Be it as you shall privately determine,
	Either for her stay or going. The affair cries haste,
	And speed must answer it.
<SPEECH 24><ACT 1><SCENE 3><17%>
	At nine i' the morning here we'll meet again.
	Othello, leave some officer behind,
	And he shall our commission bring to you;
	With such things else of quality and respect
	As doth import you.
<SPEECH 25><ACT 1><SCENE 3><17%>
	Let it be so.
	Good night to every one. <STAGE DIR>
	</STAGE DIR> And, noble signior,
	If virtue no delighted beauty lack,
	Your son-in-law is far more fair than black.
